<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE report SYSTEM "DTD/report.dtd">
<report id="154153" pubid="1496">
    <title>Surnames beginning 'L'</title>
    <subtitle/>
    <section id="s1">
        <head>Surnames beginning 'L'</head>
        
        <table id="t1">
            <tr>
                <td>Lacey, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lacey</emph><br/>Captain in the Blue regiment, London
                    Auxiliaries (Colonel George Langham, junior) in Oct. 1646.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Nagel, ‘London militia’, 317; Marshall, <emph type="i"
                        >Essex funeral</emph>, 11.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lacey, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Lacey</emph><br/>In summer 1642 he became a captain in
                    Holles’s short-lived regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army. Like most of
                    his fellow-officers and the regiment as a whole, little is heard of him after
                    their shattering defeat at Brentford in Nov. 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 37.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lacy [Lacey], -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Lacy [Lacey]</emph><br/>Captain. Lacy was
                    captain of a company evidently raised in Dorset in May 1643, probably as part of
                    foot regiment of Sir Walter Erle. In May Lacy took 200 men from Poole to take
                    Wareham. Is this Barrett Lacy, lieutenant-colonel, or Captain Lacy in the
                    Portland garrison in 1649? [See below.]<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 5.513.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lacy, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b"> Lacy</emph><br/>Captain. An officer
                    serving in the Portland garrison, evidently part of the larger Weymouth
                    garrison, reduced in an economy measure and his men passed to Captain Channing,
                    21 Dec. 1648.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset
                        Standing Committee</emph>, 486, 492; Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing
                        Committee</emph>, 240.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lacy, Barrett</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Barrett Lacy</emph><br/>Lieutenant-Colonel in 1646-8, commanding
                    at Wareham. [See above.]<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Bayley, <emph
                        type="i">Civil War in Dorset</emph>, 246, 307-8, 326, 335-6.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lacy, Barrett</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Barrett Lacy</emph><br/>Lieutenant-Colonel. Commanded at Wareham, and
                    raised a company at Portland, summer 1648.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, xxxi, xxxii,
                        527.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Laidman, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Laidman</emph><br/>Of Leeds and Kirkstall, Yorkshire (W.
                    Riding). Cornet in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper,
                    ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 113 [citing inter alia BL, Add Mss. 21,417, f. 7;
                    21,427, ff. 190, 203, 211].<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Laithropp, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Laithropp</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Mark Coe’s company in
                    the Southwark auxiliaries regiment (Colonel James Houblon) on 16 Apr.
                        1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/121A, Part 4, ff.
                        572r.-575r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Southwark</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lambe, Cornelius</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Cornelius Lambe</emph> (died 1644)<br/>Captain in Colonel Ralph
                    Weldon’s regiment of Kentish foot from 30 Nov. 1643 until his death at the siege
                    of Donnington Castle on 2 Aug. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 152.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association);
                    Kent</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lambe, Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Lambe</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Robert Patterson’s, later
                    Edward Horsman’s troop in Oliver Cromwell’s regiment of horse in the Eastern
                    Association Army in 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.15.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lambert [Lambart], John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lambert</emph> <emph type="b">[Lambart] </emph>(baptised
                    1619, died 1684)<br/>Of Calton township, Kirkby Malhamdale, Yorkshire (W.
                    Riding). Linked by his marriage to Frances, daughter of Sir William Lister of
                    Thornton-in-Craven, to the Fairfaxes.<br/>By Apr. 1643 a colonel of foot and by
                    Jan. 1644 he had a regiment of horse with which he went to Nantwich. He was an
                    active commander in the northern campaigns, securing the western part of the
                    clothing districts in early 1644 and playing a notable part at Marston
                    Moor.<br/>By 1645 he was Commissary-General of the Northern Army, and was
                    temporarily in charge of the Northern Army when Sir Thomas Fairfax went south
                    and before the appointment of Poyntz.<br/>With the war ended in the north, in
                    Jan. 1646 Lambert given Montague’s regiment of foot (after the latter resigned
                    in Oct. 1645) in the New Model Army and served in the closing stages of the
                    campaign in south-west England.<br/>Prominent in army politics, in summer 1647
                    he was sent north to restore order in and to command the Northern Army. He
                    played an important part in the second civil war, ensuring the security of
                    Yorkshire, containing Scottish-royalist forces in Cumberland and Lancashire and,
                    having joined Cromwell, prominent in the battle and wider campaign of Preston.
                    In 1650-51 was Major-General and second-in-command to Cromwell in the invasion
                    of Scotland, providing the tactics and leading the attack and victory at Dunbar
                    and also leading the assault at Inverkeithing in summer 1651 which enabled
                    Cromwell to throw most of his army across the Firth of Forth. His further
                    activity in pursuit of the Scottish-royalists and in the battle and wider
                    campaign of Worcester confirmed his military skill.<br/>Political advance
                    followed and, as a key supporter of Oliver Cromwell and an architect of the
                    Protectorate, his standing was probably second only to Cromwell for much of the
                    Protectorate, until he lost his military and political offices – though not his
                    by now extensive properties – in spring 1657 following his opposition to
                    kingship and to the new oath of allegiance. He regained senior military command
                    and some political standing under the restored Rump in 1659 and played the
                    leading role in crushing the Booth Rising in Cheshire, but he was on the losing
                    side in the brief power struggle of winter 1659-60, failed to prevent Monck
                    moving south and taking control of events, was already under arrest at the
                    Restoration and spent the rest of his life in prison.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Jones, ‘War in the
                    North’, 388; D Farr, <emph type="i">John Lambert: Parliamentary Soldier and
                        Cromwellian Major-General, 1619-1684 </emph>(2003); Jones, ‘War in the
                    North’, 388; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 112.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire; Northern Army (Poyntz); New Model
                        Army; Northern Army (Lambert)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lampart, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Lampart</emph><br/>Captain-Lieutenant of foot in Sir
                    Thomas Myddelton’s Regt, as confirmed by Myddelton’s warrant ordering payment of
                    &#xa3;5 to him in that capacity, endorsed with his signed acquittance dated 5
                    Aug. 1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346, no.
                        228.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North
                    Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lancaster, Nathaniel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Nathaniel Lancaster</emph><br/>Born in 1601 at Rainhill,
                    Lancashire, like several of his family he entered the ministry, holding several
                    livings in north Cheshire and Chester before, in 1638, becoming rector of
                    Tarplorley in Cheshire. To the dismay of some of his parishioners, he enforced
                    low church practices there. He supported the parliamentarian cause from the
                    outbreak of civil war, quickly identified by Cheshire royalists as an enemy.
                    From 1644 to 1646 he was chaplain and army clerk to Sir William Brereton.
                    However, as a Presbyterian his relations with Brereton probably became strained,
                    his account of the siege of Chester, <emph type="i">A Most Exact Declaration of
                        Chester’s Enlargement</emph>, downplayed Brereton’s role and in 1646 he was
                    replaced as army chaplain by the Independent Samuel Eaton.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Dore, <emph type="i"
                        >Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 395; TNA, SP28/224, ff. 32-3.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lander, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lander</emph><br/>By late summer 1644, Cornet in Otway’s troop
                    in William Purefoy’s regiment of horse.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s a</emph><emph type="i">rmy</emph>,
                        122.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lane, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lane</emph><br/>Merchant involved in colonial trade.<br/>A
                    godly activist in his parish of All Hallows Bread Street in 1642, and an active
                    supporter of parliament in the war, contributing horses for the cavalry and
                    sitting on the City’s gunpowder committee. In 1645-6 a Presbyterian
                    petitioner.<br/>Major in the Green regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel Owen
                    Rowe) in Oct. 1646, promoted its Lieutenant-Colonel (under Colonel Matthew
                    Sheppard) by the Presbyterian militia committee in 1647, and put out later that
                        year.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Marshall, <emph type="i"
                        >Essex</emph>, 12; Nagel, ‘London militia’, 317-8; Lindley, <emph type="i"
                        >Popular politics</emph>, 68, 70, 72, 73, 139, 140, 143, 144, 206, 207, 231,
                    377, 378; <emph type="i">A paire of spectacles for the Citie</emph> (1648),
                        9.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lanford, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lanford</emph><br/>Lieutenant in the earl of Essex’s own
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 26.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langden, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Langden</emph><br/>Captain in Sir William Springate’s
                    regiment of Kentish foot by Sept. 1643, and serving there until its disbandment
                    early the next year.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 120.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Kent; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langford, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Langford</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Viscount Saye and Sele’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 30.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langford, George </td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Langford</emph><br/>Ensign in Thomas Grantham’s regiment
                    of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 41.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langham, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Langham</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel Randall Mainwaring’s Red
                    regiment of foot at Olney, Bedfordshire, at the time of a skirmish there in Nov.
                    1643. Possibly George Langham, junior.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    George Paine, <emph type="i">A true relation of all the skirmishes between our
                        forces and the </emph><emph type="i">Cavaliers at Owlny </emph>(1643),
                        3.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Bedfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langham, George, junior</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Langham, </emph><emph type="b">junior</emph><br/>Colonel.
                    Eldest son of George Langham senior and his wife, Thomazin, daughter of Richard
                    Scales of London. Possibly the common councilman post-1642 and radical
                    identified by Lindley (rather than his father).<br/>Possibly Captain Langham of
                    Randall Mainwaring’s Red regiment of foot, present at the skirmish in Olney,
                    Bedfordshire, in Nov. 1643.<br/>Admitted to the Company of the Artillery Garden
                    (now the Honourable Artillery Company). Colonel of the Blue regiment (London
                    Auxiliaries) by 22 Oct. 1646; purged from his command by the Presbyterian
                    militia committee in summer 1647, described by the New Model Army’s informants
                    as ‘a man of approved fidelitie in times of greatest difficulty’; replaced with
                    the Army’s reported enemy Thomas Clarke.<br/>Sat on the court which tried the
                    duke of Hamilton and others for treason, 1649.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Nagel, ‘London militia’, 269, 317; <emph type="i">Vis.
                        London 1633-5</emph>, 2.44; <emph type="i"/>Lindley, <emph type="i">Popular
                        politics</emph>, 209; <emph type="i">Clarke Papers</emph>, 1.155; Brenner,
                        <emph type="i">Merchants</emph>, 548.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langham, George, senior</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Langham, </emph><emph type="b">senior</emph><br/>Captain in the militia, and presumably the George Langham
                    who was briefly colonel of a London-raised and generally London-based regiment
                    of foot attached to the earl of Essex’s Army from Nov. 1642 onwards. If so,
                    however, his service under Essex was brief, for Langham drew up his will in Mar.
                    1643 and was dead by Dec. 1644, probably earlier as command of his regiment
                    passed to his former Lieutenant-Colonel, Samuel Carleton, in summer 1643. A
                    Merchant Taylor.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Nagel, ‘London militia’,
                    57, 79n; TNA, PROB11/192/109.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >London; Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langham, Samuel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Samuel Langham </emph><br/>Lieutenant serving with Sir William
                    Waller’s Army by 3 Nov. 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring,
                        <emph type="i">Waller’s Army,</emph> 176.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langley, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Langley</emph><br/>At its muster in Nov. 1643, captain in
                    Colonel Thomas Honeywood’s regiment of foot formed from the Essex militia, part
                    of the Eastern Association Army that contributed to the siege of Reading in
                    spring 1643, the siege of Greenland House in summer 1644 and probably to some
                    other actions in which the Army was involved.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                        1.32.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langley, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Langley</emph><br/>By spring 1645 lieutenant in the
                    company of Lieutenant-Colonel Poynes in William Jephson’s regiment of
                        foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 71.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Hampshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langley, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Langley</emph><br/>Cornet in the troop formerly commanded
                    by Captain John Juxon and by early 1644 de facto under Lieutenant Charteris in
                    Edmund Harvey’s regiment of London horse, paid for 28 days’ service on 25 May
                        1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/131, f. 19r.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langridge, Anthony</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Anthony Langridge </emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir William Waller’s
                    regiment of foot by the time it was disbanded in Apr. 1645.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        155.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langrish, Hercules</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Hercules Langrish</emph><br/>Son of Hercules Langrish and his
                    wife Olymphas du Plessis; brother of Lucullus Langrish.<br/>In the 1642 list of
                    the earl of Essex’s Army, he is shown as captain of a troop of horse. Captain in
                    George Melve’s regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army by early Mar.
                    1643, perhaps succeeding Thomas Ayloffe, until at least late June 1643. By late
                    July Langrish had transferred as captain in John Middleton’s regiment of
                        dragoons.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/5/205, 206,
                    SP28/7/320, 452, SP28/9/216; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>,
                        54.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Langton, Christopher</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Christopher Langton</emph><br/>Langton was a lieutenant in Lord
                    Brooke’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642, but on 28 Nov. he
                    was ordered to Yorkshire. He apparently became a captain and may have served as
                    Major of John Holman’s regiment of foot. From 14 May 1644 to 31 July 1645
                    Langton was lieutenant-colonel of William White’s new regiment of foot,
                    commanding the regiment during his Colonel’s absences in London as Lord
                    Fairfax’s agent.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the
                    North’, 388; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 35.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Yorkshire; Northern Army
                        (Fairfax)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Larkin, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Larkin</emph><br/>Captain in Valentine Walton’s regiment of
                    foot in the Eastern Association Army (commanded by James Hobart from spring
                    1645). He is possibly the Captain Larkin who later served in Okey’s New Model
                    Army dragoon regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.105.<br/><emph type="b"
                    >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New
                        Model Army?</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lascelles, Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Lascelles</emph> <emph type="b"/>(1612-1667)<br/>Of Stank
                    Hall, Winton township, Sigston parish and of Northallerton, both in Yorkshire
                    (North Riding), son of William Lascelles and his wife Anne Daniel. A JP from 1640.
                    He married the godly Frances, daughter of Sir William St Quintin of Harpham,
                    baronet.<br/>Lascelles was captain of foot in the Hull garrison by Nov. 1642,
                    and the following month he was at the Fairfaxes’ base at Seby. He then fought at
                    Guisborough and Yarm, suggesting that he was then in Francis Boynton’s regiment
                    of foot. However, he soon moved to John Gifford’s regiment of foot, going on to
                    become its lieutenant-colonel and (in June 1644) its Colonel. He was also
                    captain of a troop of horse, 1644-5.<br/>In winter 1643-4 Lascelles fought with
                    Sir John Meldrum in the Isle of Axholme, Lincolnshire, and was captured but soon
                    released. He was at the siege of York, the battle of Marston Moor and the siege
                    of Helmsley Castle (which surrendered in Nov. 1644). In 1645 he was at the
                    sieges of Bolton Castle, Pontefract and Scarborough. Lascelles was a member of
                    every North Riding committee from 24 Feb. 1643; in June 1645 he was added to the
                    Northern Association committee for the North Riding; shortly after he was
                    elected Recruiter MP for Thirsk. He fled to the army in 1647 and resumed his
                    military career, taking part in the second siege of Pontefract. He was appointed
                    a judge for the king’s trial in 1649, but refused to sign the death warrant. He
                    was MP for the North Riding in the Nominated Asssembly and the first and second
                    Protectorate Parliaments. In 1660 he was elected to the Convention Parliament as
                    MP for Northallerton, but was discharged and declared incapable of holding
                    public office and in 1662 was suspected of conspiring against the
                        crown.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                    388-9; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 95; <emph type="i">HoP: The
                        Commons, 1660-1690</emph>, 2.711; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660
                        </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire; Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army (Lambert)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lascelles, Peregrine</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Peregrine Lascelles</emph><emph type="b"/>(1619-1658)<br/>Of
                    Stank Hall, Winton township, Sigston parish and later Lythe, Yorkshire (N.
                    Riding), son of William Lascelles and his wife Anne Daniel and younger brother
                    of Francis Lascelles.<br/>From 20 Mar. 1643 to 6 June 1644 he was captain in
                    John Gifford’s regiment of foot, promoted in June 1644 to lieutenant-colonel in
                    the same regiment now under the command of his brother Francis, and serving with
                    it until its disbandment in Jan. 1646.<br/>After 1649 he was politically
                    prominent because of his brother’s parliamentary position.<br/>He was
                    commissioned Major in a regiment of foot in the Yorkshire militia, 10 Apr.
                        1650.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 389;
                    Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 95; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>,
                        506.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire; Northern
                        Army (Poyntz)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lascelles, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Lascelles</emph> (born 1617)<br/>Of Eryholme, Yorkshire
                    (North Riding), son of William Lascelles and his wife Anne Daniel and brother of
                    Francis, Peregrine and Thomas Lascelles.<br/>Either he or Thomas received a
                    company of foot in the Hull garrison on 6 July 1643.<br/>If he continued in
                    parliament’s service, presumably he was in regiment of foot of Gifford/Francis
                        Lascelles.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                        389.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lascelles, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lascelles</emph><br/>Of Stank Hall, Winton township,
                    Sigston parish, Yorkshire (West Riding), son of William Lascelles and his wife
                    Anne Daniel and brother of Francis, Peregrine and Robert Lascelles. He was a
                    captain and also a JP.<br/>Either he or Robert received a company of foot in the
                    Hull garrison on 6 July 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper,
                    ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 95; Jones, ‘War in the North’, 389.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lathome, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lathome</emph><br/>Commissioned captain in Henry Brooke’s
                    Cheshire militia regiment of foot, 22 Aug. 1650.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 509.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Latimer, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Latimer</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Captain Richard Benson’s
                    Company of firelocks in William Bampfield’s regiment of foot in Lord Wharton’s
                    Army raised for service in Ireland in 1642. Instead, he went with Bampfield’s
                    regiment as lieutenant into the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 70,
                        40.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Laugharne, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Laugharne</emph><br/>Fourth son of John Laugharne
                    (baptised 1587, died after 1644) of St Bride’s, Pembrokshire, and his wife Janet
                    Owen, daughter of Sir Hugh Owen of Orielton, Castlemartin, Pembrokshire He was a
                    younger brother of Rowland Laugharne. He was also linked by kinship and service
                    to the earls of Essex and to the Merrick family. Sir John Merrick’s father
                    married Thomas’s father’s sister.<br/>In 1642 Laugharne was captain in his
                    cousin Sir John Merrick’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/>By
                    Feb. or Mar. 1644 Laugharne was a Major, serving under his brother Rowland who
                    was colonel and commander of the forces which took much of Pembrokshire from the
                    royalists. He probably remained fighting under his brother in Wales
                    1644-6.<br/>Like his brother, he changed his allegiance during the second civil
                    war and, by then a lieutenant-Colonel fighting against New Model troops, Thomas
                    Laugharne was killed at the battle of St Fagans on 8 May 1648.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 28;
                    TNA, SP28/2b/505; Phillips, <emph type="i">Wales</emph>, 147, 152, 369; Meyrick,
                        <emph type="i">Welsh visitations</emph>, 1.73, 137; <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph> [biography of Rowland Laugharne].<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Pembrokeshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Laughton, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Laughton</emph><br/>Captain. Captain of a company of the
                    Bristol Trained Bands by 10 Oct. 1642. At some point, between 27 Feb. and 29
                    Apr. 1643, he gave up command of his company to go into the field.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 6.603-4.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Bristol</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lawe, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lawe</emph><br/>In Feb. 1645, ensign in Captain Van der
                    Voone’s company in Sir Samuel Luke’s Newport Pagnell-based regiment of
                        foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        a</emph><emph type="i">rmy</emph>, 95.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Bedfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lawrance, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lawrance</emph><br/>Captain in the Southwark Trained Bands
                    regiment (Colonel John Hardwicke) in later 1643; Major of the same regiment on
                    22 Oct. 1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/131, Part 13, f.
                    5r.; Nagel, ‘London militia’, 317; Marshall, <emph type="i">Essex
                    funeral</emph>, 12.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Southwark</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lawrence, Adams [Adam]</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Adams [Adam] Lawrence </emph>(baptised 1622, died
                    1648).<br/>Gentleman, fourth child and only son of Richard Lawrence (died 1626)
                    and his wife Mary Adams (died 1644), of Linton, Cambridgeshire, baptised at
                    Linton, 25 Feb. 1622 (Adams is the form used in the biography which prefaces his
                    daughter’s published diary). In 1641 he married Elizabeth Cutts, daughter of
                    Henry Cutts, of Clare, Suffolk, ‘a Person learn’d in the Law, yet a great
                    Peace-Maker amongst his neighbours, and a zealous Promoter of the Interest of
                    the Gospel’ (<emph type="i">Mrs. Elizabeth Bury</emph>, 1).<br/>Captain of a
                    troop of horse in Oliver Cromwell’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association
                    Army by autumn 1643: the tapster at the Red Lyon in Cambridge was paid &#xa3;5
                    8s 2d for Lawrence’s troopers from 13 Oct. 1643 to 12 Feb. 1644. In Feb. 1645
                    his troop consisted of 95 men. He continued as its captain when the troop was
                    one of those which went into Thomas Fairfax’s regiment of horse in the New Model
                    Army.<br/>Lawrence was killed on 13 June 1648 in an unsuccessful assault during
                    the siege of Colchester.<br/>The Lawrence family had in the past included
                    members of the Family of Love. However, his friend Richard Baxter described him
                    as the only ‘orthodox’ member of Cromwell’s regiment. In 1644 it was claimed
                    before the committee for scandalous ministers that Lawrence had found 200 musket
                    balls in Barham Hall, Cambridgeshire, which were said to have belonged to the
                    fled minister.<br/>Lawrence’s widow married Nathaniel Bradshaw, the minister of
                    Willingham, Cambridgeshire (and very possibly also the officer of that name in
                    Cromwell’s regiment), who was ejected at the Restoration. The spiritual diary of
                    his Presbyterian daughter, Elizabeth Bury, was published with her funeral
                    sermon, which was delivered by Isaac Watts: there her father was described as ‘a
                    very graceful Person, of good character, and great Integrity’ (<emph type="i"
                        >Mrs. Elizabeth Bury</emph>, 1).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Firth
                    &amp; Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental history</emph>, 11, 16, 58, 62, 67; [IG:
                    personal info of R.L. Stevens of Linton]; <emph type="i"
                        >An account of the life and death of Mrs. Elizabeth Bury, who died, May the
                        11th 1720. Aged 76. Chiefly collected out of her own diary</emph> (Bristol,
                    1721), 1-3; M. Spufford, ed., <emph
                        type="i">The world of rural dissenters</emph>, <emph type="i"
                        >1520-1725</emph> (1995), 25-26; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model
                        </emph><emph type="i">Army</emph>, I, 51, 61, 72, 82, 92, 105.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association; New Model
                        Army</emph></td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
                <td>Lawrence [Lawrance], Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Lawrence [Lawrance]</emph><br/>Captain of company in
                    Colonel Robert Butler’s regiment of foot, Wareham garrison: dates certain (from
                    his lieutenant’s arrears claim), 25 Sept. 1644-13 Apr. 1646. On 20 Oct. 1646,
                    granted farm of Winterbourne Steepleton, sequestered from marquess of
                    Winchester, for one whole year; on 22 Dec. 1647 granted south farm of same; on
                    22 May 1648 fined for obstructing tenancy of north farm; on 14 June 1648 arrest
                    ordered for disobeying committee’s orders; on 14 Dec. 1648 the committee ordered
                    Lawrence’s royalist uncle to explain why he has not paid off the debts for which
                    Lawrence was bound, and for which the uncle’s sequestration was taken
                        off.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset
                        Standing Committee</emph>,<emph type="i"/>42, 34, 306, 392, 403,
                        479.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lawrence, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lawrence</emph><br/>In summer 1642 he became a lieutenant
                    in Holles’s short-lived regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army. Lieutenant in Captain Nicholas
                    Devereux’s company in John Middleton’s regiment of dragoons (pay warrant: 10
                    Nov. 1642) in the earl of Essex’s Army. Like most
                    of his fellow-officers and the regiment as a whole, little is heard of him after
                    their shattering defeat at Brentford in Nov. 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 37; TNA, SP28/3b/305.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lawson, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lawson </emph>(c. 1615-1665)<br/>Of Scarborough, Yorkshire
                    (North Riding) and already an active mariner by the time civil war broke out,
                    though very little is known about his origins, family background or early
                    life.<br/>He quit Scarborough when Cholmley defected to the king in 1643 and
                    moved to parliamentarian Hull, employing and commanding ships both to get
                    supplies into the town and to blockade and attack royalist vessels serving
                    Scarborough. He returned to his home town after the royalists surrendered in
                    1645 and exercised considerable power there, in spring 1646 commissioned as
                    captain in command of a 100-strong garrison. He held that position for around
                    five years, briefly withdrawing in 1648 when the governor of Scarborough again
                    defected to the king before being quickly subdued.<br/>Lawson’s real military
                    contribution and the basis of his fame, however, lie in his achievements not as
                    an officer of land forces but as a naval commander and admiral during the 1650s
                    and first half of the 1660s. In that capacity he served both the republican and
                    Protectoral regimes and the restored monarchy with considerable distinction,
                    down to his death in 1665 from wounds sustained in a naval battle off Lowestoft
                    during the second Anglo-Dutch war.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Oxford DNB</emph><emph type="i">.</emph><br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lawson, Sir Wilfred, first baronet</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir Wilfred Lawson, </emph><emph type="b">first</emph><emph
                        type="b"/> <emph type="b">baronet </emph>(c. 1610-1688)<br/>Son of William
                    Lawson of Hesket and nephew of Sir Wilfred Lawson of Isel, Cumberland Educated
                    at Cambridge and knighted by Charles I, he was an active parliamentarian in the
                    civil war, though based and holding property in a county which was initially
                    fairly solidly royalist. He reportedly established a parliamentarian outpost on
                    St Herbert’s Island in Derwentwater and, although firmly rebuffed in an attempt
                    on Carlisle in 1643, from 1644 became parliament’s commander-in-chief in
                    Cumberland He held local office and represented the county or local borough
                    seats in several parliaments, acquired a baronetcy from James II shortly before
                    his death, and amassed substantial property in Cumberland<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">HOP, 1660-1690</emph><emph type="i"
                        >.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Northern Army
                        (Fairfax)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Layett, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Layett</emph><br/>Captain in service on 6 Aug. 1643 and
                    still there in Nov. 1643; his accounts place him in Grenville’s/Cooke’s regiment
                    of horse, which was not in existence at that point, but perhaps he was serving
                    in a troop which later was incorporated into it or perhaps in a regiment of
                    Cooke’s in the Western Association.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 50.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller; Waller (Southern
                    Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Layfield, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Layfield</emph><br/>Major in Sir John Norwich’s short-lived
                    regiment of dragoons in the Eastern Association Army, listed as such in Nov.
                    1643 shortly before the regiment was transferred to Lord Grey of Groby and his
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.75.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Layther, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Layther</emph><br/>Lieutenant-Colonel in the Plymouth
                    garrison at the time of Prince Maurice’s siege, Sept.-Dec. 1643. He may well be
                    the same man as Lieutenant-Colonel Lowther.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Worth, <emph type="i">History of Plymouth</emph>, 110.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Devon</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Le Hunt, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Le Hunt</emph><br/>He probably began the civil war as
                    ensign in Sir Anthony Irby’s regiment of dragoons in the Eastern Association
                    Army. Captain in the regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army commanded
                    by Colonel Francis Russell, then Colonel Vermuyden and then, from Mar. 1644, by
                    Colonel Charles Fleetwood. He was a captain in the regiment (under Russell) by
                    Feb. 1644 and continued to serve in that capacity once the regiment had
                    transferred to the New Model Army, though apparently only briefly, for he seems
                    to have left under a cloud, accused of corruption, very shortly after Naseby.
                    However, that was not the end of his military career, for he later served as an
                    officer in Wales and Ireland.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring,
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.34, 45; Wanklyn, <emph type="i"
                        >New Model Army</emph>, I, 51, 61-2, 72.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model
                        Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
                        <tr>
                <td>Lea, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lea</emph>
                    <br/>Lieutenant [of horse]. May be the same man as Captain
                    John Lea, above.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i"
                        >Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, 377.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lea, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lea </emph>(died 1661)<br/>Of Bridport. Captain in regiment
                    of Sir Walter Erle, 1643 [4 Nov. 1646: Dorset committee ordered payment of
                    &#xa3;4 14s. 0d. to a Dorchester widow upon whom soldiers had been quartered
                    belonging to Captain Lea and Captain Smith, under the command of Sir Walter
                    Erle: given reference to Erle and place, this has to be before Aug. 1643 when
                    the town surrendered to the royalists].<br/>Later captain of foot in Colonel
                    Thomas Ceely’s regiment.<br/>Possibly the Captain Lay who captured Wareham in
                    Nov. 1643 (as suggested by Bayley).<br/>MP for Bridport, 1659.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing
                        Committee</emph>, 55, 568, 114; Bayley, <emph type="i">Civil War</emph><emph
                        type="i"> in Dorset</emph>, 119-120; Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall
                        of the West</emph>, 5.515; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660
                        </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
<tr>
                <td>Lea [Lee, Leigh], John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lea [Lee, Leigh]</emph><br/>Of Stafford. A certificate from
                    1645 confirms that he was one of Brereton’s captains of dragoons, from 7 Nov.
                    1642 until at least 12 Nov. 1643; he was probably captain of one of the troops
                    raised in London which Brereton took north. He fought in the campaigns in
                    Cheshire in 1643, including the battle near Nantwich on 29 Jan. and the taking
                    of Eccleshall Castle, and was ‘once shot through the body’. Wounds, or possibly
                    a falling out with Brereton (his certificate was signed by three of Sir
                    William’s enemies), may explain his apparent early departure from the army. He
                    does not appear to have fought any further in the civil war, but he did later
                    serve as a sequestration commissioner and a captain in the horse
                        militia.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton
                        letter b</emph><emph type="i">ooks</emph>, 2. 204-5.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>

                        <tr>
                <td>Lead, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lead</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Thomas Cutlett’s company
                    in the Tower Hamlets Trained Bands regiment on 18 Apr. 1644.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/121A, Part 5, f. 580 r. &amp; v.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Tower Hamlets</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leadbeater, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Leadbeater</emph><br/>A captain in Sir William Brereton’s
                    Army in Cheshire, confirmed by a surviving warrant to pay Captain John
                    Leadbeater, his officers and soldiers 14 days’ pay. Dore notes that two
                    incidents link Leadbeater with Gawsworth in Cheshire but no firmly-proved links
                    can be found, suggesting either that his family was humble/obscure or that he
                    was a recent in-comer to the area.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore,
                        <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>,<emph type="i"/>1. 331; TNA,
                    SP28/346, f. 52.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leavens, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Leavens</emph><br/>Of Knowsthorpe, Yorkshire (West Riding), a
                    parliamentarian lieutenant in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 115 [citing TNA, E121/4/8, no. 30; BL,
                    Add. Ms. 21427, f. 186].<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Lee </emph><br/>Possibly William Lee
                    (died 1650) of Pinchinthorp, Yorkshire (North Riding), captain of foot early in
                    1643 and badly wounded at Leeds.<br/>Probably the Captain Lee of 1643 was the
                    Lieutenant-Colonel Lee who was active at siege of Pontefract in 1645 and
                    captured on 13 Mar. He probably served in Sir Thomas Mauleverer’s or Richard
                    Thornton’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War
                    in the North’, 389.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, Benjamin</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Benjamin Lee</emph><br/>Ensign in Viscount Saye and Sele’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 30.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lee</emph><br/>Lieutenant-colonel of the Red regiment,
                    London auxiliaries (Colonel Samuel Harsnett) when it mustered on 27 Apr. 1644
                    (but no longer there on 22 Oct. 1644). Possibly quartermaster to the Yellow
                    regiment, London Trained Bands, in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    TNA, SP28/121A, f. 693r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lee</emph><br/>Quartermaster to the Yellow regiment, London
                    Trained Bands (Colonel Sir John Wollaston).<br/>Very possibly Henry Lee,
                    lieutenant-colonel of the Red regiment, London Auxiliaries, in 1644.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Thrale 1642.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry</emph><emph type="b"> Lee</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Samuel
                    Luke’s troop in Sir William Balfour’s regiment of horse in spring
                        1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 20.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lee</emph><br/>In spring 1645, at the point the regiment was
                    being absorbed into the New Model Army, lieutenant of William Dingley’s troop in
                    the earl of Manchester’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 1.52.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee [Leigh], Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Lee [Leigh]</emph><br/>Captain in an Aylesford Lathe
                    regiment in the Kent Trained Bands by Aug. 1642, and possibly still there in
                    1648. By June 1643 his company was garrisoning Rochester, and that summer he was
                    threatened by the royalist rising in the county. Everitt identifies him as
                    Richard Lee, senior, in which case he is probably Richard Lee of Great Delce,
                    Kent, son of Richard Lee of the same (died 1618) and his wife Mary, daughter of
                    John Sherley, serjeant-at-law. In 1619 he had a son, Richard Lee, then aged two,
                    who might be the captain. The latter was a royalist plotter in the
                        1650s.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 74; Everitt, <emph type="i">Kent</emph>, 193, 196; <emph
                        type="i">Vis. Kent, 1619</emph>, 56.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Kent </emph></td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
                <td>Lee, Thomas </td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lee</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Thomas Grantham’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 41.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, Walter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Walter Lee</emph><br/>‘A haberdasher in Ludgate at the Signe of
                    the Sun &amp; bowle, broke Westm[inster] Windowes’ (BL, Harl. 986, p.
                    21).<br/>Second captain in the Yellow regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel
                    Sir John Wollaston) in Sept. 1643 (although not a captain a year before); Major
                    of the same Yellow regiment (by then under Colonel Ralph Harrison) by Oct. 1646.
                    He was promoted to lieutenant-colonel by the Presbyterian militia committee in
                    1647 but was displaced by the Independent militia committee later that
                    year.<br/>In Dec. 1642 a victim of crowd violence by peace petitioners at the
                    Guildhall, who jeered at him as a ‘Windsor reformado, roundheaded rogue’
                    (Lindley, <emph type="i">Popular politics</emph>, 339). Lindley identifies him
                    as a parish zealot in the early 1640s. A prominent Presbyterian in 1646-7, in
                    Dec. 1646 his shop was found to be the source of a rumour of the threat from the
                    New Model Army.<br/>According to the Presbyterian <emph type="i">A paire of
                        spectacles for the Citie</emph> (1648), 10, ‘a man of Estate and Quality, an
                    honest, godly, valiant man, a man that did as good service at Cherriton as any
                    man in the Brigade, a man that from principles of Honesty and Piety leads the
                    life of a Christian in sincerity’.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: BL,
                    Harl. 986, p. 21; Marshall, <emph type="i">Essex funeral</emph>, 11; Nagel,
                    ‘London militia’, 317-8;<emph type="i"/>Lindley, <emph type="i">Popular
                        politics</emph>, 208, 339, 371, 378; <emph type="i">A paire of spectacles
                        for the Citie</emph> (1648), 10.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lee, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lee</emph><br/>A captain in John Booth’s Lancashire
                        regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Gratton, <emph type="i"
                        >Lancs. war effort</emph>, 285.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leet, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Leet</emph><br/>By spring 1645 – probably from 1643 – a
                    captain in Harry/Henry Barclay’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army.
                    Like many of his fellow-officers in that regiment, he then transferred to the
                    New Model Army, as captain in what became Edward Harley’s New Model Army
                    regiment of foot, though only very briefly, as he resigned later in spring
                        1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New
                        Model Army</emph>, 1. 47-8, 150.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, Charles</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Charles Legard</emph><br/>Of Anlaby, Yorkshire (East Riding).
                    Captain in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 100 [citing TNA, E121/4/1, no. 38].<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, Christopher</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Christopher Legard </emph>(baptised 1615, died in or before
                    1663)<br/>Fifth son of John Legard (1576-1643) of Ganton. Early service obscure,
                    but by early 1645 captain in Lord Fairfax’s regiment of horse. However, when his
                    troop went to serve under Sir William Brereton in Feb. 1645 he did not go with
                    it, and instead it was commanded by his Lieutenant Richard Rokeby.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 390.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, Christopher</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Christopher Legard</emph> (born 1592)<br/>Of Anlaby, Yorkshire
                    (East Riding), eldest son of Robert Legard (of the senior branch of the family)
                    and his wife Anne Daniel. He married a daughter of William Rokeby and was hence
                    brother-in-law to Thomas Rokeby. He was a cousin to Sir John Hotham, Sir Thomas
                    Remington and the brothers Sir Hugh Cholmley and Sir Henry
                    Cholmley.<br/>Legard’s house was pillaged in summer 1642. By then he was
                    lieutenant-colonel to Sir John Hotham at Hull. He was temporarily suspended from
                    his command after Hotham’s arrest, but was cleared after appearing before the
                    Hull committee in July 1643. Early in 1645 he was promoted Colonel. He was
                    present at the sieges of Scarborough Castle in 1645 and 1648 (on 17 Dec. 1648 he
                    was a commissioner for its surrender), but resigned his commission in
                    1649.<br/>In June 1645 he was put on the Northern Association committee for the
                    East Riding.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                    390; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 100; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>,
                        10.639-40.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire;
                        Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army (Poyntz); Northern Army
                        (Lambert)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Legard</emph> (1573-1643)<br/>Of Ganton, Yorkshire (E.
                    Riding), esquire, eldest son of John Legard (died 1587) of Ganton and his first
                    wife Margery Frank. Father of Christopher Legard and possibly also of Henry
                    Legard. His sister Susanna married Sir Richard Cholmley of Whitby, father of Sir
                    Hugh Cholmley and John Cholmley, whilst his daughter Frances married Sir John
                    Hotham. His second son Richard was a royalist.<br/>He served at Scarborough
                    under Cholmley, which he held in Nov. 1642 with a garrison of 112 men. In Mar.
                    1643 he broke the news of Cholmley’s defection, reporting how he had been
                    imprisoned. He went to Hull, where he served, possibly in Francis Boynton’s
                    regiment of foot, until his death in Dec. 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 390; <emph type="i">Yorks.
                        Vis., </emph>2.401-2; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 99.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Legard</emph><br/>Of Ganton, Yorkshire (East Riding). A
                    captain in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 99 [citing TNA, SP23/135/394].<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Legard</emph><br/>Of Anlaby and Hull, Yorkshire (E.
                    Riding), a younger son of Robert Legard of Anlaby and his second wife Frances,
                    daughter of William Bernard, Hull mayor and merchant and father of Leonard
                    Bernard. Robert was a younger half-bro. of Colonel Christopher Legard of Anlaby.
                    Robert married Ursula, daughter of John Rodes of Barlborough, Derbyshire, uncle
                    of Sir Edward Rodes.<br/>He raised a troop of horse in 1642 and was busy
                    collecting money in the East Riding in spring 1643. He escorted Sir John Hotham
                    from Beverley to Hull after the latter’s arrest.<br/>In summer 1643 he was
                    drafted into Sir Henry Foulis’s regiment of horse (later the regiment of Sir
                    William Fairfax and Matthew Alured); he went into Lincolnshire with the regiment
                    in 1643 and was still in it in early 1645.<br/>In June 1645 he was put on the
                    Northern Association committee for the East Riding.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 390, Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 100.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legard, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Legard</emph><br/>Of Beverley, Yorkshire (East Riding),
                    alderman of Beverley. The younger son of the second marriage of Robert Legard of
                    Anlaby and hence half-bro. to Christopher Legard and brother to Robert
                    Legard.<br/>A captain in Hull by Aug. 1642, but only got his own company in
                    early 1643 (he was deprived of it in late 1643, probably temporarily, because of
                    suspected sympathy for Hotham).<br/>According to Firth and Davies,
                    lieutenant-colonel to Thomas Morgan in Flanders. Other sources claim that he was
                    killed in 1659 fighting for the king of France.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 390; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 97.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Legh, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Legh</emph><br/>Captain in Sir John Seton’s regiment of
                    dragoons, named as one of the officers to whom London volunteers should resort
                    at the end of Sept. 1642; it is not certain whether he eventually marched north
                    with the force.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire
                        </emph><emph type="i">military proceedings</emph>, 41.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leicester, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Leicester</emph><br/>By Jan. 1645 a captain in command of
                    a company of 23 dragoons serving with Sir Thomas Myddelton’s brigade based in
                        Montgomeryshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: National Library of
                    Wales, Chirk Castle Ms. 1/Biii, 93.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leigh, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Leigh</emph><br/>A major in Lancashire.
                    Leigh fought at the first defence of Bolton in Feb. 1643, when the royalists
                    were driven off. His horse was shot from under him and he was shot in the arm.
                    Possibly Major in Sir Ralph Assheton’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire m</emph><emph type="i">ilitary
                        proceedings</emph>, 81-2.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leigh, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Leigh</emph><br/>A lieutenant in the
                    Lancashire forces at the siege of Chester, present in records for Dec. 1645 and
                    Jan. 1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore,<emph type="i"> Brereton
                        letter books</emph>, 2. 382, 396, 510.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leigh, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Leigh </emph>(1603-1671)<br/>Of Rushall Hall,
                    Staffordshire, and Shamwell, Leicesterhire.<br/>Second but eldest surviving son
                    of Henry Leigh (1587-1630), gentleman, of Rushall Hall, Staffordshire, and his
                    first wife, Anne (died 1611), daughter of Anthony Lisle of Wootton in the Isle
                    of Wight. He married Elizabeth Talbot (died 1707) in 1629.<br/>A committed
                    puritan and author of religious works.<br/>He raised a troop of horse for
                    parliament, and served in the defence of Lichfield Close in Apr. 1643. He went
                    on to serve as colonel of a regiment of foot at Stafford.<br/>A Staffordshire
                    county committeeman man, named to it on 22 Feb. 1643. In its politics he was
                    pro-Denbigh, and in Sept. 1644 presented a Staffordshire petition in the earl’s
                    support to the Commons, and published the speech he then made.<br/>Elected MP
                    for Stafford in Oct. 1645 (by one vote), when Brereton hoped that, though
                    brought in by ‘the worse party’, Leigh might be won over as a ‘religious gent’
                    (Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2.216, 218)<emph type="i">.
                    </emph>Leigh was removed at Pride’s Purge.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter
                        books</emph>, 1. 62, 362, 2.127, 215-8; Pennington and Roots, <emph type="i"
                        >Committee at Stafford</emph>, <emph type="i">passim</emph>; <emph type="i"
                        >HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660 </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Staffordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leigh, Goddard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Goddard Leigh</emph><br/>Captain in Cholmley’s probably
                    short-lived regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642-3.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>,
                        36-7.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leigh [Lee], John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Leigh [Lee]</emph><br/>Major in the Westminster auxiliaries
                    regiment (Colonel James Prince) at muster of 13 May 1644 (when the regiment was
                    serving with Sir William Waller) and in Oct. 1646.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/121A, Part 4, ff. 538r.-539r.; Nagel, ‘London
                    militia’, 317; Marshall, <emph type="i">Essex funeral</emph>, 11.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leigh [Legh], John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Leigh [Legh]</emph><br/>Of Norbury Booths, Knutsford, ‘a
                    substantial squire of ancient descent’. Aged 12 in 1613, son of William Leigh
                    (died 1641) and his wife Dorothy Shakerley of Shakerley and Holme. Captain by
                    1643 and perhaps for a time governor of Northwich. Colonel of a regiment of foot
                    in Sir William Brereton’s Cheshire Army by 30 Apr. 1645.<br/>A close
                    collaborator of Brereton in the 1640s; hostile to the Protectorate because of
                    his radical principles; sheriff at the time of Booth’s Rising.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton</emph><emph
                        type="i"> letter b</emph><emph type="i">ooks</emph>, 1. 161, 329;<emph
                        type="i"/>Morrill, <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph>, <emph type="i"
                        >passim.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
                <td>Leigh, Jude</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Jude Leigh</emph><br/>Captain in Lord Wharton’s regiment of foot
                    in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Leighton</emph><br/>Captain of a trained
                    band company for Bramber Rape garrisoning Cowdray House, Sussex, until 7 Dec.
                        1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army</emph>, 124.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Sussex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, David</td>
                <td><emph type="b">David Leighton</emph><br/>Captain in Christopher Potley’s
                    regiment of foot until early 1644, when he became the regiment’s
                    Lieutenant-Colonel, leading his troops at the battle of Cheriton. He was with
                    the regiment when it served in the West in 1644-5, at some point before its
                    reduction in spring 1645 succeeding Potley as Colonel.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        113.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, Eliziar</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Eliziar Leighton</emph><br/>Major of a troop of horse at
                    Plymouth, dated references Sept. and Dec. 1643. Peachey and Turton suggest that
                    this troop was probably raised in London from survivors of Devon units which had
                    been at Roundway or from south-eastern recruits, and sailed to Plymouth with
                    Colonel William Gould. In Nov. 1643 he was captured when a sortie he was leading
                    pushed too far forward. Within the year he was free and promoted to colonel. On
                    3 Dec. 1644, the Commons approved the decision of the Committee of the West, who
                    had imprisoned Colonel Leighton for challenging Colonel John Luttrell, and left
                    final judgment to it. He may have been demoted, as in Mar. 1645 it was Captain
                    Leighton who was one of the petitioners who presented a petition from Plymouth
                    to the Commons. On 9 Apr. 1645 he was paid &#xa3;30 remaining due to him of
                    &#xa3;50 ordered to be paid to him in part-payment of arrears before he left
                    for London, ‘and wch. by reason of the exigencie of the garrison could not be
                    pd.’.<br/>On 24 Dec. 1645 the Lords recommended to the Commons that Leighton be
                    appointed colonel of the horse at Plymouth, which became the Plymouth regiment
                    in Massey’s Brigade.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton,
                        <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 4.446; Worth, <emph type="i">History
                        of Plymouth</emph>, 228; Worth, ‘Plymouth siege accounts’, 228; <emph
                        type="i">JHC</emph>, 3.712-3; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 4.72-5, 384-5;
                    Temple, ‘Massey Brigade’, 442.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Devon; Massey Brigade</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, Thomas </td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Leighton</emph><br/>Captain in Arthur Aston’s regiment of
                    foot in Northumberland’s Army against the Scots in 1640.<br/>Major in Rochford’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642, from or by 9 Sept., until
                    its disbandment in May or June 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 79, 32; TNA, SP28/2a/209,
                        SP28/7/294.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, Titus</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Titus Leighton </emph>(died 1643)<br/>Ensign in Thomas Lunsford’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Northumberland’s Army against the Scots in
                    1640.<br/>Reformado lieutenant of foot on 2 Aug. 1642. Shortly afterwards became
                    captain in Sir William Fairfax’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army,
                    coming north with Fairfax at the end of the year to join Lord Fairfax’s
                    Army.<br/>In July 1643 Leighton was at Hull; there he became Major to Sir Henry
                    Foulis’s regiment of horse on 13 Aug. 1643.<br/>On 28 Aug. 1643 he was killed in
                    Sir Thomas Fairfax’s retreat to Beverley.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    TNA, SP28/1d/481; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 84, 44; Jones, ‘War
                    in the North’, 389.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex; Northern Army (Fairfax)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, Walter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Walter Leighton</emph><br/>An officer of the small regiment of
                    reformado horse commanded by Major James Baker which came up from London to the
                    siege of Chester in late 1645.<br/>On 27 Nov. 1645 he was one of the officers
                    who signed a letter to Brereton explaining the mixture of social slighting and
                    lack of pay and secure quarters which had led the men to disobey a direct order
                    to march.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore<emph type="i">,
                        </emph><emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2. 275.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Reformado; London;
                    Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leighton, Walter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Walter Leighton</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of horse of
                    Robert Burghill/Jonas Vandruske.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring,
                        <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 139.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Waller</emph><emph type="i">;</emph><emph type="i"> Waller
                        (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lenerick, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lenerick</emph><br/>Captain-lieutenant of the Colonel’s own
                    troop in Sir John Gell’s regiment of horse, killed in 1643 in the operation to
                    drive the royalists out of and away from Nottingham.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Hutchinson, <emph type="i">Life</emph>, 144.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Derbyshire;
                    Nottinghamshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leonards, Leonard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Leonard Leonards</emph><br/>Recommended by the Commons on 25 Oct.
                    1642 that the earl of Holland, Lord lieutenant of Middlesex, appoint Leonards
                    Captain, under the lieutenant of the Tower, of a company drawn from St
                    Katherine’s and East Smithfield, ‘he being earnestly desired and recommended by
                    all the Inhabitants, as a Man very worthy of that Trust’ (<emph type="i"
                        >JHC</emph>, 2.823). This became part of the Tower Hamlets Trained Bands
                    regiment but at some point passed to Christopher Gore, captain by Oct. 1646. At
                    the muster of Apr. 1644 the company was still described as Leonards’s, but the
                    officer at the muster was Gore, his lieutenant.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 2.823; TNA, SP121A, Part 6,
                    ff. 602r.-603r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Tower
                        Hamlets</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lestead, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lestead </emph>(died 1643)<br/>A major in Cheshire, killed in
                    an abortive attack on Cholmondeley House, 11 Apr. 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire tracts</emph>,<emph type="i"
                        />49-50.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leventhorp, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Leventhorp</emph><br/>Early in 1642 lieutenant to Captain
                    William St Leger in his troop of horse in Lord Wharton’s army intended for
                    Ireland. Instead, later that year he became captain in the earl of Essex’s own
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army, and still captain on 13 Jan.
                        1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        Lists</emph>, 68, 25; TNA, SP28/5/100.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leverett, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Leverett</emph><br/>Captain in Thomas Rainsborough’s
                    regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                        2.90.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Levett, Willliam</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Levett</emph><br/>Major of the Tower Hamlets auxiliaries
                    regiment in Oct. 1646; promoted by the Presbyterian militia committee in 1647 to
                    be lieutenant-colonel of the Tower Hamlets Trained Bands regiment.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Nagel, ‘London militia’, 317; Marshall, <emph
                        type="i">Essex funeral</emph>, 11; TNA, SP28/46, Part 1, f. 34r.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Tower Hamlets</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Levington [Lemmington], Patrick</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Patrick Levington [Lemmington] </emph>Chaplain to James Kerr’s
                    [Carr’s] regiment of foot, 29 Aug. 1643-20 Feb. 1644. Chaplain to Colonel Hans
                    Behre’s regiment of horse from 1 July 1644.<br/><emph type="b"
                    >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 26.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lewinger [Longer], -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lewinger [Longer]</emph><br/>Captain in Lord Willoughby’s
                    regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army and the Eastern Association Army.
                    He probably transferred as lieutenant in Blethin’s company when the regiment
                    transferred to the New Model Army, by 1649 promoted to captain in the same
                    regiment, by then commanded by William Constable.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                    2.107; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 102.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Ea</emph><emph type="i">rl of Essex;
                        Ea</emph><emph type="i">stern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model
                        Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lewis, Roger</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Roger Lewis</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Francis Blethin’s company in
                    Edward Montagu’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.72.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lewis, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lewis</emph><br/>Captain of Dorset volunteer foot
                    company, references 8 Nov. 1642-31 July 1643. Apparently present at Sherborne in
                    Nov. and Dec. 1642-Feb. 1643 stationed at Dorchester where it was supported by
                    contributions from the town.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and
                    Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 5.507.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Leyfield [Lafield], Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Leyfield [Lafield]</emph> (died 1648)<br/>Of Sutton
                    Coldfield, Warwickshire, a man of modest wealth, whose inventory at death
                    amounted to &#xa3;70.<br/>A captain of horse in Warwickshire, whose troop
                    formed part of the Tamworth garrison during the first civil war (accounts for
                    Aug. 1644-Aug. 1645). He sat on the council of war there on 27 Oct. 1644. On 12
                    Mar. 1645 he was ordered to collect the weekly assessment for part of Edingdale,
                    Staffordshire. Governor of Maxstoke Castle, Warwickshire, Oct. 1645-May
                        1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hughes, <emph type="i"
                        >Warwickshire</emph>, 187n., 188, 196, 199n.; TNA, SP28/139, Part 17;
                    Pennington and Roots, <emph type="i">Committee at Stafford</emph>, 202,
                        270.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Warwickshire;
                        Staffordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lidcott, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lidcott</emph><br/>In 1642 listed as captain of a troop of
                    horse in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 51.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Liddiatt, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Liddiatt</emph><br/>A captain in the earl
                    of Denbigh’s Army: on 10 May 1644 he was paid &#163;1 to buy a hat and boots
                    for one of the general’s trumpeters.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA,
                    SP28/147, part 3, f. 470r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl
                        of Denbigh</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lilburne, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lilburne </emph>(baptised 1618, died 1648)<br/>Third son of
                    Richard Lilburne (baptised 1583, died 1667) of Thickley Punchardon, County
                    Durham and his wife Margaret Hixon (died 1619), daughter of Thomas Hixon, Keeper
                    of the Standing Wardrobe at Greenwich; younger brother of Robert Lilburne and
                    John Lilburne. He married in 1647 Anne Rushworth, sister of John Rushworth,
                    secretary to Sir Thomas Fairfax and author of <emph type="i">Historical
                        Collections </emph>(for whom see <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>).<br/>On 6
                    June 1644 Henry was commissioned captain in his brother Robert Lilburne’s
                    newly-raised regiment of horse and was promoted Major two weeks later. In Aug.
                    he and his cousin Thomas Lilburne were ordered to block the Tees to prevent
                    royalists escaping into Yorkshire, and in Oct. he took 40 prisoners in an action
                    at Scarborough. He remained in Yorkshire until 1646, when he went south with his
                    brother and became captain and (in July 1647) lieutenant-colonel in Robert
                    Lilburne’s New Model Army regiment of foot, although he returned north with
                    Robert to settle the unrest in the Northern Army. Back south, he was a speaker
                    at the Putney debates where his stance was that of ‘a sceptical maverick’,
                    challenging some of the more radical voices (Gentles, <emph type="i">New Model
                        Army</emph>, 215). On 1 Nov. he commented, ‘That hee never observed that the
                    recovery of our liberties which wee had before the Normans was the occasion of
                    our taking uppe armes, or the maine quarrel; and that the Norman Lawes are nott
                    slaverie introduced upon us, but an augmentation of our slaverie before’ (<emph
                        type="i">Clarke papers</emph>, 1.368). He is probably (and was so believed
                    to be by his brother John Lilburne) ‘E.R.’ who on 9 Nov. sent a letter warning
                    Charles I of a (highly improbable) plot by the army agitators against his life,
                    which gave the king a public pretext for his escape from army captivity at
                    Hampton Court two days later.<br/>Henry was appointed deputy-governor of
                    Tynemouth Castle where, on 9 Aug. 1648, he declared for the king. He was killed
                    two days later in the subsequent attack by Sir Arthur Hesilrige and his head
                    displayed on the castle gate.<emph type="i"/><br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 390; <emph type="i">Vis.
                        London, 1687</emph>, 2.491, 496; Firth and Davies, <emph type="i"
                        >Reg</emph><emph type="i">imen</emph><emph type="i">tal History</emph>,
                    1.264, 2.456; P. Gregg, <emph type="i">Free-born John </emph>(1961), 364, 205,
                    247; I. Gentles, <emph type="i">The New Model Army in England, Ireland and
                        Scotland, 1645-1653</emph> (1992), 215; C.H. Firth, ed., <emph type="i">The
                        Clarke papers</emph>, 1.368); A. Woolrych, <emph type="i">Soldiers and
                        Statesmen: The General Council of the Army and its debates, 1647-1648</emph>
                    (1987), 82, 229, 249, 271-5; Hill and Watkinson, <emph type="i">Major
                        Sanderson’s war</emph>, 179.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">County Durham; Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army (Poyntz);
                        Northern Army (Lambert); New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lilburne, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lilburne</emph> (c.1615-1657)<emph type="b"/><br/>Born c.
                    1615 at Sunderland, son of Richard Lilburne of Thickley Punchardon near Bishop
                    Auckland. Elder brother of Henry Lilburne, younger brother of Robert
                    Lilburne.<br/>In 1630 he was apprenticed to a puritan London clothier and as the
                    decade progressed his own godly views strengthenedIn 1637-8 he clashed with the
                    government and was whipped, pilloried and for a time imprisoned by order of Star
                    Chamber for his involvement in publishing seditious material.<br/>Released in
                    late 1640, he fought for parliament from the outset and began the civil war as
                    captain in Lord Brookes’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army, probably
                    captured and briefly held prisoner by the royalists when they attacked and
                    mauled Brookes’s and Holles’s regiments in their storming of Brentford in Nov.
                    1642, before transferring to the Eastern Association Army in autumn 1643 and
                    becoming Major in command of a company within Edward King’s regiment of foot.
                    However, like many others, he fell out with King and by spring 1644 he was
                    serving as lieutenant-colonel in the earl of Manchester’s regiment of dragoons;
                    he effectively took command of that regiment of dragoons at that point and led
                    it during the campaign and battle of Marston Moor and then in taking a string of
                    royalist bases in southern Yorkshire and campaigning in the East Midlands in
                    autumn 1644. He did not join the New Model and so left the army in spring
                    1645.<br/>Lilburne’s fame lies, of course, not in his military career of 1642-5,
                    but in his political ideas and activism and in his later role as a Leveller and
                    radical thinker and writer and in the various accusations, trials and sufferings
                    which resulted in the late 1640s and early 1650s.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 1.47.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">E</emph><emph type="i">arl of Essex</emph><emph type="i">;
                        E</emph><emph type="i">astern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lilburne, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Lilburne </emph>(1614-1665)<br/>Second son of Richard
                    Lilburne (baptised 1583, died 1667) of Thickley Punchardon, County Durham and
                    his wife Margaret Hixon (died 1619), daughter of Thomas Hixon, Keeper of the
                    Standing Wardrobe at Greenwich; brother of Henry Lilburne and John
                    Lilburne.<br/>Little is known of his life before the outbreak of the civil war.
                    He began the war as an officer – initially Cornet in Lord Brooke’s troop, later
                    lieutenant in Richard Crosse’s troop – of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army,
                    1642-3. He returned north in 1644, raising a regiment of horse in his native
                    County Durham and campaigning in the Fairfaxes’ Northern Association Army.
                    Although not initially appointed to the New Model Army, at the end of 1645
                    Colonel Ralph Weldon was appointed governor of Plymouth and a few months later
                    Lilburne succeeded him as colonel of his New Model regiment of foot. He was
                    prominent in army politics during 1647, though by the end of the year he had
                    again gone north, this time appointed governor of Newcastle upon Tyne. As such,
                    he effectively relinquished command of his (soon to be mutinous) New Model foot
                    regiment and instead took command of a northern-based New Model horse regiment.
                    As such he campaigned in 1648 with Lambert and in support of Cromwell to crush
                    the Scottish-royalist army in the campaign and battle of Preston and then he
                    helped mop up remaining royalist bases, notably Pontefract. However, he was in
                    London in early 1649 and was a regicide.<br/>He spent much of the first half of
                    the 1650s campaigning in Scotland, initially in support of Cromwell’s expedition
                    and then as commander of the army in Scotland crushing resistance in the
                    Highlands. He became governor of York and in 1655-7 was deputy Major-General (to
                    the absent Lambert) in Yorkshire and County Durham. He was elected to all three
                    Protectorate Parliaments, though his return to the third was challenged. In 1659
                    he helped crush Booth’s Rising and supported the army’s seizure of power in the
                    autumn, but in early 1660 he and his old colleague Lambert proved ineffective in
                    halting Monck’s march south. He surrendered at the Restoration and although
                    convicted of treason, was spared execution; instead he spent his last years in
                    prison in Plymouth and on an island in Plymouth Sound.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph><emph type="i"
                        >.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex;
                        Northern </emph><emph type="i">Army</emph><emph type="i">; New Model
                        Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lilburne, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Lilburne</emph><br/>Almost certainly not the Robert
                    Lilburne (1614-65) who was a regicide and deputy Major-General and was elder
                    brother of the Leveller leader, but a separate and different man. This Robert
                    Lilburne was lieutenant, later captain, in Edward King’s regiment of horse in
                    the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring,
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.46.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lilburne, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lilburne </emph>(died 1665)<br/>Of Offerton, County
                    Durham, eldest son of George Lilburne (baptised 1578, died 1699), esquire, and
                    his first wife Isabel Chambers of Cleadon; first cousin to Robert Lilburne, John
                    Lilburne and Henry Lilburne. George was a leading coal magnate, merchant and
                    mayor of Sunderland, 1635-8 and 1640-2.<br/>He was made captain in Robert
                    Lilburne’s newly-raised regiment of horse on 25 May 1644. In Aug. 1644 he and
                    his cousin Henry Lilburne were sent to guard the passages into Yorkshire to
                    royalists escaping from County Durham. He served in both the first and second
                    civil wars. ‘He was known … as a good officer and disciplinarian of his troops’
                    and was careful of his men when they were in contact with civilians’ (Jones,
                    ‘War in the North’, 391). In Sept. 1647 his and John Sanderson’s troops were
                    sent into Liddesdale to pursue moss-troopers.<br/>Lilburne was loyal to Oliver
                    and Richard Cromwell, and feared the army intrigues against the latter. MP for
                    County Durham in 1656 and for Newcastle-upon-Tyne in 1659. He continued to serve
                    in Robert Lilburne’s regiment, but was displaced after the fall of the
                    Protectorate. He was re-instated when his regiment turned against their colonel
                    and John Lambert, and he brought his troop into the field with Fairfax in
                    Yorkshire in early 1660. He was briefly promoted Major, but was reduced back to
                    captain in July; the regiment was disbanded in Nov. 1660.<br/>Lilburne was
                    involved in various purchases of crown lands, and by 1660 was apparently sole
                    owner of the manor of Holm Cultram, Cumberland He died 25 Mar. 1665, described
                    by his memorial inscription in Houghton-le-Spring church as ‘one of the
                    instrumental persons in his majesty’s happy Restoration’ (<emph type="i">Vis.
                        London, 1687</emph>, 2.496).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones,
                    ‘War in the North’, 391; Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Reg</emph><emph
                        type="i">iment</emph><emph type="i">al history</emph>, 1.264, 266, 273-7;
                        <emph type="i">Vis. London, 1687</emph>, 2.492, 496; Gentles, ‘Debentures
                    Market’, 308.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">County Durham;
                        Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army (Poyntz); Northern Army (Lambert);
                        New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Linch, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Linch</emph><br/>At the time the regiment was broken up in
                    spring 1645, captain in Francis Russell’s regiment of horse in the Eastern
                    Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 2.98.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Linch, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Linch</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir William Constable’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 42.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lincoln, Maurice</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Maurice Lincoln</emph><br/>Alderman of Hull, Yorkshire (E.
                    Riding) and a lieutenant of the watch there.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 91.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Linde, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Linde</emph><br/>A cornet in Waller’s
                    Southern Association Army, captured at the battle of Cropredy Bridge (29 June
                        1644).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> App. 2, p. 3.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lindsey [Lyndsey], John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lindsey</emph><emph type="b"> [Lyndsey]</emph><br/>Probably
                    started the civil war as lieutenant in Captain Thomas Hammond’s troop of horse
                    in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642. Lieutenant in Captain Adam Lawrence’s troop
                    in Oliver Cromwell’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army by 13
                    Aug. 1643, and still there in Jan. 1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.21; TNA, SP28/13/59,
                        SP25/23/153.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Ea</emph><emph
                        type="i">rl of Essex; Ea</emph><emph type="i">stern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Line, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Line</emph><br/>In spring 1645 captain-lieutenant in Colonel
                    John Browne’s Shepway Lathe Kentish trained band regiment of
                        auxiliaries.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army</emph>, 86.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Kent</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ling, Carax</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Carax Ling</emph><br/>Listed as cornet in James Temple’s troop of
                    horse in the earl of Essex’s army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 50.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ling, Nicholas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Nicholas Ling</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lord Brooke’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 34.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lingwood, Lionel[?]</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Lionel</emph>[?] <emph type="b"/><emph type="b"
                    >Lingwood</emph><br/>By spring 1644 and still there in Mar. 1645, shortly before
                    the regiment was broken up, captain in Francis Russell’s regiment of horse in
                    the Eastern Association Army. He was intended to be a captain in the regiment
                    upon its transfer to the New Model Army, but he chose not to serve.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.97; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I,
                        46-7.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lisle, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lisle</emph><br/>Of Gisborough, Yorkshire. Commissioned
                    captain in a regiment of foot in the Yorkshire militia.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 506.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lister, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lister</emph><br/>Ensign in Sir William Constable’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 42.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lister, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Lister</emph><br/>Gentleman, a younger
                    son of Sir William Lister of Thornton-in-Craven, Yorkshire (North Riding), and a
                    royalist until the surrender of York, when he changed sides. He became captain
                    in Sir Richard Sandys’s regiment of horse and was captured by the royalists in
                    Sept. 1644 when Sir John Mayney beat a force under Sandys near
                        Brotherton.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                        392.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lister, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"/><emph type="b">Lister </emph><br/>Of
                    Manningham township, Bradford parish, Yorkshire (West Riding). A captain in
                        Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 106.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lister, Christopher</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Christopher Lister </emph><br/>Of Thorenton-in-Craven, Yorkshire
                    (North Riding). He is possibly the third son of Sir William Lister (died 1650) of
                    Thornton-in-Craven, who married Winifred, daughter of Sir Richard Fletcher and
                    widow of Sir Richard Dacres. Alternatively, he might also possibly be
                    Christopher Lister (died 1668), second son of Sir William’s eldest son William
                    Lister (died 1642) of Thornton-in-Craven, admitted Gray’s Inn 13 Aug. 1639; MP
                    for Westmorland in the first and second Protectorate Parliaments. Whatever his
                    parentage, he was a captain in Yorkshire. His is probably the Christopher Lister
                    who later in the 1640s became a captain in Lilburne’s newly-formed northern
                    regiment of horse on the New Model Army payroll.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 119; Wanklyn, <emph type="i"
                        >New Model Army</emph>, I, 164.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Yorkshire</emph><emph type="i">; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lister, Hugh</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Hugh Lister </emph>(1621/2-1666)<br/>Fourth son of Sir John
                    Lister (died 1640), knight, of Hull and his wife Elizabeth Armyn of Hull. He was
                    possibly Ensign Lister in Sir William Constable’s regiment of foot in 1642, and
                    was by early 1645 captain in the same regiment, now commanded by Simon Needham.
                    In Feb. 1645 he carried money from Hull to Scarborough to pay the
                        soldiers.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                    391; <emph type="i">Yorks. Vis., </emph>341-2.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
                <td>Lister [Lyster], Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lister [Lyster] </emph>(baptised 1615, died 1642)<br/>Of
                    Lower Hall, Westby, in Gisburn township, parish of Gisburn, Yorkshire (W.
                    Riding), esquire, eldest son of Thomas Lister (died 1619) and his wife Jane
                    Heber. He married Catherine, daughter of Sir Richard Fletcher of Hutton,
                    Cumberland). A ward of the crown. At his majority he bought Westby Lower Hall
                    and its demesnes. He was admitted to Gray’s Inn, 7 May 1640.<br/>Captain of foot
                    in the Northern Army by Oct. or Nov. 1642, and fought at the battle of Wetherby
                    in Nov. He was buried at Gisburn, 19 Nov. 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 391; <emph type="i"
                        >Yorks.</emph><emph type="i"/><emph type="i">Vis., </emph>2.139; Hopper,
                    ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 108.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lister [Lyster], William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lister [Lyster] </emph>(died 1642)<br/>Of
                    Thorneton-in-Craven and Midhope, Yorks (North Riding), eldest son of Sir William
                    Lister (died 1650) and his wife Mary Bellasis (whom he had married in 1610). Sir
                    William was MP for East Retford, 1646-8. William’s sister Frances (died 1676)
                    married John Lambert, whilst his brother Martin married Catherine, a daughter of
                    Sir William Fairfax of Steeton.<br/>William was admitted to Gray’s Inn, 5 Mar.
                    1629. He married Catherine, daughter of Sir Richard Hawkesworth of Hawksworth,
                    who after his death married John Bright.<br/>Captain of foot by Oct. 1642, he
                    fought at Bradford and Leeds (Oct.), Wetherby (Nov.) and was killed at Tadcaster
                    (6 Dec.). ‘Captain Will’m Lister, a valiant and gallant Gentleman, who was shot
                    with a Musketbullet in the Head’ (<emph type="i">JHL</emph>, 5.493-6).<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 391; <emph type="i"
                        >Yorks.</emph><emph type="i"/><emph type="i">Vis., </emph>2.136; Hopper,
                    ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 119; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>, 5.493-6.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
                <td>Littler, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Littler </emph>(died 1644)<br/>Captain in Colonel Leigh’s
                    regiment of foot in Cheshire. Died early 1644 and succeeded as captain by
                    William Wright.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: BL, Harl. Ms. 2128, f.
                        166r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Livesay [Livesey], Sir Michael</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir Michael Livesay [Livesey], first baronet
                    </emph>(1614-1665?)<br/>Son and heir of Gabriel Livesay of Hollingborne, Kent, a
                    modest but established gentry family. Created baronet in the late 1620s and a JP
                    by the late 1630s, but as a strong puritan he became a fierce opponent of the
                    king and a leading light in Kentish parliamentarian circles. He raised a
                    regiment of horse in Kent at the outbreak of the civil war, which helped secure
                    his own county and neighbouring Sussex, which in 1643 supported Waller in
                    operations at Farnham and Arundel and which during 1644 fought under Waller in
                    his Oxfordshire campaign and at the battles of Cheriton and Cropredy Bridge. In
                    the wake of the latter, his regiment became mutinous and began to disperse,
                    though most or all of the regiment seems to have fought under Waller again at
                    the second battle of Newbury and then went west with Waller until it returned to
                    Kent in spring 1645.<br/>Despite his extensive military service in south-eastern
                    and southern England and his role on the Kent county committee, Livesay was
                    accused of cowardice and of encouraging the mutinous nature of his regiment by
                    some fellow parliamentarians. He left the army in spring 1645, though most of
                    his regiment survived and was absorbed into Henry Ireton’s New Model Army
                    regiment. Later in 1645 Livesay was elected MP for Queenborough, Kent, where he
                    supported the political Independents and the army interest; having been active
                    again in Kent, Surrey and Sussex, quelling disturbances and royalism and
                    ensuring loyalty to parliament in 1647-8, he became a regicide and a radical
                    member of the Rump. He was probably disenchanted by the Protectorate, though he
                    retained local office in Kent, served in the recalled Rump in 1659 and fled to
                    the continent at the Restoration; he died there, probably in the
                        mid-1660s.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Kent;
                        Waller</emph><emph type="i">; Waller</emph><emph type="i"> (Southern
                        Association) </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Llewellin, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Llewellin</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir William Fairfax’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 44.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, Andrew</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Andrew Lloyd</emph><br/>Of Ashton Hall, near Oswestry,
                    Shropshire, from a modest gentry family and ‘a smallish landowner’, according to
                    Carr and Atherton. By 1643 a member of the Shropshire county committee and by or
                    from mid-1643 captain in Thomas Mytton’s regiment of horse, described as
                    commanding a ‘broken troop’ at Wem in Feb. 1644 according to the royalists.
                    Based at Oswestry in summer 1644. By the time of the taking of Shrewsbury in
                    Feb. 1645, he was colonel of a regiment of Shropshire horse, described as
                    300-strong when it took part in the fight at Stokesay in June 1645, and of a
                    regiment of foot, companies from which garrisoned Bridgnorth in 1646. Governor
                    of Bridgnorth after town and castle fell to parliament in spring 1646. In 1648
                    he gathered parliamentarian volunteers at Wem and in Aug. was appointed to raise
                    and command a regiment of militia foot in Shropshire. A very active
                    committeeman, named to all Shropshire county committees, 1643-8.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Carr and Atherton, <emph type="i">Brereton
                        Staffs</emph>., 93, 175; BL, Add. Ms. 18981, f. 69; Warws. RO, C2017?c10/4;
                        <emph type="i">JHL</emph>, X, 425; National Library of Wales, Aston Hall
                    estate records, D1 Ms. 2468; <emph type="i">More Exact and Particular Relation
                        of the taking of Shrewsbury, than hath hithero been published. With the
                        manner and performance thereof by Lieutenant Colonell William
                        Reinking</emph> (1645); <emph type="i">Intelligence from Shropshire of Three
                        Great Victories obtained by the Forces of Shrewsburie</emph>
                        (1645);<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Shropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lloyd</emph><br/>Captain. An officer at Bristol during its
                    siege. Noted as being there on 27 July 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 6.610.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Bristol</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, Jeffrey</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Jeffrey Lloyd</emph><br/>Ensign in Rochford’s regiment of foot in
                    the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock,
                        <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 32.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lloyd</emph><br/>Captain in Sir John Merrick’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army. He was one of those captains in the regiment
                    who fought with and under Waller in summer 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 28.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lloyd</emph><br/>Captain in Sir Thomas Myddelton’s North
                    Wales Army, confirmed by surviving pay warrants and receipts of spring 1644 for
                    his own pay and that of his lieutenant and ensign.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346, nos. 39, 51, 122.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lloyd</emph><br/>Ensign in Sir William Fairfax’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 44.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lloyd</emph><br/>Ensign in the earl of Essex’s own regiment
                    of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642; captain of the same regiment by
                    June 1643 and still there in Oct. 1644. Not one of the captains who transferred
                    to the New Model Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph
                        type="i">Army lists</emph>, 26;<emph type="i"/>TNA, SP28/9/1,
                        SP28/19/21.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lloyd, Luke</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Luke Lloyd</emph> (1609/10-1695)<br/>Of Bryn, Flint. (detached)
                    (died 1695, aged 85). A Puritan and minor squire, who maintained a garrison at
                    Willington, near Bryn, for Myddelton. Surviving pay warrants of spring 1644 (and
                    later) direct payment to him, holding the rank of Captain, to defray his
                    expenses in maintaining forces in the area and for horses. In 1645 he was taken
                    prisoner, with 20 of his troop and imprisoned in Holt Castle by Major Francis
                    Manley, elder brother of the parliamentarian John Manley, and granted parole to
                    negotiate his exchange in Oct. 1645. On 26 Apr. 1646 he wrote a letter of
                    complaint to Brereton about the depredations of Brereton’s Captain Walker,
                    governor of Ridley, and his soldiers. Commissioner for the propagation of the
                    gospel in Wales (1650). In his later years Philip Henry was his pastor; Henry
                    described him as ‘the glory of our little congregation…a man of great courage
                    and resolution…his charity and moderation known to all men…a pattern of piety
                    and primitive christianity’. He married the half-sister of Colonel Roger
                    Whitley, royalist governor of Aberystwyth (for whom see <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph>).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i"
                        >Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 300, 2. 97-8, 155, 389; TNA, SP28/346,
                    nos. 90, 91, 164, 283.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North
                        Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
<tr>
                <td>Lloyd [Floyd], Walter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Walter Lloyd [Floyd]</emph><br/>Captain in Viscount Saye and
                    Sele’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642. In spring 1645 he
                    became lieutenant-colonel of the New Model Army regiment of foot initially and
                    briefly commanded by Aldridge, by May succeeding Aldridge as its Colonel, only
                    to be killed at Taunton a few weeks later.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 30.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lobb, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lobb</emph><br/>Present at the siege of Portsmouth in Aug.
                    1642 and serving as deputy governor of the town and Major of the foot serving
                    there from early 1643. He was one of those officers who were incorporated into
                    the Portsmouth-based regiment of foot which served under William Jephson in
                    1644-5, again as Major.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring<emph
                        type="i">, Waller’s army, </emph>71<emph type="i">.</emph><br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association);
                        Hampshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Locke, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Locke</emph><br/>Captain in Randall Mainwaring’s Red regiment
                    of foot, briefly captured in a skirmish at Olney, Bedfordshire, in Nov.
                        1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: George Paine, <emph type="i">A
                        true relation </emph><emph type="i">of all the skirmishes between our forces
                        and the Cavaliers at Owlny </emph>(1643), 3.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Locke, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Locke</emph> (born c. 1610)<br/>Captain-lieutenant. Son
                    of Roger Locke, gentleman, who became free as a Bristol merchant on 1 Feb. 1632.
                    He was captain-lieutenant to Colonel Andrew Charlton in the Bristol Trained
                    Bands in 1643:<br/>‘That dewring the time Collonell Nathaniell Fines was
                    governor of Bristoll until the time the Cittie of Bristoll was taken in by the
                    King the saide Lock served under Collonell Charelton deceased as his Captain
                    Liuetenant faithfully And iustlie without takeing or demanding any paie or
                    recompence for such his service, which could not bee undergon butt by great
                    expence and charge, hee having two hundred men under his charge which weare
                    twice everie weake upon dewtie’ (<emph type="i">Merchants and
                    Merchandise</emph>, 133).<br/>In 1654 he pleaded his heavy financial losses.
                    Twice during the siege of Bristol in 1643 his ships had been commandeered by the
                    governor to cover the approaches to the town. He suffered from both sides; the
                    royalist Sir John Pennington pressed two of his ships whilst parliamentarian
                    frigates captured some of his ships, and his property was burnt or plundered by
                    royalists in 1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Merchants and Merchandise</emph>, 150-5.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Bristol</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lodge, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lodge</emph><br/>Commissioned captain in a regiment of foot
                    in the Yorkshire militia.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >CSPD, 1650</emph>, 506.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lodge, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lodge</emph><br/>Of Sherborne. On 7 Jan. 1647, claimed
                    for arrears of pay 13 Dec. 1644-20 Feb. 1646. Quartermaster to troop of horse of
                    Captain-Lieutenant Riddout [Rideout] and Captain Mooreton.<br/>From 20 Feb.
                    1646-28 Aug. 1646 [26 weeks], lieutenant to troop of horse of Captain Thomas
                        Hughes.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset
                        Standing Committee</emph>, 132-3.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Loftus, Samuel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Samuel Loftus</emph><br/>Fourth captain in Charles Essex’s
                    regiment of foot in Lord Wharton’s Army raised for Ireland in 1642. He went
                    instead with the regiment into the earl of Essex’s Army as captain in Charles
                    Essex’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph
                        type="i">Army lists</emph>, 70, 45.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Loftus, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Loftus</emph><br/>Cornet in Edward Kightley’s troop in the
                    earl of Essex’s army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton,
                        <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 7.709; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 52.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lomax, Gervase</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Gervase Lomax</emph><br/>Captain of a company of foot in Francis
                    Pierrepont’s and then John Hutchinson’s Nottingham-based regiment of foot. Later
                    possibly promoted to major in that regiment.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Hutchinson, <emph type="i">Life</emph>, 110-11, 124,
                    129, 196, 208, 213.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Nottinghamshire </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lomax, Jarvis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Jarvis Lomax</emph><br/>By Oct. 1643 and still there in Aug.
                    1644, captain of a company in a regiment of foot which served under Oliver
                    Cromwell and later under Colonel Francis Russell in their capacity as governors
                    of the Isle of Ely and later under Colonel Valentine Walton senior, which
                    probably originated as an auxiliary regiment of the Cambridgeshire
                        militia.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 1.29.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Long, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Long</emph><br/>Captain in Nathaniel
                    Fiennes’s regiment of horse at Bristol in 1643. Probably Captain William Long,
                    captain of a troop in Essex’s army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                    >References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>,
                    6.611.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Long, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Long</emph><br/>By the beginning of 1645, lieutenant in Azariah
                    Husbands’s company in John Pickering’s regiment of foot in the Eastern
                    Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 2.85.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Long, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Long</emph><br/>Second captain in Lord Wharton’s regiment
                    of foot in his army raised for Ireland in 1642; he went as captain in Wharton’s
                    regiment in the earl of Essex’s Army from or by 23 Aug. 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 68, 31; TNA,
                        SP28/2a/90.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Long, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Long</emph><br/>During late winter and early spring 1644,
                    lieutenant-colonel in Edward Montagu’s regiment of foot in the Eastern
                    Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 2.69.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Long, Sir Walter, first baronet</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir Walter Long, first baronet
                    </emph>(c.1591-1672)<br/>Born the younger son of Henry Long (died 1612), who was
                    an affluent clothier and landowner of Whaddon, Wiltshire. He gained experience
                    of naval expeditions against the Algerian corsairs, but by the early 1620s he
                    was back in England, following the deaths of his father and then his elder
                    brother having inherited the family’s by then debt-ridden estate. He was an MP
                    in the early parliaments of Charles I and soon became a critic of some aspects
                    of the government, especially the role of the duke of Buckingham. He supported
                    the Petition of Right and played a leading role in the tumultuous events in the
                    Commons at the end of the 1629 session, leading to his arrest and imprisonment
                    in the Tower until 1633.<br/>He was an MP in the Long Parliament and in 1642
                    actively supported the war effort. He became a captain in Sir William Balfour’s
                    regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army in summer 1642, commissioned on 29
                    July, and he commanded the troop at least until Dec., though he was reportedly
                    wounded at Edgehill.<br/>A pay warrant for late July 1643 places his troop by
                    then in James Sheffield’s regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army. The
                    troop was no longer there by summer 1644.<br/>Long became colonel of a regiment
                    by June 1643 until at least mid-Oct., perhaps as late as the beginning of May
                    1644 (he was paid for his regiment on the former date; other pay warrants to the
                    latter date call him colonel but only pay him for his troop).<br/>He was active
                    in trying to bolster the parliamentarian position in his native Wiltshire and in
                    Shropshire, where his second marriage had brought him connections and land.
                    However, in the words of the <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>, ‘it is uncertain
                    whether he saw further action’.<br/>In the later 1640s he became a prominent
                    political Presbyterian, and thus one of the eleven MPs targeted for removal from
                    the Commons or worse by the New Model Army. He fled to the continent and
                    probably had connections with royalists in exile. He returned to England in
                    1659, supported the Restoration and was rewarded with a baronetcy.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>;<emph type="i"
                    />Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 55; TNA, SP28/2a/161, SP28/3a/142,
                    SP28/4/372, SP28/7/282, SP28/9/76, SP28/10/246, SP28/15/103; <emph type="i">HoP:
                        The </emph><emph type="i">Commons, 1604-1629</emph>; <emph type="i">HoP: The
                        Commons, 1640-1660 </emph>[forthcoming]<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Wiltshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Long, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Long</emph><br/>Captain in Sir Henry Foulis’s regiment of
                    horse in Yorkshire from early in the war, and still in the regiment (now under
                    Sir William Fairfax) in Lincolnshire in Dec. 1643. He was present at the battle
                    of Nantwich in Jan. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in
                    the North’, 392.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Longhey [Longkey], Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Longhey</emph><emph type="b"> [Longkey]</emph><emph
                        type="b"/><br/>Lieutenant in Captain Henry Turner’s company in the
                    Westminster auxiliaries regiment (Colonel James Prince) at its muster, 13 May
                    1644. The name may be Longkey.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA,
                    SP28/121A, Part 4, ff. 536r-537v.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Westminster</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lookar, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lookar</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Thomas Ballard’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 43.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lou, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lou</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lyme garrison who in 1650
                    signs a petition for maimed soldier. His surname may be a misreading of
                        signature.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton,<emph
                        type="i"> Fall of the West</emph>, 5.516.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lovekyn, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Lovekyn</emph><br/>Captain-lieutenant in the Colonel’s
                    company in Valentine Walton’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army;
                    by the beginning of 1644 he had been promoted to captain and continued to serve
                    in the regiment in 1645-6, when it was commanded by James Hobart.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.104.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lovell, Benjamin</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Benjamin Lovell </emph>(born 1607/08)<br/>Graduated BA from
                    Merton College, 11 Apr. 1627; proceeded MA from St Edmund Hall, 1630. Ordained
                    priest, 11 Dec. 1628. Schoolmaster of Horley, Oxfordshire, 1629; curate of
                    Alkerton, Oxfordshire, in 1631 and of Shutford chapel, Swalcliffe parish (Oxon.)
                    in 1634-5. Rector of Preston Bagot (Warws.) from 1636.<br/>He married (1) Mary
                    Godwin (died 1658); their children included the naturalist Robert Lovell
                    (1630?-1690) and Sir Salathiel Lovell (1631/32-1713), for both of whom see <emph
                        type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>.<br/>For some months in 1643, probably from about
                    Easter, Lovell commanded a troop of horse in Warwickshire. On 17 Oct. 1643 he
                    was forced to hand over his troop to Major Abraham Pont on the orders of Colonel
                    William Purefoy. The troop took part in the taking of Tamworth Castle.<br/>He
                    became rector of Lapworth, Warwickshire, in 1643, where he resisted paying the
                    sequestered minister's wife her due out of the revenues of the parish. In 1646
                    he was threatened with the loss of the living unless he did so, and by May 1649
                    owed her two years’ arrears. Benjamin Lovell conformed at the Restoration,
                    remaining rector of Lapworth, and was still alive in 1677.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/136, Part 35; SP28/136, Part 32; <emph
                        type="i">Alumni Oxonienses</emph>; Clergy of the Church of England database,
                    <a href="http://www.theclergydatabase.org.uk/">www.theclergydatabase.org.uk</a>; <emph type="i">Oxford DNB
                    </emph>[Salathiel Lovell].<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lovell, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Lovell</emph><br/>Ensign in Rochford’s regiment of foot in
                    the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock,
                        <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 32.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lovell, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lovell</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of foot of the
                    earl of Peterborough in the earl of Essex’s Army, 1642-3.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 28.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lovell, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lovell</emph><br/>Ensign in the regiment of foot of Oliver
                    Lord St John/Thomas Essex, named in the published list of officers in the earl
                    of Essex’s army, 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton,
                        <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 6.650; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        Lists</emph>, 34.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Bristol</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowe [Lower], -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lowe [Lower]</emph><br/>Captain in Sir John Merrick’s regiment
                    of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army. He was one of those Captains in the
                    regiment who fought with and under Waller in summer 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 28.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowe, Alexander</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Alexander Lowe</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Holmes’s company in
                    Colonel Richard Holland’s regiment of foot in the Manchester garrison.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: TNA, E121/5/7 (Duckenfeild, 6/5/1651).<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowe, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lowe</emph><br/>A lieutenant in Alexander Rigby’s Lancashire
                    regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Gratton, <emph type="i"
                        >Lancs. war effort</emph>, 295.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowe, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lowe</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain William Johnstone’s
                    company in Lawrence Crawford’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army
                    at the time of its disbandment on 17 Apr. 1645.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                        1.15.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowenger, -</td>
                <td>-<emph type="b"> Lowenger</emph><br/>A Dutchman with a company in the Hull
                    garrison, who served in the West Riding in late 1642 under Captain John Hotham.
                    He was based in Cawood Castle until Mar. 1643, when he went to Beverley. He
                    raised a troop of horse and went into Lincolnshire with his foot and horse with
                    John Hotham. In June 1643 he acted as an agent provocateur to entrap the
                    Hothams; unaware of this, the Commons ordered his arrest on 6 July, although he
                    was later released and his property restored.<br/>Later promoted Major, serving
                    under Lord Willoughby of Parham in Lincolnshire.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 392.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lower [Lowther], William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lower [Lowther]</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir Jacob
                    Astley’s regiment of foot in the earl of Northumberland’s Army against the Scots
                    in 1642.<br/>Fifth Captain, of firelocks, in Lord Kerry’s regiment of foot in
                    Lord Wharton’s Army raised for service in Ireland in summer 1642, instead
                    becoming Major in Thomas Ballard’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army.
                    He reportedly defected to the King early in the war.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 76, 69,
                        43.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lownes, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lownes</emph><br/>He is presumably the Captain Lowance who in
                    Sept. 1643 took over as joint-governor of Cholmondeley. On 29 Oct. 1644 (with
                    Croxton) led his foot company in a raid from Nantwich on Farndon.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: BL, Harl. 1999, f. 61r.; <emph type="i">Cheshire
                        tracts</emph>, 138, 150.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowser, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Lowser</emph><br/>Captain in the Kent
                    Trained Bands.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army,</emph> 78.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Kent</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowther, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Lowther</emph><br/>Lieutenant-colonel in
                    Colonel James Wardlaw’s regiment at Plymouth. His lieutenant recorded as serving
                    28 Mar. 1643-28 Mar. 1644. He may well be the same man as William
                        Layther.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph
                        type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 3.360.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Devon</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowther, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Lowther</emph><br/>Captain of Shropshire forces and
                    commander of the garrison at Wrockwardine church, Shropshire in late 1645,
                    successfully beating off a royalist assault on 19 Dec. 1645.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books,</emph> 2.
                        394.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Shropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowthian [Lothian, Louthiane], James</td>
                <td><emph type="b">James Lowthian [Lothian, Louthiane]</emph><br/>(He spelt his name
                    as Louthian).<br/>Evidently a Scottish professional soldier. Lowthian came north
                    with Sir William Brereton in Jan. 1643 as his Sergeant-Major. He rallied the
                    troops at Hopton Heath (19 Mar. 1643). Captured in the early stages of the siege
                    of Nantwich (Dec. 1643), he had been exchanged by the time of the battle of
                    Montgomery (18 Sept. 1644). There, Sir John Meldrum reported, ‘The <emph
                        type="i">Cheshire</emph> foot, with their Officers, carried themselves more
                    like Lions than Men, especially Major <emph type="i">Lowthian</emph>, who
                    commanded as Major General’ (<emph type="i">JHL</emph>, 6.715).<br/>In 1645
                    Lowthian was Sir William Brereton’s Adjutant-General at the siege of Chester. On
                    20 Sept. 1645 he and Colonel Michael Jones led the forces which captured the
                    eastern suburbs of Chester up to the city walls; five days later, whilst the
                    king’s and Poyntz’s armies were clashing on Rowton Heath, Lowthian and his foot
                    repelled a royalist sally out of Chester.<br/>On 17 July 1646 the Commons
                    ordered:‘That Adjutant-General Louthian shall have the Sum of Two hundred Pounds
                    bestowed upon him for his good Service to the Parliament at Lichfield, and other
                    Places: and that the Sum of Five hundred Pounds more be paid unto the said
                    Adjutant-Gneral Lowthian, by the Committee of Goldsmiths-Hall, upon Account’
                        (<emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 4.621).<br/>Lowthian remained in the Chester
                    garrison. In 1648 he was appointed colonel of the ‘Standinge Regimt. of this
                    County’ (also called the ‘Regt. of foote now called upon Service, and raised for
                    the safety of Cheshier’); the regiment was mustered on 19 Aug. and 2 Sept. (TNA,
                    SP28/224, ff. 308, 31). With this force he served under Mytton, suppressing the
                    rising in North Wales and marching into Anglesey. In late Aug. 1648 he and the
                    sheriff of Cheshire, Roger Wilbraham, took the surrender of the fleeing Scottish
                    Army at Warrington. On 7 Oct. the Commons awarded him &#xa3;1,000 out of the
                    sequestrations of North Wales rebels involved in the second civil
                    war.<br/>Lowthian seems to have disappeared from the local rcords, playing no
                    part with the Cheshire forces in the Worcester campaign. In May 1657 he was
                    still seeking payment of arrears from the Commons.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Dore<emph type="i">, Brereton letter books</emph>, 1.
                    103; <emph type="i">Civil war in Cheshire</emph>, 43; TNA, SP28/224, ff. 267,
                    308, 317, 318; <emph type="i">VCH, Cheshire</emph>, 5.i.115-25; <emph type="i"
                        >JHC</emph>, 4.139, 621, 5.688-9, 6.43-4, 46, 7.539; <emph type="i"
                        >JHL</emph>, 6.715, 609, 10.533.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lowton, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Lowton</emph><br/>A lieutenant in John Moore’s Lancashire
                    regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Gratton, <emph type="i"
                        >Lancs. war effort</emph>, 292.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lucas, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Lucas</emph><br/>A captain in George Doddington’s
                    Lancashire regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Gratton, <emph
                        type="i">Lancs. war effort</emph>, 287; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1655</emph>,
                        58..<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Luddington, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Luddington</emph><br/>A Lincolnshire gentleman, initially
                    serving on the Lincolnshire committee of the Eastern Association. By 26 Sept.
                    1644 he was a captain in Chrsitopher Copley’s regiment of horse, raising and
                    arming 50 troopers at his own expense. He turned his troop over to Copley on 24
                    June 1645 under the provisions of the Northern Association Ordinance, claiming
                    &#xa3;525 in expenses.<br/>Possibly the Mr Luddington of Sculcoates in 1654
                    appointed a Hull ejector.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in
                    the North’, 392.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ludlow, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Ludlow </emph><br/>Captain in Richard
                    Norton’s Hampshire regiment of horse.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 103.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Hampshire; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ludlow, Edmund</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edmund Ludlow</emph> (1616/17-1692)<br/>Son of Sir Henry Ludlow,
                    MP for Wiltshire in the Long Parliament. At the beginning of the war he enlisted
                    as one of the 100 gentlemen forming the Life-Guard of the earl of Essex, and was
                    present at the skirmish at Worcester (23 Sept. 1642) and at the battle of
                    Edgehill (23 Oct. 1642). Invited by Sir Edward Hungerford to raise a troop in
                    his regiment, Ludlow returned to Wiltshire in late Apr. 1643, after the fall of
                    Reading, ‘with three more of the life-guard, two whereof were to be officers in
                    my troop, and the third in another troop of the same regiment’ Appointed
                    governor of Wardour Castle after its capture in May 1643, where he was besieged
                    for three months before it fell. In early summer 1644 he was released upon an
                    exchange of prisoners, and on 10 May 1644 was made major in Sir Arthur
                    Hesilrige's regiment of horse in Waller’s army. On 30 July 1644, Waller gave him
                    a colonel's commission, sending him into Wiltshire to raise a regiment of horse,
                    whilst parliament made him sheriff around the same time, and although he fought
                    at second Newbury (Oct. 1644), Basing House (Nov. 1644) and Taunton (Dec. 1644),
                    his main efforts were in winning control of Wiltshire. In early Jan. 1645
                    Langdale surprised Ludlow’s regiment and Ludlow only escaped with difficulty.
                    Hesilrige pushed for him to be an officer of the New Model Army, but the
                    Wiltshire committee claimed that that he could not be spared. Ludlow was elected
                    MP for Wiltshire in May 1646. Subsequent military career as colonel of horse,
                    Wiltshire militia, 10 Apr. 1650; lieutenant.-general. of horse in Ireland from 2
                    July 1650; and commander-in-chief, Ireland, July 1659. Colonel regiment of foot,
                    June, July 1659.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB; HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660 </emph>(forthcoming).<br/>.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Wilts</emph><emph type="i"
                        >hire</emph><emph type="i">: </emph><emph type="i">Sir Edward Hungerford’s
                        </emph><emph type="i">Regt.</emph><emph type="i"> of </emph><emph type="i"
                        >Horse</emph><emph type="i">; Ireland</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ludlow, Gabriel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Gabriel Ludlow</emph> (died 1644)<br/>Cornet in Edmund Ludlow’s
                    regiment of horse, probably in the Colonel’s troop. He served in the garrison at
                    Wardour Castle and was killed at the second battle of Newbury.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        82.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ludlow, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William </emph><emph type="b">Ludlow</emph> (born
                    1618/19)<br/>Cousin of Edmund Ludlow and son of Henry Ludlow of Hill Deverill
                    and Tadley; MP for Old Sarum in 1659. Cornet to Captain Edmund Ludlow, and
                    wounded in an ambush in autumn 1643 when Ludlow’s troop was stationed in the
                    lands between Poole and Southampton: ‘being brought to Southampton, and his
                    wounds searched, the bullet that went in at his belly was found at the chine of
                    his back, with a piece of the waistband of his breeches, which being cut out, he
                    wonderfully recovered to be in some measure serviceable to the publick’. Still
                    cornet in Edmund Ludlow’s troop in Jan. 1644. Late in 1644 he was put in command
                    of the garrison of Falston Manor, Wiltshire and ‘with his troop somewhat
                    restrained the excursions of the King’s party from their garrison thereabouts’.
                    When Falston was slighted in late 1645, Ludlow took his force to garrison
                    Langford Castle. On 4 May 1646, the Commons resolved on the slighting of Castle
                    Hill and fortifications at Devizes and also Langford castle. Force to be left in
                    Wiltshire was to consist of 100 horse under Captain William Ludlow, governor of
                    Devizes, with 150 foot garrisoning.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Memoirs of Edmund Ludlow</emph> ed. C.H. Firth, 2 vols. (1894),
                    2.69, 117, 124;<br/><emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660
                        </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Wilts</emph><emph type="i">hire</emph><emph type="i">: </emph><emph
                        type="i">Sir Edward Hungerford’s </emph><emph type="i">Regt.</emph><emph
                        type="i"> of </emph><emph type="i">Horse</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Ludlow, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William </emph><emph type="b">Ludlow</emph><emph type="b"/> (born
                    1618/1619)<br/>Cousin of Edmund Ludlow and son of Henry Ludlow of Hill Deverill
                    and Tadley; MP for Old Sarum in 1659. Cornet to Captain Edmund Ludlow, and
                    wounded in an ambush in autumn 1643 when Ludlow’s troop was stationed in the
                    area between Poole and Southampton; ‘being brought to Southampton, and his
                    wounds searched, the bullet that went in at his belly was found at the chine of
                    his back, with a piece of the waistband of his breeches, which being cut out, he
                    wonderfully recovered to be in some measure serviceable to the publick’. Still
                    Cornet in Edmund Ludlow’s troop in Jan. 1644. Late in 1644 he was put in command
                    of the garrison of Falston Manor, Wiltshire, ‘who with his troop somewhat
                    restrained the excursions of the King’s party from their garrison thereabouts’.
                    When Falston was slighted in late 1645, Ludlow took his force to garrison
                    Langford Castle. On 4 May 1646, the Commons resolved on slighting of Castle Hill
                    and fortifications at Devizes and also Langford Castle. Parliament directed that
                    the force to be left in Wiltshire should consist of 100 horse under Captain
                    William Ludlow, governor of Devizes, with 150 foot garrisoning
                        Malmesbury.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Ludlow, <emph type="i"
                        >Memoirs</emph><emph type="i"/>1.69, 117, 124; Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army,</emph> 82.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Wiltshire; Waller; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lufkin, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Lufkin</emph><br/>A captain in Coventry
                    regiment of foot (Colonel John Barker), evidently early in the first civil war,
                    as his successor, Captain Matthew Randall, commanded the company from Dec.
                        1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/136, Part 15; Part
                        21.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Luke, Oliver</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Oliver Luke</emph><br/>In Nov. 1644, lieutenant in the Colonel’s
                    own company in Sir Samuel Luke’s Newport Pagnell-based regiment of
                        foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        a</emph><emph type="i">rmy</emph>, 95.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Bedfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Luke, Sir Samuel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir Samuel Luke </emph>(1603-1670)<br/>Born the eldest son of Sir
                    Oliver Luke (died c.1650) of Woodend, Cople, Bedfordshire. Via his parents, he
                    was linked to several other parliamentarian families, including the Fleetwoods
                    and the Barringtons, and more distantly the Cromwells and the Fienneses. He
                    married and was knighted during the 1620s and by the 1630s was active in the
                    county government of Bedfordshire.<br/>He was eleted to both the Short and the
                    Long Parliaments, though in both cases his return was disputed and there was a
                    delay before he could take his seat. Like his father, he strongly supported
                    parliament in the civil war, in 1642 raising and commanding a troop of horse
                    which formed part of the earl of Essex’s Army and was present at the campaign
                    and battle of Edgehill.<br/>In 1643 he was commissioned colonel of a regiment of
                    dragoons or horse, with which he campaigned around the fringes of Oxfordshire
                    over the next few months; in his absence his regiment was mauled by Prince
                    Rupert at Chinnor in June but he was present alongside Hampden at
                    Chalgrove.<br/>He became Scoutmaster General of Essex’s Army and campaigned with
                    part of the Army in the Home Counties in the late summer and early autumn; he
                    took part in the operation to recover Newport Pagnell in late Oct. 1643 and was
                    appointed Governor.<br/>From that point until he eventually stood down in June
                    1645 in line with the Self-Denying Ordinance, Luke combined the role of
                    Scoutmaster with the governorship of what became the major parliamentarian
                    garrison at Newport Pagnell. As such, he had interests in and often contributed
                    to parliamentarian operation over a wide area of the south and east Midlands,
                    from Leicesterhire and Northamptonshire, through Bedfordshire, Buckinghamshire
                    and Berkshire, and around Oxfordshire; even developments as far away as
                    Warwickshire and Gloucs. concerned him. His geographically wide-ranging
                    interests and involvement in the war across a large part of the Midlands, his
                    fears for his own garrison, often under-manned, short of supplies and thus in
                    danger, he thought, together with his energy and industry in the parliamentarian
                    cause, are all revealed by his voluminous surviving correspondence from his time
                    as governor of Newport Pagnell, one of the major sources for the civil war in
                    that region.<br/>His opposition to radicalism and radical religious practices
                    evident during his period as Governor, including his arrest in June 1645 during
                    the closing days of his governorship and his subsequent (unsuccessful) pursuit
                    of two Baptist-inclined New Model officers (Hobson and Beaumont) who preached in
                    Newport Pagnell, had already earned the distrust of many in the New Model and of
                    the political Independents. He was seized by soldiers in 1647 but released on
                    Fairfax’s orders and he was arrersted again at Pride’s Purge, though he was
                    released before the end of Dec. 1648. He played no part in public events or
                    national politics for the next ten years or more, living in retirement on his
                    Bedfordshire estates. He sat in the Convention Parliament in 1660.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph><br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex;
                    Bedfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lukeman, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lukeman</emph><br/>In summer 1644, during the doomed campaign
                    in the South West, captain in John Dalbier’s regiment of horse.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        51.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex;
                        </emph><emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lumsden, James</td>
                <td><emph type="b">James Lumsden</emph> (died 1644)<br/>Captain in James Kerr’s
                    [Carr’s] regiment of foot, 29 Aug. 1643-15 Mar. 1644; captain in Sir William
                    Waller’s regiment of foot, 25 Mar. 1644 until his death on 15 Apr.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 25,
                        150<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lundy, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Lundy</emph><br/>By spring 1645, when it was disbanded,
                    captain in the regiment of foot by then commanded by Edward Aldridge in the earl
                    of Essex’s Army. He transferred at that rank and in that regiment, initially
                    under Aldridge, into the New Model Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, 1. 48-9, 149.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lune [Lunn], -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lune</emph><emph type="b"> [Lunn]</emph><br/>By early 1645
                    lieutenant in Captain Cromwell’s company in John Pickering’s regiment of foot in
                    the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring,
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.86.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Luttrell, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Luttrell </emph>(1610-45)<br/>Of Santon Court, near
                    Barnstaple, Devon. Colonel. Eldest son of John Luttrell (1584-1617) and his wife
                    Frances, daughter of Sir Edward Gorges of Wraxall. He married Rachel (died
                    1653), daughter of Francis Hardy. A friend of Robert Bennet.<br/>Luttrell was a
                    captain by early 1643, possibly in Sir Samuel Rolle’s Devon Trained Band
                    regiment (which was also Bennet’s regiment early in the war). In Apr. 1643 his
                    actions at Sourton Down were noted.<br/>In the summer of 1644 Luttrell landed
                    from South Wales to organize the rising against the royalists at Barnstaple as
                    Essex’s army approached. The town rose on 26 or 27 June, and Luttrell was a
                    leader in repelling Colonel Digby’s attempt to retake the town on 1 July. Essex
                    commissioned Luttrell to raise a volunteer regiment of foot, probably the 374
                    men whom he commanded at Barnstaple, where he was appointed governor. On 15 July
                    the Commons appointed him high sheriff of Devon. In Aug. he attacked the nearby
                    royalist stronghold at Appledore, Cornwall, but had to withdraw when a royalist
                    relieving force approached. He evidently marched out when the town surrendered
                    on 17 Sept. 1644.<br/>Colonel Eliziar Leighton challenged Luttrell to a duel: on
                    3 Dec. 1644, the Commons approved the decision of the Committee of the West, who
                    had imprisoned Colonel Leighton for challenging Colonel Luttrell, and left to it
                    final judgment.<br/>Luttrell was killed at Milverton, Somerset, on 28 Jan. 1645.
                    Captain William Mercer wrote a broadside elegy for him:<br/>‘O! Devon, Devon,
                    doe nothing but weep.<br/>Because thy keeper Luttrell lyes asleep’.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Vis. </emph><emph type="i"
                        >Devon</emph>, 539, 541; Cotton, <emph type="i">Barnstaple</emph>, 255-7,
                    277-9, 328, 299, 335; Andriette, <emph type="i">Devon</emph>, 213; Peachey and
                    Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 3.327; <emph type="i"
                    >JHC</emph>, 3.712-3; W. Mercer, <emph type="i">An Elegie on the Death of the
                        thrice valiant and worthy Colonell John Luttrell </emph>(1645).<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Devon</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Luxford, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Luxford</emph><br/>Captain in Herbert Morley’s regiment of
                    foot from its formation in Mar. 1644 to its reduction on 30 Apr. 1645. He was
                    apparently at the unsuccessful siege of Basing House in 1644.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        100.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Sussex; Waller
                        (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lvereier[?], - </td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lvereier[?]</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Captain Samuel Bosa’s
                    reformado troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army in Nov./Dec.
                        1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/4/175.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lydcott, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lydcott</emph><br/>Successively captain and then Major in
                    Nathaniel Whetham’s Northampton-based regiment of horse, who seems to have taken
                    command of part or all the regiment towards the end of the war, including at the
                    siege of Banbury. As such, he appears frequently in Sir Samuel Luke’s letter
                    books, and several letters to and by him survive there.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s a</emph><emph type="i"
                        >rmy</emph>, 164; <emph type="i">Luke Letter Books</emph>, especially nos.
                    125, 134, 311, 414, 478, 956, 1105, 1114, 1195.<br/><emph type="b"
                    >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Northamptonshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lyeathcock, Humphrey</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Humphrey Lyeathcock</emph><br/>Ensign in Lord Brooke’s regiment
                    of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 34.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lygon, William </td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Lygon</emph><br/>Of Madresfield Court, Worcestershire, by
                    Mar. 1645 he was a colonel empowered to work with Rous in raising troops in
                    Worcestershire and Warwickshire to strengthen parliament’s hold on
                        Worcestershire</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lynn, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Lynn</emph><br/>In May 1643, captain serving in one of the
                    three regiments of foot formed from the Essex militia, part of the Eastern
                    Association Army that contributed to the siege of Reading in spring 1643, the
                    siege of Greenland House in summer 1644 and probably to some other actions in
                    which the Army was involved.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.33.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lysle, Edmund</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edmund Lysle</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Thomas Bowman’s company
                    in the Isle of Wight foot regiment of Thomas Carr.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        24.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Isle of
                    Wight</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Lysley, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Lysley</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel Richard Shuttleworth’s
                    regiment of foot. Owed &#xa3;321 17s 1d in Sept. 1650.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, E121/4/8.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>
</report>
