<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE report SYSTEM "DTD/report.dtd">
<report id="154150" pubid="1496">
<title>I</title><subtitle />
<section id="s1"><head>Surnames beginning 'I'</head>
    <table id="t1">
<tr><td>Ince, Peter</td><td><emph type="b">Peter Ince </emph>(1614/5-1683)<br/>Son of Peter Ince of Chester and seems to have had links to the Myddelton family, for in Mar. 1644 Sir Thomas Myddelton authorised payment of &#xa3;20 to him in his capacity as either a personal or army chaplain. He had already served with Myddelton’s army the previous winter, and was part of the garrison placed in Hawarden Castle by the short-lived thrust of Brereton and Myddelton into north-east Wales in Nov. 1643 and left stranded by their rapid retreat upon the landing of the king’s army from Ireland. On 12 Dec. 1643, one royalist officer, reporting the surrender of the garrison on terms which allowed them to march away with one colour flying, drily noted that the parliamentarian force had consisted of 120 men, being all that was left of Myddelton’s regiment, seditious chaplain and all, except for Myddelton himself. During his time serving Myddelton, he wrote and published several accounts and religious pieces, including<emph type="i"> An Addition to the Relation of some Passages about the English-Irish Army, before they came to the siege at Namptwich, Wherein are set down the Occurrences at Hawarden Castle</emph> (London, 1643; Thomason date 9 Feb. 1643/4). In his preface, Ince rejoiced, ‘That God should burne your bullets in their bodies who would have sheathed their swords in yours...’.<br/>Ince’s time as Myddelton’s chaplain can have lasted no more than a few months after his payment in spring 1644, for he became chaplain to the parliamentarian garrison at Weymouth in 1644-6 and published <emph type="i">A brief relation of the surprise of the forts of Weymouth, the siege of Melcombe, the recovery of the forts and raising of the siege</emph>, describing events there early in 1645. His presence on the Dorset coast is probably explained by the detour imposed on the infantry forces under Colonel Beale and Lieutenant-Colonel Carter which were being sent by sea to join Myddelton. On 8 Sept. 1644 the Committee of Both Kingdoms ordered Beale, who now lay very conveniently for reinforcing Weymouth for the brief period until a force of 1,000 men arrived, to take over its defence.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; TNA, SP28/346, nos. 48, 97; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1644</emph>, 43; <emph type="i">Calamy Revised</emph>, 288-9; Laurence, <emph type="i">Army Chaplains</emph>, 137-8.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales; Dorset</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ingoldsby, Francis</td><td><emph type="b">Francis Ingoldsby </emph><br/>Eldest son of Sir Richard Ingoldsby (died 1656) of Lenborough, Buckinghamshire, and his wife Elizabeth (died 1666), daughter of Sir Oliver Cromwell of Hinchinbrooke, Huntingdonshire (the uncle of Oliver Cromwell). Brother of Richard Ingoldsby, Oliver Ingoldsby and Henry Ingoldsby.<br/>An addition to the copy of the herald’s visitation of 1634, probably made by the Augustan antiquarian Peter Le Neve, noted that Francis was still alive in 1650, and that he was ‘a prodigall sold Lethenborow came to be a Pentioner in the Charterhouse’ (<emph type="i">Vis. Buckinghamshire, 1634</emph>, 76).<br/>Captain of a troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army, recorded in a series of pay warrants between May 1643 and Apr. 1644. He does not appear in the published list of Essex’s officers in its early months, nor in the list of cavalry captains mustered during the campaign of summer 1644 in the South West.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/7/87, 434, SP28/8/98, SP28/9/106, 213, SP28/10/176, SP28/11/216, SP28/12/116, SP28/15/106; <emph type="i">Vis. Bucks., 1634</emph>, 76.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ingoldsby, Sir Henry, first baronet</td><td><emph type="b">Sir </emph><emph type="b">Henry Ingoldsby</emph><emph type="b">, </emph><emph type="b">first</emph><emph type="b"> b</emph><emph type="b">aronet</emph> (1623-1701)<br/>Younger son of Sir Richard Ingoldsby (died 1656) of Lenborough, Buckinghamshire, and his wife Elizabeth (died 1666), daughter of Sir Oliver Cromwell of Hinchinbrooke, Huntingdonshire (the uncle of Oliver Cromwell). Brother of Francis, Thomas and Richard Ingoldsby.<br/>In the course of the civil war he became a captain in the regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army commanded successively by Hampden, Tyrrill and his elder brother Richard Ingoldsby. He was still there in spring 1645 and transferred with that regiment to the New Model Army. He left the regiment in summer 1647 in order to fight in Ireland, becoming first lieutenant-colonel and then colonel of a regiment of horse and dragoons which campaigned in Ireland for many years, fighting under Cromwell at Drogheda and elsewhere and under Ireton at Limerick. He became governor of Limerick, acquired much land and property in Ireland and represented Irish seats in all three Protectorate parliaments. He returned to England and supported Monck and the Restoration. Charles II confirmed him as a baronet and confirmed his possession of Irish lands and estates. He continued to live in Ireland for the rest of the century, serving as an Irish privy councillor and sitting in the Irish parliament. He supported and raised a regiment for William III in Ireland.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, 1. 148.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; New Model Army</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ingoldsby, Oliver</td><td><emph type="b">Oliver Ingoldsby</emph><br/>Sometime between the end of 1643 and the transfer of the regiment into the New Model Army he superseded Thomas Brundell as captain, later (by Jan. 1645) major in Sir John Norwich’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army. In spring 1645 he seems to have been appointed a captain in Fortescue’s New Model Army regiment of foot, serving in that capacity until he was killed at Pendennis Castle in Mar. 1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.45; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 56-7.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ingoldsby, Richard</td><td><emph type="b">Richard Ingoldsby </emph>(1617-1685)<br/>Second son of Sir Richard Ingoldsby (died 1656) of Lenborough, Buckinghamshire, and his wife Elizabeth (died 1666), daughter of Sir Oliver Cromwell of Hinchinbrooke, Huntingdonshire (the uncle of Oliver Cromwell). Brother of Francis, Thomas and Henry Ingoldsby. His mother’s aunt was the mother of John Hampden.<br/>Captain in John Hampden’s regiment of foot from or by 10 Aug. 1642. He may well have been promoted major when Major William Barriffe was promoted lieutenant-colonel after the defection of Joseph Wagstaffe. Promoted lieutenant-colonel of the same regiment by 23 Oct. 1643, no doubt in succession to the deceased Barriffe, who died in July-Aug.<br/>Colonel of the same regiment by 21 Oct. 1644 in succession to Thomas Tyrrill who had commanded it from Hampden’s death through to the Cornish expedition.<br/>He commanded the regiment for the remainder of its time in the earl of Essex’s Army and in spring 1645 transferred with it as colonel to the New Model Army. As such, he and his regiment served with the New Model during the final year of the war and played an important role in the South West in relieving Taunton and capturing Bridgwater and Bristol. He retained his command after being elected a Recruiter MP. Although he rarely attended the king’s trial, he did sign the death warrant. He supported the ejection of the Rump and, although he did not hold high office under it, he supported the Protectorates of Oliver and Richard Cromwell; accordingly, as one of the few senior officers to support Richard in spring 1659, he found himself isolated and was deprived of command by the returning Rump. He actively supported the Restoration and, on the basis of his claim that he had unwillingly signed the death warrant, his hand held and forced by Cromwell, he was pardoned and held office under Charles II. sitting in most parliaments of the reign.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1660-1690</emph>;<emph type="i"></emph>TNA, SP28/2b/329, 518, SP28/10/270, SP28/19/76, E121/2/10#49; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-1659 </emph>[forthcoming].<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; New Model Army</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Inman, Owen</td><td><emph type="b">Owen Inman</emph><br/>Of Bouthwaite, Kirkby Malzeard, Yorkshire (West Riding), a parliamentarian lieutenant in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 112.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Innes [Ennis], Christopher </td><td><emph type="b">Christopher Innes [Ennis]</emph><br/>In summer 1644 he became captain in, and was later major of, Sir Samuel Luke’s Bedfordshire-based regiment of horse. Innes and his troop remained at Newport Pagnell until autumn 1645, before joining Poyntz.<br/>He was one of Luke’s most trusted and apparently most active officers in and around Bedfordshire and as such is frequently mentioned in his letter books, including several surviving letters to and from him.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army</emph>, 93; <emph type="i">Luke Letter Books</emph>, especially nos. 182, 239, 310, 346, 362, 390, 391, 393, 425, 443, 449, 476, 479, 480, 513, 518, 645, 715, 840, 1034, 1086, 1124, 1201, 1210, 1218, 1552, 1572, 1578, 1602, 1608, 1613.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Bedfordshire; Northern Army (Poyntz)</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Innes, John</td><td><emph type="b">John Innes</emph><br/>In spring 1645 lieutenant-colonel of the regiment of foot – which he had probably joined as major from its formation towards the end of 1642 – commanded by Henry/Harry Barclay in the earl of Essex’s Army. Like his commander, he was then earmarked for transfer as lieutenant-colonel to a New Model Army regiment of foot, but like Barclay – and probably for the same reason, because as a Scot he had been directed by his government not to take up that service – he did not actually go on to serve in the New Model.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, 1. 47-8, 150.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ipsy, -</td><td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Ipsy</emph><br/>A captain in the Bristol garrison who was offered as a hostage when surrender was parleyed on 26 July 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">The Humble Petition of Major Hercules Langrish and Olymphas his Wife </emph>[1644?], sig. A3r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Bristol</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Irby, Sir Anthony</td><td><emph type="b">Sir Anthony Irby </emph>(1605-1682)<br/>Born eldest son and heir of Sir Anthony Irby of Whaplode, Lincolnshire, The family were landowners in southern Lincolnshire/Holland, with particular influence in and around Boston. Irby sat for Boston in almost every parliament between 1628 and 1681, including the Short and the Long parliaments and the second and third (but not the first) Protectorate parliaments.<br/>He held local office in Lincolnshire during the 1630s and was an opponent of some aspects of Charles I’s government both there and in the Long Parliament.<br/>In the 1642 army list, he is shown as a captain in John Browne’s regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army. Although his direct military career was limited, holding the (perhaps semi-honorary) rank of colonel he was a very active war-time administrator within the Eastern Association in general and in his native Lincolnshire in particular. Present at the siege of Crowland in spring 1643 and at least part of the company/regiment seems to have served with Fairfax in Yorkshire.<br/>Nonetheless, his moderation led to increasing divisions between Irby and more radical parliamentarians. He was ejected at Pride’s Purge and was probably an active royalist by the end of the 1650s.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock<emph type="i">, Army lists</emph>, 57; Keeler, <emph type="i">Long </emph><emph type="i">P</emph><emph type="i">arliament</emph>, 230-1; Spring <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.45.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Northern Army?</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ireland, Adam</td><td><emph type="b">Adam Ireland</emph><br/>Fifth son of George Ireland of Hutt and Hale, Lancashire, and his first wife Elizabeth, daughter and heir of Ralph Birkenhead of Crowton, Cheshire.<br/>Captain in the Lancashire regiment of foot of Colonel John Moore, identified from arrears owed to one of his soldiers. He was uncle to Gilbert Ireland, who served in the same regiment.<br/>Probably the Captain Ireland present at the siege of Chester, Dec. 1645 and Jan. 1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Vis. Lancs., 1664</emph>, 165; TNA, E121/5/7 (Duckenfeild, 6/5/1651); Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 265, 2. 382, 437-8, 510; Gratton, <emph type="i">Lancs. war effort</emph>, 291.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ireland, Gilbert</td><td><emph type="b">Gilbert Ireland </emph>(1624-1675)<br/>Of Hale Hall, Childwall, Lancashire. Eldest son of John Ireland of Hutt, Childwall parish and his wife Elizabeth Hayes. He married in 1646 Margaret, daughter and heiress of Thomas Ireland of Bewsey Hall, Warrington, Lancashire. His income in 1641 has been valued at &#xa3;1,000 per annum.<br/>Captain of horse (for which he was owed &#xa3;770 18s 8d in Oct. 1650) and later colonel of the Lancashire militia foot. In Jan. 1644 his quarters at Knowsley were attacked by the royalists. He was in the Liverpool garrison in June 1644 when the town was taken by Prince Rupert; possibly an officer in John Moore’s regiment.<br/>He was possibly at the siege of Chester in Dec. 1645 and Jan. 1646, though this is more likely to have been his uncle Adam. He was a captain in Jan. 1650.<br/>Commissioned colonel of a Lancashire militia regiment of foot on 22 Mar. 1650. Gratton notes as a sign of the Rump’s unpopularity amongst the Lancashire gentry, that ‘it was forced to rely upon moderate Presbyterians such as the ambitious Gilbert Ireland to fill the officer ranks’ (Gratton, <emph type="i">Lancashire war effort</emph>, 129). Indeed, though Ireland served in the third civil war, a list of leading local parliamentarians found in the earl of Derby’s papers suggested that he, like some other Lancashire Presbyterians, had not been wholly unsympathetic to the royalist rising. He was governor of Liverpool from 1655.<br/>From 1645 to 1648 Ireland was an active county committeeman. He was also a sequestrator – one of several complained of as being too soft on the royalists by Thomas Birch – and a magistrate. He was appointed high sheriff in Dec. 1647. He continued to serve in local government under the republic and Protectorate, was<br/>MP for Lancashire in 1654 and 1656 and for Liverpool in 1659, 1660 and 1661-75. In 1657 he voted for Cromwell to have the crown.<br/>Ireland was heavily implicated in Booth’s Rising in 1659.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1660-1690</emph>, 2.637-8; Gratton, <emph type="i">Lancs. war effort</emph>,<emph type="i"></emph>10, 94, 118, 129, 156, 180, 226, 289-90 Blackwood, <emph type="i">Lancashire g</emph><emph type="i">entry</emph>, 75; HMC, <emph type="i">Tenth Report, App. 4</emph>, 69-70, 102-3; <emph type="i">Moore Mss.</emph>, 167, 207; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 505;TNA, E121/4/8; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 105, 265; 2. 382, 437-8, 510; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-16</emph><emph type="i">60</emph> (forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ireland, Robert</td><td><emph type="b">Robert Ireland</emph><br/>Lieutenant in the company of Lieutenant-Colonel Thomas Gell in Sir John Gell’s regiment of foot in Derbyshire. In Nov. 1645 he was the company’s <emph type="i">de facto</emph> commander, when it was accused of having intimidated voters in the recruiter election which resulted in Thomas Gell’s election.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Slack, <emph type="i">Man at War</emph>, 144-5; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660 </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Derbyshire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ireton, -</td><td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Ireton</emph><br/>Captain of a troop of horse in the regiment of Colonel Ralph Assheton (unclear whether his colonel was Assheton senior or junior). An intriguing surname, but the only information as yet comes from identification from the arrears due to one of his troopers and he cannot be linked with (Cromwell’s son-in-law) Henry Ireton and his Nottinghamshire family.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, E121/5/7 (Duckenfeild, 6/5/1651).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ireton, Henry</td><td><emph type="b">Henry Ireton</emph><emph type="b" ></emph>(1611-1651).<emph type="b"></emph><br/>Born the eldest son but not heir of German Ireton of Attenborough, Nottinghamshire.<br/>Ireton raised a troop of horse at the outbreak of war, initially to protect and secure Nottingham, but he joined the earl of Essex and was present at the battle of Edgehill in Oct. 1642. During much of 1643 he served as major in Colonel Francis Thornhaugh’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army, but in late 1643 he and his troop transferred to Oliver Cromwell’s regiment of horse. He continued to serve in that role, fighting at Marston Moor and the second battle of Newbury, but also became quartermaster-general of the Eastern Association horse. In spring 1645 he became colonel of a regiment of horse in the New Model Army and became the Army’s commissary general, playing a prominent role in the campaign and battle of Naseby (where he was wounded) in summer 1645 and the mopping up of the South West and remaining royalist strongholds in 1645-6, in army politics in 1646-8 – he also became a Recruiter MP in the Long Parliament in autumn 1645 – and in Fairfax’s operation in Kent and Essex and against Colchester in summer 1648.<br/>He supported and was probably a driving force behind Pride’s Purge and the trial of the king; he was a regicide. He campaigned with Cromwell in Ireland in 1649-50 and in 1650 he succeeded his father-in-law – having married Cromwell’s daughter Bridget in 1646 – as commander-in-chief of the New Model forces in, and as lord deputy of, Ireland, down to his death from the plague outside Limerick in Nov. 1651.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 53-4. 64, 74, 78, 84, 95-6, 109<emph type="i">.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">E</emph><emph type="i">arl of Essex; E</emph><emph type="i">astern Association; New Model Army</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Ireton, Thomas</td><td><emph type="b">Thomas Ireton</emph><br/>Captain-Lieutenant (but, given that his nominal Captain, Valentine Walton senior, was colonel of another regiment) in effect commander of a troop within the earl of Manchester’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army. He entered the New Model Army and served as captain of Sidney’s, later Rich’s regiment of horse.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.54; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 52, 62, 73, 83, 95, 107.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model Army</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Isbourne, -</td><td><emph type="b">- Isbourne</emph><br/>By spring 1644 lieutenant in Robert Shephard’s company in Sir Miles Hobart’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.42.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Isham, Henry</td><td><emph type="b">Henry Isham</emph><br/>Lieutenant in John Hampden’s/Thomas Tyrrell’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642-4. He was lieutenant in Lieutenant-Colonel William Barriffe’s company in that regiment in 1643, and was still lieutenant in the regiment on 2 Apr. 1644. By May Isham was a reformado lieutenant of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 46; TNA, SP28/10/191, SP28/11/369, SP28/14/219, SP28/15/247.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Izod, Thomas </td><td><emph type="b">Thomas Izod</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Anthony Markham’s troop in Edward Rossiter’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army. Although he appears initially not to have transferred as an officer to the New Model, in 1647 he appears as a lieutenant in Rossiter’s, later Twistleton’s, New Model Army regiment of horse.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.92; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 123, 141.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model Army</emph></td></tr>
</table>
</section>
</report>
