<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE report SYSTEM "DTD/report.dtd">
<report id="154162" pubid="1496">
<title>U</title><subtitle />
<section id="s1"><head>Surnames beginning 'U'</head>

    <table id="t1">
<tr><td>Umfrevile, William </td><td><emph type="b">William Umfrevile</emph><br/>At its muster, in Nov. 1643, captain in Colonel Thomas Honeywood’s regiment of foot formed from the Essex militia, part of the Eastern Association Army that contributed to the siege of Reading in spring 1643, the siege of Greenland House in summer 1644 and probably to some other actions in which the Army was involved.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.32.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Underwood, -</td><td><emph type="b">- Underwood</emph><br/>Cornet.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, 377.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Underwood, Francis</td><td><emph type="b">Francis Underwood</emph><br/>Captain of a company in a regiment of foot which Oliver Cromwell and later Colonel Francis Russell commanded in their capacity as governors of the Isle of Ely and which probably originated as an auxiliary regiment of the Cambridgeshire militia. Later became major and then lieutenant-colonel, probably of the same regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.28.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Underwood, Joseph</td><td><emph type="b">Joseph Underwood</emph><br/>His claim for arrears, 18 Apr. 1647, gives his career:<br/>22 Sept. 1644 to 7 Feb. 1645, private soldier under Captain Dewy in Colonel Browne’s [Brune’s] regiment [of horse]; 8 Feb. to 15 Mar. 1645, captain of a troop of horse under Major Haynes in the same regiment; 4 Apr. 1645 to 4 May 1646, captain-lieutenant to Colonel Browne.<br/>Underdown suggests that he may have been married and a householder by the time he enlisted.<br/>In 1651 he was captain of a company in Colonel Heane’s regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 17, 22; Underdown, <emph type="i">Fire from Heaven</emph>, 206-7; Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, 240-1.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Underwood, Joseph</td><td><emph type="b">Joseph Underwood</emph><br/>Captain, of Dorchester. His claim for arrears, 18 Apr. 1647, gives his career:<br/>22 Sept. 1644-7 Feb. 1645: private soldier under Captain Dewy in Colonel Browne’s regiment [of horse]<br/>8 Feb.-15 Mar. 1645: captain of a troop of horse under Major Haynes in Browne’s regiment.<br/>4 Apr. 1645-4 May 1646: captain-lieutenant to Colonel Browne.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, 240-1.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Underwood, William</td><td><emph type="b">William Underwood</emph><br/>Fourth captain in the Blue regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel Thomas Adams) in summer 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Thrale 1642.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Unite, John</td><td><emph type="b">John Unite</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel John Fiennes’s regiment of horse in Oxfordshire from summer 1644 onwards.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army</emph>, 54.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxfordshire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Upton, John</td><td><emph type="b">John Upton</emph><br/>In 1642 listed as cornet in George Thompson’s troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 51.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Upton, John</td><td><emph type="b">John Upton</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lieutenant-Colonel Alexander Newton’s company in Henry Bradshaw’s regiment of foot in the Cheshire militia at the battle of Worcester (3 Sept. 1651).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Earwaker, <emph type="i">East Cheshire</emph>, 2.64-8.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Upton, Richard</td><td><emph type="b">Richard Upton</emph><br/>Ensign in Sir William Fairfax’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 44.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Urin [Ursin], Hans</td><td><emph type="b">Hans Urin [Ursin]</emph><br/>A continental soldier, who served first under Sir Hugh Cholmley at Scarborough, but went to Beverley when the latter defected.<br/>Urin reappeared in the forces before Chester in 1645 as an officer (probably captain) in Sir Thomas Norcliffe’s regiment of horse. He may have joined the regiment when it was newly formed in spring 1644 and would have known Norcliffe from Scarborough.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 405; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 421, 522.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire; Northern Army (Fairfax)</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Urry, Alexander</td><td><emph type="b">Alexander Urry</emph><br/>Major in Lord Robartes’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642, serving in the regiment from the start.<br/>Captured at the second battle of Newbury.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 37.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Urry, Sir John</td><td><emph type="b">Sir John Urry </emph>(died 1650)<br/>Born the son of John Urry of Pitfitchie, Aberdeenshire. He fought in Germany during the Thirty Years War, returning to his native Scotland in the late 1630s and becoming lieutenant-colonel in the Covenanter army of 1639. In 1641 he was allegedly invited to join the plot against leading Covenanters known as the Incident but he refused and revealed details of the supposed plot. By summer 1642 he was in England and was given command of a troop of horse in Wharton’s Army earmarked for service in Ireland, but instead became a captain in Balfour’s regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army, fighting in the campaign and battle of Edgehill. Although earmarked for promotion to major at the start of 1643, instead he changed sides and joined the king’s army, prominent in campaigning in Oxfordshire and Buckinghamshire and knighted by the king. He took part in Rupert’s campaign and battle of Marston Moor, but later in summer 1644 he tried to rejoin the parliamentarian or Covenanter forces. He was arrested and held prisoner in London for a time, but by the end of Oct. 1644 he was back in the parliamentarian army, before transferring to the Scottish Covenanter army early in 1645 and campaigning against Montrose in Scotland, only to change sides once more and join Montrose, going into exile on the continent with him in the latter half of 1646. He returned to Scotland in 1648 in support of the Scottish-royalist army and took part in the Preston campaign, in which he was captured but managed to escape and return to the continent. He accompanied Montrose on his Scottish campaign in 1650, but was captured and executed in Edinburgh in May 1650.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph><emph type="i">;</emph> Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 47;<emph type="i"></emph>TNA, SP28/2a/95, 3a/142; Furgol, <emph type="i">Covenanting armies</emph>, esp. 240-1, 421-2.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
<tr><td>Usher, George</td><td><emph type="b">George Usher</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lord Wharton’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td></tr>
</table>
</section>
</report>
