<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE report SYSTEM "DTD/report.dtd">
<report id="154154" pubid="1496">
    <title>M</title>
    <subtitle/>
    <section id="s1">
        <head>Surnames beginning 'M'</head>
       
        <table id="t1">
            <tr>
                <td>Mackworth, Humphrey</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Humphrey Mackworth </emph>(1603-1654)<br/>Born the eldest child
                    and only son of Richard Mackworth (died 1617) of Betton Strange, Shropshire, a
                    modest landed family.<br/>Humphrey practised law and by the 1630s was prominent
                    in the administration of Shrewsbury, as alderman and legal advisor. His godly
                    religious views inclined him to parliament and he supported the war effort. From
                    1643 he was appointed to Shropshire committees, even though the county was then
                    in royalist hands. By summer 1643 he was captain in Thomas Mytton’s regiment of
                    horse, based at Wem during the autumn and on into early 1644, when Mackworth’s
                    troop was described by the royalists as ‘broken’. Deemed by the Committee of
                    Both Kingdoms to be vital to parliament’s still fragile hold over parts of
                    Shropshire. In 1644 he was promoted to colonel early in 1645 and although he
                    does not seem to have taken part in the capture of Shrewsbury in Feb. 1645, he
                    was soon based there and in command of a regiment of foot raised largely from
                    militia units. He was present at the fight at Stokesay on 8 June 1645 and
                    commanded Shrewsbury units at the siege of Shrawardine Castle in July. By summer
                    1646 he had been confirmed as governor of Shrewsbury and commander in chief of
                    all the ‘standing companies’ in Shropshire. He was very active on Shropshire
                    county committes from 1643 onwards.<br/>He was active in ensuring the security
                    of Shropshire in the face of renewed royalist threats in 1648 and 1651. He also
                    acquired a string of offices – the recorderships of Shrewsbury, Wenlock and
                    Bridgnorth, attorney general for North Wales and deputy chief justice of the
                    Chester circuit. In Feb. 1654 and despite hithero limited experience in national
                    government, he was appointed to the Protectoral Council of State and became a
                    very diligent and active member of the Council, down to his sudden death at his
                    Whitehall lodgings in Dec. 1654. He was buried in Westminster Abbey but his was
                    one of a number of corpses exhumed and removed at the Restoration.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Dore, <emph
                        type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2. 394; HMC, <emph type="i">13th
                        Report, Appendix 1,</emph> 141-3; BL, Add. Ms. 18981, f. 69; <emph type="i"
                        >CSPD, 1644</emph>, 514; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1644-45</emph>, 259; <emph
                        type="i">CSPD, 1645-47</emph>, 441; H. Johnstone, ‘Two governors of
                    Shrewsbury during the great civil war and interregnum’, <emph type="i">English
                        Historical Review</emph>, 26 (1911); <emph type="i">Mercurius
                    Civicus</emph>, 12-18 June 1645; <emph type="i">The Kingdom’s Weekly
                        Intelligencer</emph>, 1-8 July 1645; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, IV, 614, V,
                    122; <emph type="i">Intelligence from Shropshire of Three Great Victories
                        obtained by the Forces of Shrewsburie</emph> (1645).<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Shropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maghull, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Maghull</emph><br/>A lieutenant, then a captain, in John
                    Moore’s Lancashire regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Gratton, <emph type="i">Lancs. war effort</emph>, 291.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maguire, Rosse</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Rosse </emph><emph type="b">Maguire</emph> (died ?1647)<br/>A
                    corporal in Captain Master’s troop of horse; later lieutenant in Sir William
                    Waller’s regiment of horse; and by Nov. 1645 captain-lieutenant to the colonel’s
                    troop in Edward Cooke’s regiment of horse. He remained there until the
                    disbandment of the Massey brigade and was a signatory to the petition of its
                    officers in July 1647. A few weeks later he was convicted at the Old Bailey of
                    murder. Colonel Henry Sanderson appealed to the Commons for his reprieve, but
                    they merely laid debate on it to one side on 6 Sept. It is not certain whether
                    he was hanged or not.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Temple, ‘Massey
                    Brigade’, 438-9, 441; Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 147; <emph
                        type="i">JHC</emph>, 5.293.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Waller (Southern Association); Massey Brigade</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mainwaring, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Mainwaring</emph><br/>Perhaps of the family of Ightfield,
                    Shropshire, a captain in command of one of the companies of Shropshire foot at
                    the siege of Lichfield in spring 1646, on 26 May ordered to march to
                        Worcester.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Carr and Atherton, <emph
                        type="i">Brereton Staffs</emph>., 280.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Shropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mainwaring [Manwaring], Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Mainwaring [Manwaring] </emph>(born 1605/1606, alive in
                    1666)<br/>Of Kermincham, Cheshire. Eldest son of Henry Mainwaring of Kermincham
                    (died 1637x39) and his wife May, daughter of Anthony Kinnarsley of Loxley,
                    Staffordshire. He married Frances, fourth sister and coheir of Sir Edward Fitton
                    of Gawsworth, Cheshire. His son Roger married Sarah, daughter of Randle
                    Ashenhurst of Ashenhurst, Derbyshire.<br/>An active JP in Cheshire in the 1630s.
                    In 1641 Mainwaring was a supporter of the pro-episcopal and pro-court Sir Thomas
                    Aston, but in 1642 chose to support parliament. In Dec. he raised the country
                    and saw off the earl of Derby’s attempted venture into Cheshire and expelled the
                    royalists from Macclesfield. Reinforced by Manchester forces, he compelled the
                    royalist commissioners of array to flee and on 10 Dec. garrisoned Nantwich.
                    Having established a position of strength, Mainwaring was one of the two
                    parliamentarian negotiators for the very short-lived cessation of arms within
                    the county which was negotiated at Bunbury on 23 Dec. 1642, and which was
                    followed by both sides.<br/>However, a month later, when Sir William Brereton
                    came north as commander-in-chief in Chesh, Mainwaring brought his independent
                    troop of horse to the headquarters at Nantwich.<br/>In Jan. 1644 Mainwaring was
                    one of the commanders who came to the battle of Nantwich. However (like the
                    other captains who had come to Brereton in Jan. 1643), he was evidently becoming
                    more distanced from the more militant war being fought by Sir William.<br/>On 7
                    May 1644 the Commons resolved that Mainwaring and another Cheshire man active
                    early in the war be deprived of their offices: ‘Resolved, &amp;c. that Henry
                    Manwaring, and Henry Vernon, Esquires, two deputy lieutenants of Cheshire, in
                    regard of their Disservice to the Parliament in many Particulars, be forthwith
                    discharged and removed from their said Places, and other Power of Command in any
                    military Way, in or gathering or receiving Monies: And that all Horses, Arms,
                    Ammunition, and Money, now under their or either of their Commands, belonging to
                    the State, be, upon Demand, delivered up to Sir Wm. Brereton, to be by him
                    disposed of and employed for the said Service of King and Parliament: And that
                    the said Persons be called to account for what Monies, Arms, and Ammunition they
                    have; and accordingly to restore the same for the publick Service’ (<emph
                        type="i">JHC</emph>, 3.484).<br/>The ‘disservice’ remains obscure, and the
                    resolution does not seem to have taken effect immediately, perhaps because of
                    the crisis in the north. On 25 May Mainwaring’s and Robert Duckenfeild’s
                    regiments were drawn up at Stockport, powerless to oppose the march of Prince
                    Rupert; on 30 June his regiment was part of the force that marched from Nantwich
                    to relieve Thomas Mytton at Oswestry. On 30 Apr. 1645 Mainwaring was still
                    formally named as a colonel of a regiment of foot of four companies and ‘about
                    160 men all countrymen’ (Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1.
                    326). Nevertheless, Dore found no evidence of Mainwaring ‘still exercising
                    military command’ in 1645 (Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1.
                    332).<br/>Mainwaring, like the other gentleman who had brought their troops to
                    Brereton at Nantwich, had by summer 1645 withdrawn from military service. The
                    doubts about his loyalty were pursued when Mainwaring found himself facing
                    sequestration as a delinquent, although he was cleared.<br/>In 1659 Mainwaring
                    took part in the Booth Rising, as a colonel charged with recruiting in Northwich
                    Hundred.<br/>In Oct. 1646 Mainwaring had been admitted, alongside his kinsman
                    Elias Ashmole, as a freemason at Warrington, the first known Masonic lodge in
                        England.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton
                        letter books</emph>, 1. 326, 332, 420; Morrill, <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph>, 9, 16, 53, 66, 71, 80, 215, 272, 311; <emph type="i">Civil
                        war in Cheshire</emph>, 29-34, 36-7, 116-7117, 130, 134, 241-3, 245, 247;
                    HMC, <emph type="i">Portland manuscripts</emph>, 1.94-6; <emph type="i">Vis.
                        Cheshire, 1613</emph>, 161; <emph type="i">Vis. Cheshire, 1666</emph>, 73;
                    Ormerod, <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph>, 3.i.80; D. Stevenson, <emph type="i"
                        >The origins of freemasonry: Scotland’s century, 1590-1710 </emph>(1988),
                        219.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>

            <tr>
                <td>Mainwaring, Philomen</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Philomen Mainwaring </emph><br/>Dore identifies him as of Great
                    Warford, Cheshire, illegitimate half-bro. of Colonel Henry Mainwaring (Henry was
                    the eldest son of Henry Mainwaring, died 1639, and his first wife; Philomen was
                    the son of Henry and his second wife, Felicia, daughter of Thomas Baskerville,
                    but born before their marriage.) He acquired the estate at Great Warford, where
                    he died c. 1674, through his marriage to Margaret Parsons, daughter and coheir
                    of a Macclesfield alderman.<br/>Dore makes a very strong case that Mainwaring
                    was lieutenant in Captain Humphrey Bulkeley’s troop of horse in Brereton’s horse
                    regiment, and that following the capture of Bulkeley and most of his troop near
                    Wrexham on 29 Apr. 1645, Mainwaring was probably transferred to Myddelton’s
                    forces in Wrexham, and was captured in Oct. 1645 when part of that army under
                    Colonel John Carter was attacked at Eccleston. Thereafter he was linked with
                    Bulkeley in the prolonged negotiations for an exchange and was evidently finally
                    released in Jan. 1646., though in the interim, he managed to smuggle out
                    information about the state of Chester; on 21 Dec. 1645 his letter to Brereton
                    began, ‘I have thought good to acquaint your honour (having a convenient and
                    trusty messenger) with what news my intelligencers have informed me’ (Dore,
                        <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2. 407-8).<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2.
                    99-100, 407-8, 463, 480-1.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire; North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mainwaring, Randall</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Randall Mainwaring</emph> (died 1652)<br/>Born Whitmore,
                    Staffordshire, son of Edward Mainwaring. He married in London in 1618, became
                    active within the Grocers’ Company and became a colonial trader in partnership
                    with members of his wife’s family, the Hawes. Treasurer of the Company of the
                    Artillery Garden (now the Honourable Artillery Company), 1631-5. Prominent in
                    radical City politics during the 1640s, became a member of the London militia
                    committee and a very active supporter of parliament’s war effort.<br/>‘His Shope
                    is In Cheape Side neare Ironmonger lane by Colonel Towse’ (BL, Harl. 986, p.
                    2).<br/>Captain in London Trained Bands in 1639.<br/>Major of the Red regiment,
                    London Trained Bands (Colonel Thomas Atkin) in 1642, and its lieutenant-colonel
                    by 26 Sept. 1643. Appointed sergeant-major-general of the City of London in Oct.
                    1642 to replace Philip Skippon. Colonel of a regiment of Redcoats (1642-Jan.
                    1644) raised for the earl of Warwick’s short-lived reserve army raised to cover
                    London, which, however, survived to be used to police the metropolis under
                    Mainwaring as sergeant-major-general. He was with them at the first battle of
                    Newbury.<br/>He died in autumn 1652.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Overton 1642; Thrale 1642;<emph type="i"/>Nagel,
                    ‘London militia’, 58, 59, 85, 86, 87, 316; BL, Harl. 986, p. 2.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mainwaring, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert</emph> <emph type="b">Mainwaring</emph>
                    (1607-1652)<br/>Born 1607 in London, son of William Mainwaring, Citizen and
                    merchant tailor. Robert became a wealthy officer of the London Customs House and
                    was noted by Symonds as being of the Custom House, living in Aldermanbury.
                    Addmitted to the Company of the Artillery Garden (now the Honourable Artillery
                    Company) in 1642.<br/>Recorded in a spy’s report of a Trained Bands muster in
                    Sept. 1643 as Third captain of the Green regiment, London Trained Bands. Richard
                    Symonds annotates: ‘Hath a Troope of horse besides &amp; quitted this
                    Capt[aincy]’ (BL, Harl. 986, p. 38).<br/>The troop was evidently in Colonel
                    Edmund Harvey’s regiment of London horse, of which he was Major by Dec. 1643,
                    when he sought to stem the flight of his troops at a skirmish in Olney,
                    Bedfordshire, reportedly breaking his pistol on their heads, and still the
                    regiment’s Major on 9 May 1644. Money was owed for the cost of quartering part
                    of his troop in Grub Street, 11 Jan.-26 May 1644. On 24 July 1644 he received 14
                    days’ pay for the regiment and for his troop. He was still with the regiment
                    when it was disbanded in spring 1645.<br/>He later served as a common councillor
                    for Cripplegate Without and within the sixth London classis. He was appointed to
                    the London militia committee during the attempted Presbyterian coup of 1647, but
                    was removed after the restoration of army and Independent control. He died at
                    his home in Grub Street in 1652.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; BL, Harl. 986, p. 38; G. Paine, <emph type="i">A
                        true relation of all the skirmishes between our forces and the Cavaliers at
                        Owlney </emph>(1643), 2; TNA, SP28/15/66, SP28/17/119; <emph type="i">CSPD,
                        1644</emph>, 155.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Malbon [Mauberne], George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Malbon [Mauberne]</emph><br/>Son of Thomas Malbon
                    (1578-1658) of Bradley and Nantwich, gentleman,, whose manuscript ‘Memorial of
                    the Civil War’ is reprinted in <emph type="i">Cheshire tracts</emph>, 23-225;
                    brother of Thomas Malbon.<br/>Captain of a company of Nantwich townsmen in
                    George Booth’s regiment of foot in Sir William Brereton’s Army by 30 Apr. 1645,
                    the company shortly after discontented after Booth resigned for want of
                    pay.<br/>Commissioned Major in Thomas Croxton’s militia regiment of foot, 22
                    Aug. 1650.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire
                        tracts</emph>, xii-xiv, 136-7, 148; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter
                        books</emph>, 1. 325, 329-30, 371, 372; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>,
                        510.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Malbon [Mauberne], Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Malbon [Mauberne]</emph><br/>Son of Thomas Malbon
                    (1578-1658) of Bradley and Nantwich, Cheshire, gentleman, whose manuscript
                    ‘Memorial of the Civil War’ is reprinted in <emph type="i">Cheshire
                        tracts</emph>, 23-225; brother of George Malbon.<br/>Captain of a company of
                    Nantwich townsmen in George Booth’s regiment of foot in Sir William Brereton’s
                    Army by 30 Apr. 1645, the company shortly after became discontented after Booth
                    resigned for want of pay.<br/>Malbon and his brother, both captains, fought at
                    taking of Cholmondeley Castle, 7 July 1644.<br/>Commissioned captain in Thomas
                    Croxton’s militia regiment of foot, 22 Aug. 1650.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire tracts</emph>, xii-xiv, 136-7,
                    148, 225; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 325, 329-30,
                    371; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 510.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Malbon, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Malbon</emph><br/>Ensign to Major Kett in Myddelton’s North
                    Wales Army, as proved by a pay warrant of 6 Apr. 1644 for &#xa3;5.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346, no. 85.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mall, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mall</emph><br/>By early 1645, major in Valentine Walton’s
                    regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army; he continued to serve in that
                    capacity after John Hobart had taken command of the regiment in spring
                        1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.104.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mallery, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Mallery</emph><br/>In Sept. 1642 lieutenant to Captain
                    Cosby in the regiment of foot which formed part of the earl of Essex’s Army
                    under the earl of Stamford and which then formed the core of Edward Massey’s
                    garrison and army at Gloucester.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey
                    and Turton, <emph type="i">War</emph><emph type="i"> in the West</emph>,<emph
                        type="i"/>6.646-7.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mallory, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Mallory</emph><br/>Captain. He was not one of the original
                    captains in the earl of Stamford’s regiment of foot in 1642, nor is he listed
                    amongst the officers at Gloucester in Apr. 1643. He had joined by Aug. 1643, and
                    fought during the siege of Gloucester, leading a sally on 14 Aug.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 6. 642-6; <emph type="i">Bibliotheca</emph>, 46, 214.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Glo</emph><emph type="i"
                        >ucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manaton, Samson</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Samson Manaton</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Christopher Burgh’s
                    company in William Bampfield’s regiment of foot in Lord Wharton’s Army for
                    Ireland in 1642. Instead, he went with Bampfield’s regiment as ensign into the
                    earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock,
                        <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 70, 40.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manby, William, junior</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William </emph><emph type="b">Manby, </emph><emph type="b"
                        >junior</emph><br/>Son of William Manby senior and his wife Alice, daughter
                    of Mr Long of Wiltshire. Of St Helen’s Bishopsgate.<br/>During the Presbyterian
                    domination of the London militia committee, Manby junior was captain in the
                    White regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel Joseph Vaughan). This had been his
                    fa’s regiment, so perhaps he had held unrecorded lower commissioned ranks before
                    then. A Presbyterian satire implies that he was still in the regiment later that
                    year, after his father had been reinstated, suggesting that ‘the Puppy his
                    Sonne’ be made Major (<emph type="i">A paire of spectacles for the Citie</emph>,
                    (1648), 9).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Vis. London,
                        1633-5</emph>, 2.76; Nagel, ‘London militia’, citing pay warrants in TNA,
                    SP28/237; <emph type="i">A paire of spectacles for the Citie</emph> (1648),
                        9.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manby, William, senior</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Manby,</emph> <emph type="b">senior</emph> (died 1660)<br/>Lieutenant-colonel. Admitted to the Company of
                    the Artillery Garden (now the Honourable Artillery Company) in 1618. Son of
                    William Manby of London, fishmonger, and his wife Alice, daughter of Thomas Nash
                    of Evesham, Worcestershire. He married Alice, daughter of Mr Long of Wiltshire.
                    Father of William Manby, junior.<br/>Buried 8 Dec. 1660 in St Helen’s
                    Bishopsgate, where his rank of lieutenant-colonel is noted in the parish
                    register.<br/>Member of Fishmongers’ company, treasurer of the Artillery Garden,
                    1639, and noted as clerk of the Leathersellers’ Hall by Richard Symonds (BL,
                    Harl. 986, p. 14).<br/>Lieutenant in the Red regiment, London Trained Bands
                    (Colonel Thomas Atkin), 1642; by Sept. 1643. Third captain of the White
                    regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel Isaac Penington) and by Oct. 1646
                    lieutenant-colonel of the same White regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel
                    Thomas Player). In 1647 the Presbyterian militia committee put him out in favour
                    of Robert Thomson, but he was re-instated later that year by the Independent
                    militia committee.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Vis.
                        London, 1633-5</emph>, 2.76;<emph type="i"> Reg. St Helen’s
                        Bishopsgate</emph>, 309; Nagel, ‘London militia’, 316-8; Barriffe, <emph
                        type="i">Mars</emph>, sig. 2r; BL, Harl. 986, p. 14; <emph type="i">A paire
                        of spectacles for the Citie</emph> (1648), 9.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manestey, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Manestey</emph><br/>Captain in the earl of Manchester’s
                    regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army, serving until the regiment
                    disbanded. He became a captain in Sir Thomas Fairfax’s regiment of foot in the
                    New Model Army, down to his death in autumn 1645.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.63;
                    Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 43, 55.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association; New Model
                    Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maning, Samuel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Samuel Maning</emph><br/>Colonel’s ensign in the Yellow regiment,
                    London Trained Bands (Colonel Sir John Wollaston) in summer 1642.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Thrale 1642.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manley, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Manley </emph>(c.1622-1699)<br/>The third son of Cornelius
                    Manley of Erbistock, Cheshire (died 1623). His elder brothers Francis (later
                    chief justice of the Carmarthen circuit) and Roger (army officer and historian,
                    see <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>) were both royalists. The surviving pay
                    warrants, covering the periods June to Dec. 1643 and May 1644 to June 1645, give
                    no clue to any rank (frequently, even if the rank is not given in the warrant
                    itself or the signed acquittance, it is noted on the clerk’s endorsement on the
                    back, but not in Manley’s case). He evidently rose to the rank of Captain, the
                    rank with which he appears in a pass to travel abroad in 1652 and in the
                    complaint against him by the sheriff of Denbighshire in 1659 when he and Captain
                    Sontley were active against local royalists (<emph type="i">CSPD, 1652</emph>,
                    555; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1659-1660</emph>, 159).<br/>Apprenticed to a skinner
                    in London in 1639. Greaves dates to 1643 his public attack on infant baptism, on
                    the clergy as unlawful and unchristian and his claim that he was as much an
                    apostle as Paul. He married Isaac Dorislaus’s daughter and was
                    Postmaster-General, 1653-5 and MP for Denbigh in 1659. A loyal servant of the
                    republic in Denbighshire and persecuted after the Restoration for dissent, he
                    returned to London as a brewer, was active in radical Whig politics and was on
                    the fringe of the Rye House Plot and served as a major in Monmouth’s Army. MP
                    for Bridport in 1689.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Oxford DNB</emph>; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1660-1690</emph>,
                    3.13-4; Greaves and Zaller, <emph type="i">BDBR</emph>,<emph type="i"/>2.211-2;
                    Tucker, <emph type="i">Denbighshire Officers</emph>, 69; TNA, SP28/346; <emph
                        type="i">CSPD, 1652</emph>, 555; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1659-1660</emph>,
                        159.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North
                    Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mann, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Mann</emph><br/>Captain of dragoons in
                        Kent.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 70.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Kent;
                        Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mann, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Mann</emph><br/>By early 1644 captain in Valentine
                    Walton’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army; he continued to serve
                    in that capacity after John Hobart had taken command of the regiment in spring
                        1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.104.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manwaring, Andrew</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Andrew Manwaring</emph><br/>Captain in Sir William Waller’s
                    regiment of foot (later of dragoons) from at least 16 Nov. 1643 to Dec. 1644.
                    Perhaps the Captain Mainwaring, captain of a troop of horse in Waller’s Western
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph><emph type="i"/>149; Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of
                        the West</emph>, 7.716.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Waller (Southern Association); Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Manyford, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Manyford</emph><br/>Cornet.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, 377.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marbury, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Marbury</emph><br/>An officer in Brereton’s Cheshire Army.
                    Marbury was commissioned Major and had been Major in Brooke’s regiment of foot
                    (though no longer by Apr. 1645). Half-brother to William Marbury of Marbury,
                    deputy-lieutenant and enemy of Brereton, and brother to the latter’s heir
                    Thomas, he seems to have shared William’s alienation (although Dore suggests to
                    a lesser extent than the Booths). In Nov. 1645 he was one of three officers,
                    along with Captains Massey and Whitney of Booth’s regiment, whose arrest was
                    ordered as ‘it appears that they are dangerous and do much disturb the peace of
                    the county’.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton
                        letter books</emph>, 2. 225.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>March, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William March</emph><br/>A captain in John Booth’s Lancashire
                        regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Gratton, <emph type="i"
                        >Lancs. war effort</emph>, 285.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Margery, Ralph</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Ralph Margery</emph><br/>From the raising of the troop in his
                    native Suffolk in autumn 1643, he served as captain of the troop in Oliver
                    Cromwell’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army, through the
                    absorption of the troop in Colonel Pye’s regiment of horse in the New Model
                    Army; Margery continued to serve as captain in that regiment (by then under
                    Rich) until 1653.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 1.23; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model
                        Army</emph>, I, 53, 63, 74, 83, 95, 108.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Markham, Anthony</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Anthony Markham</emph><br/>Brother of Henry Markham. Captain in
                    Edward Rossiter’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army and stayed
                    with the regiment when it transferred to the New Model Army. He left the
                    regiment in 1648 and in 1649 he succeeded his brother Henry as governor of
                    Belvoir Castle.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 2.91; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model
                        Army</emph>, I, 52, 62, 73, 83, 94.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model
                    Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Markham, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Markham</emph><br/>Brother of Anthony Markham and, like
                    him, having served in Rossiter’s horse regiment in the Eastern Association Army,
                    he transferred with it into the New Model and by the end of 1646 was a captain
                    in the regiment. He left the regiment in 1647 and between Nov. 1647 and Jan.
                    1649, holding the rank of Major, he was governor of Belvoir Castle. He served in
                    Ireland for much of the 1650s.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Wanklyn,
                        <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 73, 83.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">;
                        New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Markland, Gerrard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Gerrard Markland</emph><br/>Markland came from a family of
                    mercers in Wigan, Lancashire captain of a troop in the Lancashire regiment of
                    horse of Colonel Ralph Assheton, senior, later of Colonel Nicholas Shuttleworth.
                    He was owed arrears of &#xa3;59 17s &#x2157;d and of &#xa3;843 19s 1¼d in Oct.
                    1650.<br/>In Feb. 1644 Markland brought the first summons from Fairfax to the
                    countess of Derby to surrender Lathom House. He later served at the siege of
                    Chester.<br/>In 1659 Markland joined Booth’s Rising.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, E121/4/8; <emph type="i">Lancashire </emph><emph
                        type="i">military proceedings</emph>, 163; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton
                        letter books</emph>, 2. 437-8.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marr, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Marr</emph><br/>Ensign in Major
                    Archibald’s company in Sir William Waller’s regiment of dragoons.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        145<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marriott, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Marriott</emph><br/>In late 1644, cornet in the colonel’s
                    own troop in Sir Samuel Luke’s Bedfordshire-based regiment of horse.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring<emph type="i">, Waller’s a</emph><emph
                        type="i">rmy</emph>, 92.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Bedfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marrow, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Marrow</emph><br/>Captain in Viscount Saye and Sele’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 30.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marrow, Peter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Peter Marrow</emph><br/>Captain in Sir John Seaton’s/George
                    Melve’s regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army, from or by 30 Nov.
                    1642 to at least early Mar. 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA,
                    SP28/4/361, SP28/5/205, 206, 334.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marsden, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Marsden</emph><br/>Lieutenant, and later captain, of a
                    company in Richard Shuttleworth’s (later Ughtred Shuttleworth’s) regiment of
                    foot in Lancashire. He was owed arrears of 	&#xa3;632 16s 17&#xbd;d in May
                    1659.<br/>Whilst a lieutenant, Marsden fought with distinction at the defeat of
                    the earl of Derby at Whalley, 20 Apr. 1643: ‘Amongst those that came in to
                    them…was Marsden then a lieutenant after mad a captaine, a man of courage and
                    hardie spirit. He incouradged the souldiers much with manly words to goe one,
                    God would fight for them, and the like’ (<emph type="i">Warr in
                        Lancashire</emph>, 33). Commissioned captain in Thomas Birch’s militia
                    regiment of foot in Lancashire, 16 Aug. 1650.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, E121/4/8; <emph type="i">Warr in Lancashire</emph>,
                    33; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 509.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marsh, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Marsh</emph><br/>A captain in Cheshire. He is mentioned in a
                    passing reference, dated Warrington, 10 Oct. 1644, to goods taken up to ‘Captain
                        Marshes’.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/225, f.
                        6.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marsh, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Marsh</emph><br/>Of Shenley, Hertfordshire, and owner of a
                    St Albans inn. In 1643 captain in and then lieutenant-colonel of one of the
                    militia-based regiments of foot in Hertfordshire.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: A. Thompson, <emph type="i">The Impact of the First
                        </emph><emph type="i">Civil War on Hertfordshire, 1642-47</emph> (2007),
                        xxiii.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Hertfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marshall, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Marshall</emph><br/>A captain serving
                    with Sir William Waller’s army in June and July 1644. Possibly the same Captain
                    Marshall who was in Christopher Potley’s/David Leighton’s regiment of
                        foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> app. 2, p. 3.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marshall, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Marshall</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Thomas
                    Essex’s regiment of foot in 1643. He was accused of involvement in the royalist
                    plot to betray Bristol to the king’s army in the published confession of Robert
                    Yeamans. He is there described as commanding the sergeant-major’s
                        company.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph
                        type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 6.650-l; Seyer, <emph type="i"
                        >Bristol</emph>,<emph type="i"/>389.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Bristol</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marshall, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Marshall</emph><br/>Of Stokesley, Yorkshire (North Riding), a
                    parliamentarian lieutenant in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 95.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marshall, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Marshall </emph><br/>Captain in
                    Christopher Potley’s/David Leighton’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        113.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marshall, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Marshall</emph><br/>Ensign in the Colonel’s company in
                    Edward King’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 1.47.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Marshall, Lewis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Lewis Marshall</emph><br/>In 1643-4 lieutenant in Francis De
                    Latoure’s troop in Waller’s regiment of horse. Although cashiered from that
                    regiment for abusing his Captain, by the beginning of 1645 he had become
                    lieutenant in Francis Duett’s troop in Edmund Ludlow’s regiment of
                        horse.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 91, 147.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martin, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Martin</emph><br/>In Apr. 1645, on the eve of its disbandment,
                    lieutenant in William Wade’s company in the regiment of foot in the Eastern
                    Association Army then commanded by Sir Thomas Hoogan and formerly by Sir John
                        Palgrave.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 2.80.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martin, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">– Martin</emph><br/><emph type="b"/>Cornet, Captain Newdigate’s troop
                    of horse.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph
                        type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 5.531.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martin, Gabriel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Gabriel Martin</emph><br/>Early in 1645 he probably became a
                    captain in the earl of Essex’s own regiment of horse, commanded by Stapleton,
                    succeeding Lionel Copley, to whom he had been Lieutenant. Like several officers
                    of that regiment in the earl of Essex’s Army, he transferred to the New Model
                    Army in spring 1645, becoming a captain in Thomas Sheffield’s New Model horse
                    regiment and serving in that capacity until summer 1647.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, 1. 51,
                    61, 72, 82, 150<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex;
                        New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martin, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Martin </emph><br/>Successively cornet in Captain
                    Newdigate’s troop in Sir Walter Erle’s regiment, lieutenant in Captain
                    Blackford’s Dorset troop, and lieutenant in Captain Jaques’s troop in Waller’s
                    regiment of horse in the Southern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph><emph
                        type="i"/>149<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller
                        (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martin, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Martin</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Titus’s company in
                    Thomas Ayloffe’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army in Apr.
                        1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 1.9.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martin [Martyn], Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Martin [Martyn]</emph><br/>Captain of a company at
                    Dartmouth and Plymouth in 1642-3, which served in the summer of 1643 at the
                    defence of Exeter.<br/>By Mar. 1644 Martin was a lieutenant-colonel at Plymouth.
                    Following the death of Colonel William Gould on 27 Mar., the command of the town
                    was put in commission to the mayor, Colonel Crocker and Martin, until Parliament
                    sent down a new governor. On 16 Apr. the other two passed full command to
                    Martin, who ordered various sallies against the royalist blockade. He was still
                    in command in early July, by which time Colonel James Kerr had arrived from
                    London to take command. Martin was buried in St. Andrew’s church, Plymouth, in
                    Oct. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph
                        type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 3.361, 4.441; Worth, <emph type="i"
                        >History of Plymouth</emph>, 111-5; <emph type="i">Continuation</emph><emph
                        type="i">.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Devon</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Martyn [Martin], Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Martyn [Martin]</emph><br/>At the start of the war
                    lieutenant-colonel in Ballard’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army.
                    When Ballard left in summer 1643, he succeeded him as the regiment’s colonel and
                    as such led it under Essex at the relief of Gloucester and first battle of
                    Newbury in 1643. In spring 1644 Martyn and part of the regiment garrisoned
                    Aylesbury, until its disbandment in autumn or winter 1645-6. As such, he
                    features from time to time in Sir Samuel Luke’s letter books and a handful of
                    letters to or by him survive there.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 43; <emph type="i">Luke Letter
                        Books</emph>, nos. 256, 821, 824, 888.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mase, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mase</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir Thomas Myddelton’s North
                    Wales Army. Surviving warrants record payments to him, authorised by Sir Thomas
                    Myddelton, covering the period 22 July to 1 Dec. 1643; it is notable than in the
                    endorsements he makes a mark and so presumably was unable to sign his
                        name.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346, no.
                        260.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North
                    Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Masham, Anthony</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Anthony Masham</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lord Wharton’s regiment
                    of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 31.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maskall, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Maskall</emph><br/>Ensign in Major
                    William Bridges’s company in the Worcestershire regiment of foot (Colonels
                    Edward Rous/William Dingley [Dineley]), 16 Apr. 1646.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/138, part 17, f. 51r.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Worcestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mason, Benjamin</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Benjamin Mason</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel John Fiennes’s
                    regiment of horse in Oxfordshire. On 10 Aug. 1644 he was paid &#xa3;50 at
                    London to set forth his troop and to discharge his soldiers’ quarters, convoying
                    arms and saddles to the regiment; on 20 Aug. &#xa3;27 1s 11d was paid to
                    several innkeepers in Warwick for discharging the quarters of Fiennes’s and
                    Mason’s troops. He last appears in the accounts on 4 Sept. 1644, a significant
                    omission as the captains are generally recorded thereafter up to the regiment’s
                    disbandment in Aug. 1645.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/139,
                    Part 19, f. 205r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Oxfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mason, Besney</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Besney Mason</emph><br/>Colonel’s ensign in the Orange regiment,
                    London Trained Bands (Colonel John Towse) in summer 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Thrale 1642.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mason, Bestney</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Bestney Mason</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of dragoons in
                    the earl of Essex’s Army which was commanded by Sir John Seaton and then George
                    Melve in 1642-3.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i"
                        >Army lists</emph>, 57.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mason, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John</emph><emph type="b"> Mason</emph><br/>In 1644 appointed by
                    John Hutchinson captain of a newly-formed company of foot raised for the
                    townsmen of Nottingham to defend the town. According to Lucy Hutchinson’s
                    account, he soon became a rotten egg, recalcitrant, disobedient, a supporter of
                    her husband’s opponents and perhaps a closet royalist.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Hutchinson, <emph type="i">Life</emph>, 168, 180, 191,
                    192, 204, 206, 210, 225.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Nottinghamshire </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mason, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mason</emph><br/>Probably a late arrival in Sir Thomas
                    Myddelton’s Army in North Wales, described by Thomas Mytton to the Speaker in
                    1646 as ‘a soldier these 20 years and lost his command in Ireland because he
                    refused to bear arms against the Parl.’. He probably joined no earlier than
                    1644, sat on a council of war of 11 Apr. 1645 (Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton
                        letter books</emph>, 1. 194), and serving under Mytton was prominent in the
                    conquest of North Wales in 1645-6. There he remained, serving as a commissioner
                    for the propagation of the gospel in Wales and he fell under the radical
                    influence of Morgan Llwyd and Vavasor Powell (his support for them in 1653-4
                    lost him his place as commissioner).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore,
                        <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 144, 194.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mason, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Mason</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Richard Hill’s company
                    in Sir Arthur Hesilrige’s/James Holborne’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        59.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massey [Massie], Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Massey </emph><emph type="b">[Massie] </emph>(died
                    1674)<br/>He was the fifth of eleven sons of John Massey of Coddington,
                    Cheshire, and Anne (born 1582), daughter of Richard Grosvenor of Eaton,
                    Cheshire. He was probably born between 1610 and 1615.<br/>See <emph type="i"
                        >Oxford DNB</emph>, which covers fully his military career in the 1640s, his
                    political Presbyterianism in the late 1640s, his royalism in the 1650s and his
                    post-Restoration career.<br/>MP for Wootton Bassett in 1646 and for Gloucester
                    in Convention and Cavalier Parliaments.<br/>He served in the Low Countries and
                    in the Bishops’ War of 1639-40 as a captain of Pioneers under Colonel William
                    Legge.<br/>According to the hostile Clarendon he was with the King at York in
                    1642 and only decided to join the Parliamentarian cause when he saw no chance of
                    preferment; he later claimed that he had been undecided between the two sides,
                    but was persuaded by parliament’s claims of self-defence and constitutional
                    conservatism.<br/>He became lieutenant-colonel in the earl of Stamford’s
                    regiment. When Stamford marched west in the autumn of 1642, Massey was left at
                    Gloucester with a regiment, formally as deputy-governor under Stamford and from
                    June 1643 as governor. He became a leading figure in the defence of the town,
                    especially after the storming of Cirencester on 2 Feb. 1643 swept away many of
                    the local levies. Shortly before that, he had taken Sudeley Castle, which now
                    had to be abandoned. In June 1643 he was formally made governor of Gloucester,
                    and commanded there throughout the siege (Aug. 1643) and until May 1645.
                    Warmington, <emph type="i">Glos</emph><emph type="i">.</emph>, and Warmington’s
                    biography in <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph> provide excellent
                    accounts both of Massey’s military achievements in 1643-5, and his ability to
                    feud with Gloucester civilians of any political hue and his own officers.<br/>In
                    May 1645 Massey was appointed general of the forces of the Western Association
                    (Devon, Cornwall, Somerset, Dorset and Wilts). His brigade earned a reputation
                    for disorder.<br/>A leading Presbyterian. An enemy of the New Model Army, which
                    opposed his appointment as lieutenant-general of the army in Ireland in 1647. In
                    Aug. he was one of the eleven Presbyterian MPs singled out as incendiaries by
                    the army, and fled to the Netherlands when it occupied London.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Warmington,
                        <emph type="i">Glos</emph><emph type="i">.</emph>; R. Howes, ‘Sources for
                    the life of Colonel Massey’, <emph type="i">Transactions of the Bristol and
                        Gloucestershire Archaeological Society</emph>, 112 (1994), 127-41.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Gloucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massey, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Massey </emph>(1604x09-1674)<br/>Born a younger son of
                    John Massey of Coddington, Cheshire. Two of his younger brothers, George and
                    Robert, served under him during the civil war. He probably fought on the
                    continent during the 1620s and 1630s and in the Scots Wars of 1639-40. In 1642
                    he supported parliament and became lieutenant-colonel in the earl of Stamford’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army. As such, in winter 1642-3 he
                    remained with much of the regiment, its commander in all but name, when Stamford
                    moved on to take command of parliament’s forces in Devon. Commanding Stamford’s
                    old regiment – he was in due course appointed its Colonel, probably in Nov. 1643
                    – and raising further troops, Massey supported Waller’s campaigns in the region
                    during the opening months of 1643, including the recapture of Cirencester, the
                    engagements at Highnam and Ripple and renewed attempts upon Hereford and
                    Worcester, but by summer 1643 he and his men were bottled up in Gloucester; his
                    stout defence of the town in the face of a huge and lengthy royalist siege
                    during summer 1643 made Massey a hero in the eyes of many parliamentarians.
                    Although still short of money and resources and also involved in sometimes
                    vicious squabbles with parliamentarian administrators and some members of the
                    county committee, during 1644 and early 1645 Massey was able to go on the
                    offensive, slowly recovering much of Gloucestershire, venturing into
                    Herefordshire and Mons. and capturing a string of royalist bases, including
                    Westbury, Newnham, Beverston Castle, Malmesbury, Tewkesbury, Beachley and
                    Monmouth.<br/>In May 1645 he was given a broader remit by parliament as general
                    of a western brigade which supported the relief of Taunton and parts of the New
                    Model’s campaign in the area, including the battle of Langport and the capture
                    of Bridgwater.<br/>In autumn 1646 much of Massey’s Western Army was disbanded
                    and he took his seat as Recruiter MP in the Long Parliament. Always a moderate,
                    by 1647 he was seen as a leading political Presbyterian and opponent of the New
                    Model Army. He went into exile in the Netherlands for a time, was back in
                    England and in London by late 1648 but was secluded and imprisoned at Pride’s
                    Purge. In 1649 he escaped and fled to the continent. By 1650-1 he was openly
                    supporting the royalist cause in Scotland and was an officer in the
                    Scottish-royalist army of invasion in summer 1651, but he was badly wounded a
                    few days before the battle of Worcester. He recovered and was again imprisoned,
                    but he again escaped and went abroad. He was back by 1660, actively supporting
                    the Restoration, which brought him a knighthood, office and a renewal of his
                    parliamentary career.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Oxford DNB.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex; Gloucestershire; Massey Brigade</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massey, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Massey </emph>(born 1614x19)<br/>Ninth son of John Massey
                    of Coddington, Cheshire, and Anne (born 1582), daughter of Richard Grosvenor of
                    Eaton, Cheshire and younger brother of Colonel Edward Massey, governor of
                    Gloucester.<br/>Massey was not initially in the earl of Stamford’s regiment of
                    foot (of which his brother was Lieutenant-Colonel). By 18 Aug. 1643 he was at
                    Gloucester, when he was engaged in a sally, and a few weeks later was wounded
                    when the parliamentarians were outnumbered at Bruckthrop Hill. He was governor
                    of Sudeley Castle, Gloucs., by Dec. 1644, when the garrison mutinied: over pay,
                    according to one account, whilst another conceded that Massey had killed the
                    ringleader, but had merely pricked him in the thigh (the same account, somewhat
                    implausibly, claimed that they mutinied because their pay was just one day
                    late). Sir Samuel Luke was told that Massey ‘has killed a gentleman there
                    [Sudeley], whereupon there arose such a mutiny in the castle that he was forced
                    to fly to his brother at Gloucester for relief’ (Luke, <emph type="i">Letter
                        books</emph>, 117).<br/>If so, Gloucester was still too close and he needed
                    to get further away. By 30 Apr. 1645 Masssey was serving in Sir William
                    Brereton’s Army around Chester, as captain in George Booth’s regiment of foot.
                    About a week later Captain Massey, ‘brother to the governor of Gloucester, and
                    near 20 gentlemen and officers and about 40 common soldiers’ were taken in and
                    about Wrexham by Welsh royalists (Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter
                        books</emph>, 1. 369-70).<br/>Massey had been released by 7 Nov. 1645, when
                    the committees for examinations at Westminster ordered the arrest of Massey
                    (alongside Major John Marbury and Captain Hugh Whitney) upon complaints received
                    from which it appeared that ‘they are dangerous and do much disturb the peace of
                    the county’ (Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2. 225). The
                    reasons are uncertain, and Dore suggests that in Marbury’s and Whitney’s case
                    they may have been victims of the clash between Brereton and his Cheshire
                    enemies. If George shared his brother’s Presbyterianism, he may also have been
                    brought in as against Brereton. However, given his past reputation, and if he
                    was like his brother in behaviour, he might very well have been guilty of the
                        charge.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph
                        type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 6.644-6; <emph type="i">Bibliotheca
                        Gloucestreiensis</emph>, xcix, 74-5, 216; <emph type="i">The Letter Books of
                        Sir Samuel Luke</emph>, ed. H.G. Tibbutt, Bedfordshire RS, 42 (1963), 117;
                    Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 325, 330, 366, 369-70, 2.
                    225; J.W. Willis Bund, <emph type="i">The Civil War in Worcestershire,
                        1642-1646, and the Scotch invasion of 1651 </emph>(1905), 145;<emph type="i"
                    />J.P. Rylands, ed., <emph type="i">Cheshire and Lancashire Funeral
                        Certificates, A.D. 1600 to 1678</emph>, RS of Lancashire and Cheshire, vol.
                    6 (1882), 98, 101 [for calculation of date of birth].<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Gloucestershire; </emph><emph type="i"/><emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massey, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Massey</emph><br/>Captain. A younger son of John Massey of
                    Coddington, Cheshire, and Anne (born 1582), daughter of Richard Grosvenor of
                    Eaton, Cheshire and younger brother of Colonel Edward Massey. He was not
                    initially in the earl of Stamford’s regiment of foot (of which his brother was
                    Lieutenant-Colonel). He was engaged in a sally on 18 Aug., and a few weeks later
                    was wounded when the parliamentarians were outnumbered at Bruckthrop Hill. He
                    was governor of Sudeley Castle, Gloucestershire by Dec. 1644, when the garrison
                    mutinied: over pay, according to one account, although Sir Samuel Luke was told
                    that Massey ‘has killed a gentleman there [Sudeley], whereupon there arose such
                    a mutiny in the castle that he was forced to fly to his brother at Gloucester
                    for relief.’<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph
                        type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 6. 644-6; <emph type="i"
                        >Bibliotheca</emph>, xcix, 74-5, 216; <emph type="i">Luke Letter
                        Books,</emph> 117 (for quotation).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Glo</emph><emph type="i">ucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massey [Massye], Hugh</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Hugh Massey</emph><emph type="b"> [Massye]</emph><br/>Despite his
                    Cheshire name, Dore could not place Hugh Massey with either the Coddington or
                    Audlem families of that name who both provided parliamentarian army
                    officers.<br/>By autumn 1644 Massey was a captain in Sir Thomas Myddelton's
                    brigade, serving in Sept. in Myddelton's invasion of Montgomeryshire, and on 2
                    Oct. with the detachment that stormed the Red Castle. By mid Jan. 1646 Massey
                    was acting along with Captain William Daniel of Sir William Brereton’s Army in
                    besieging Holt Castle. By then, like the remainder of Myddelton’s original
                    brigade, Massey was serving under Colonel (acting Major-General) Thomas
                        Mytton.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore<emph type="i">, Brereton
                        letter books</emph>, 1. 520; Phillips, <emph type="i">Wales</emph>, 2.212;
                    National Library of Wales, Chirk Castle Ms. 1/Biii, 93.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massey, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Massey</emph><br/>Of the Moss House, Audlem, Cheshire.
                    Lieutenant-colonel of George Booth’s regiment of foot in Cheshire on 30 Apr.
                    1645. He succeeded Booth as colonel following the latter’s resignation by 8 May
                    1645. He was for a time governor of Chester, and was serving as such on 30 June
                    1647 when he was arrested by mutineers.<br/>Massey was active in Booth’s Rising
                    in 1659.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Dore<emph type="i">, Brereton
                        letter books</emph>,<emph type="i"/>1. 55, 327; Morrill, <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph>, 200-1, 295.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Massingberg, Drayner</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Drayner Massingberg</emph><br/>Captain in Lord Willoughby’s
                    regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army and the Eastern Association
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.108.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >E</emph><emph type="i">arl of Essex; E</emph><emph type="i">astern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Masters, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Masters</emph><br/>Cornet in Captain Francis Sydenham’s
                    Dorset troop of dragoons, references June and July 1643. By Oct. 1646, a
                    captain, and evidently serving (1 Dec. 1647) in the Poole garrison.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 5.536-7; Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>,
                    41, 295, 377.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Masters, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Masters</emph><br/>By Dec. 1643, captain in William
                    Springate’s regiment of Kentish foot, later entering Ralph Weldon’s regiment of
                    foot when Springate’s regiment was broken up in 1644.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        126.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Kent; </emph><emph
                        type="i">Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Masterson, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Masterson</emph><br/>Captain in Jonas Vandruske’s
                    regiment of horse by 21 Jan. 1644. He was captured (possibly at the second
                    battle of Newbury) and was released from imprisonment from Donnington Castle in
                    Nov. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 138.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller
                        (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Masterton, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Masterton</emph><br/>Captain of a company
                    in St Augustine Lathe regiment of auxiliaries garrisoning Canterbury by 26 Jan.
                        1648.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 76.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Kent</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mathew, Simon</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Simon Mathew</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel George Melve’s
                    regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army, as confirmed by pay warrants
                    of 23 Jan. and 25 May 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA,
                    SP28/5/115, SP28/7/92.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mathews, Humphrey</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Humphrey Mathews</emph><br/>Lieutenant-colonel.
                    Lieutenant-colonel in the Gloucester garrison. An officer in the Gloucester city
                    regiment of foot commanded by Henry Stephens (and later Edward Massey and Thomas
                    Morgan). In Aug. 1643 he was part of a sally against the royalist forces
                    approaching Gloucester.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and
                    Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the West</emph>, 6.625-7; <emph type="i"
                        >Bibliotheca</emph>, 208.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Glo</emph><emph type="i">ucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mathews, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Mathews</emph><br/>Captain. A captain in Gloucestershire.
                    On 26 Aug. 1646 Colonel Thomas Morgan, governor of Gloucester, ordered him to
                    issue warrants to the chief constable of Berkeley Hundred to summon men to
                    slight Berkeley castle.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: HMC, <emph
                        type="i">Fifth Report</emph>, 356.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Glo</emph><emph type="i">ucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mathias [Matthews], Christopher</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Christopher Mathias [Matthews]</emph><br/>Captain in the earl of
                    Essex’s own regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>,
                        25.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mattersby, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Mattersby</emph><br/>Captain-Lieutenant of the Colonel’s
                    company in the earl of Manchester’s regiment of foot, known to have served 7
                    May-15 July 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 1.61.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mattersey, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mattersey</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lord Brooke’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 34.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthew, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Matthew</emph><br/>A clothier of Leeds, Yorkshire (W.
                    Riding). Captain in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper,
                    ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 113 [citing TNA, SP19/123/15; SP19/23/23;
                    SP19/158/128; SP23/135/239].<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Matthews</emph><br/>An officer in, perhaps lieutenant-colonel
                    of, Nathaniel Whetham’s Northampton-based regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s a</emph><emph type="i"
                        >rmy</emph>, 165.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Northamptonshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Matthews</emph><br/>Cornet in the Colonel’s troop in John
                    Middleton’s regiment of horse by 1 Mar. 1644, but by 13 Mar. another officer had
                    succeeded to that position.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 96.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, Humphrey</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Humphrey Mat</emph><emph type="b">t</emph><emph type="b"
                        >hews</emph><br/>Initially an officer in the Hull garrison. He was lent with
                    a company of 140 men to Sir John Gell in Oct. 1642 and formed the initial core
                    of Gell’s forces in Derbyshire. In Nov. an order came from Hull for his arrest
                    for reasons that are unclear, and he was taken prisoner back there (Gell
                    allegedly got hold of some of Mathews’s property which he left with his landlord
                    for safekeeping, and as late as 1658 Mathews was threatening to kill him on
                    sight). On 13 Mar. he was a prisoner in the Gatehouse prison, Westminster,
                    ordered to be sent to Ipswich. However, he must have been soon released. He
                    became lieutenant-colonel in the Gloucester city regiment of foot commanded by
                    Henry Stephens (and later Edward Massey and Thomas Morgan). In Aug. 1643 he was
                    part of a sally against the royalist forces approaching Gloucester.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 6.625-7; <emph type="i">Bibliotheca</emph>, 208; Brighton,
                    ‘Civil War’, 44; Brighton, ‘Governor’, 1-3; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 2
                    (1640-1643), 1000-2.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire,
                        Derbyshire, Gloucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, Nicholas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Nicholas Matthews</emph><br/>Captain in Lord Willoughby’s
                    regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                        2.111.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Matthews</emph><br/>Captain.<emph type="b"/><br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Bayley, <emph type="i">Civil War in
                        Dorset</emph>, 337.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, Simon</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Simon Matthews</emph><br/>Lieutenant of Lord Grey’s troop of
                    horse in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642, according to the contemporary printed
                        list.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 48.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Matthews, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Matthews </emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lieutenant-Colonel
                    Robert Thorpe’s troop in George Thompson’s regiment of horse.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        141.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mauleverer, James</td>
                <td><emph type="b">James Mauleverer</emph> (baptised 1590/1, died 1664)<br/>Of
                    Arncliffe, Yorkshire (North Riding), second and eldest surviving son of William
                    Mauleverer (baptised 1557, died 1618) of Wodersome, Yorkshire. He married
                    Beatrice, daughter of Sir Timothy Hutton.<br/>Mauleverer was colonel of a
                    regiment which he raised for service in the North, but which never got
                        there.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 392;
                    Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 92.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Northern Army (Fairfax)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mauleverer, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mauleverer</emph> (1610/11-1650)<br/>Of Letwell township,
                    Laughten-en-le-Morthen, Yorkshire (West Riding), eldest son of John Maulverer of
                    Letwell and his wife Margaret Lewis. He married Dorcas, daughter and coheir of
                    John Matthew and granddaughter of Archbishop Tobie Matthew.<br/>Mauleverer was first
                    active in the Rotherham area, fleeing to the West Riding clothing districts in
                    May 1643 after the local triumph of the royalists. He may have commanded the
                    south Yorkshire forces at Adwalton Moor. He headed the list of prisoners
                    captured at Bradford on 2/3 July 1643, but was soon released or escaped.<br/>He
                    went to Hull where, probably in Mar. or Apr. 1644, he was made colonel of the
                    garrison regiment. In Apr. 1645 Sir Thomas Fairfax, appointed governor, upon his
                    father’s recommendation, made Mauleverer his deputy-governor (i.e. <emph
                        type="i">de facto </emph>governor). Hull’s MP Peregrine Pelham reported some
                    dissatisfaction at the appointment, though the town welcomed him both then and
                    in 1648. He was superseded at Hull by Robert Overton about Mar. 1648.<br/>In 1648
                    Mauleverer commanded a regiment of foot at the siege of Pontefract. The regiment
                    remained in being after the castle’s surrender. On 4 May 1650 it was one of five
                    selected to form a ‘marching army’, and accordingly, Mauleverer led it into
                    Scotland, where he died of ‘the megrims’ at Edinburgh in Dec. On 28 Dec. 1650,
                    supporting the claims of his widow and seven children, Cromwell commended him to
                    the Commons as one who ‘had a spirit very much beyond his natural strength of
                    body, having undergone many fits of sickness during his hard service in the
                    field’ (Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental history</emph>, 2.530).
                    Command of the regiment passed to Richard Deane.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 392; <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph>; Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental history</emph>,<emph
                        type="i"/>2. 529-530; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 113; Wanklyn,
                        <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 162.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire; Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern
                        Army (Poyntz); Northern Army (Lambert); New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mauleverer, Sir Thomas, first baronet</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir Thomas Mauleverer, </emph><emph type="b">first</emph><emph
                        type="b"> baronet </emph>(baptised 1599, died 1655)<br/>Of Allerton
                    Mauleverer, Yorkshire (West Riding). Baptised 9 Apr. 1599, eldest son of Sir
                    Richard Mauleverer of Allerton Mauleverer (c.1528–1603), high sheriff of
                    Yorkshire in 1588, and his second wife Katherine, daughter of Sir Ralph
                    Bourchier of Beningbrough. He married (1) Mary, daughter of Sir Richard Hutton,
                    Justice of Common Pleas; (2) Elizabeth (<emph type="i">d</emph>. 1653), daughter
                    of Thomas Wilbraham of Woodhey, Cheshire.<br/>MP for Boroughbridge in the Long
                    Parliament and a regicide.<br/>Lord Fairfax appointed him as a negotiator of the
                    local neutrality pact made at Rothwell on 29 Sept. 1642. After its rapid
                    collapse, Mauleverer was besieged at his house until rescued by some of
                    Fairfax’s horse.<br/>Maulverer claimed to have raised two regiments of foot
                        (<emph type="i">Oxford DNB </emph>says one) and a troop of horse early in
                    the war. He was associated with James Mauleverer. He was present at Adwalton
                    Moor (30 June 1643), escaping from the rout by boat from Selby to Hull with Lord
                    Fairfax, and at Nantwich (Jan. 1644).<br/>(His son Richard (baptised 1623, died
                    1675) fought for the king, for which his father took away his &#xa3;500 annual
                    allowance; he was knighted at Oxford in 1645, was captured in a royalist rising
                    in Yorkshire in 1655 and escaped from Chester Castle.)<br/>Sir Thomas died in or
                    by 1655.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 102;<emph type="b"/>Greaves and Zaller, <emph type="i"
                        >British radicals</emph>, 2.228; Keeler, <emph type="i">Long </emph><emph
                        type="i">P</emph><emph type="i">arliament</emph><emph type="b">,
                    </emph>270-1; <emph type="i">HoP: the Commons, 1640-1660
                        </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maunder, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Maunder</emph><br/>In 1642 cornet in James Sheffield’s
                    troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army and then Cornet of the Colonel’s own
                    troop in Sheffield’s regiment of horse in Essex’s Army probably from its
                    formation in summer 1643 through to its disbandment in spring 1645; unlike
                    several officers of the regiment, he did not transfer to the New Model
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 49; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, 1.
                        150.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maurice, David</td>
                <td><emph type="b">David Maurice</emph><br/>Son of Thomas Maurice of Llangedwin,
                    Montgomeryshire.<br/>By Jan. 1644 Maurice was senior commissary officer to Sir
                    Thomas Myddelton. He served in that role with Myddelton’s brigade when it
                    invaded Montgomeryshire in Sept. 1644, and into 1645 supervised the magazines at
                    Myddelton’s castle strongholds at Montgomery and Red Castle. By 1646 Maurice was
                    second-in-command at Chirk Castle (occupied by parliamentary forces in early
                    Mar.), and by 1648 was described as a gentleman of Chirk Castle, leasing a house
                    at Halton in Chirk parish from Myddelton until his death in 1653. Maurice’s will
                    was dated 25 Apr. and proved on 29 July by his widow Ellin and father
                        Thomas.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346, Part 1, no.
                    301, Part 2, no.14; National Library of Wales, Chirk Castle Ms. 1/Biii, 93; W.M.
                    Myddelton, <emph type="i">Chirk Castle Accounts, 1605-1666</emph> (1908), 21n.
                    and <emph type="i">passim.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mauser, Joseph</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Joseph Mauser</emph><br/>In 1645-6, by which time it was
                    commanded by John Fielder, ensign in Lieutenant-Colonel Jeremy Baines’s company
                    in the Surrey regiment of foot based at Farnham Castle.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring<emph type="i">, Waller’s army, </emph>74<emph
                        type="i">.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller
                        (Southern Association); </emph><emph type="i">Surrey</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mawdesley, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Mawdesley</emph><br/>Commissioned captain in Gilbert
                    Ireland’s militia regiment of foot in Lancashire, 16 Aug. 1650.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 509.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maxey, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Maxey</emph><br/>In May 1643, captain serving in one of the
                    three regiments of foot formed from the Essex militia, part of the Eastern
                    Association Army that contributed to the siege of Reading in spring 1643, the
                    siege of Greenland House in summer 1644 and probably to some other actions in
                    which the Army was involved.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.33.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>May, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">May </emph><br/>Cornet in the Colonel’s
                    troop in Sir Michael Livesay’s Kentish regiment of horse by 24 Apr.
                        1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army,</emph> 79.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Kent,
                        Waller (Southern Association) </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>May, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- May</emph><br/>Captain in Randall Mainwaring’s Red regiment of
                    foot, in Olney, Bedfordshire, in Nov. 1643 when Edmund Harvey’s regiment of
                    London horse was routed by the royalists.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    George Paine, <emph type="i">A true relation</emph><emph type="i"/><emph
                        type="i">of all the skirmishes between our forces and the Cavaliers at Owlny
                    </emph>(1643), 3.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Bedfordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>May, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- May</emph><br/>Captain in Thomas Rainsborough’s regiment of
                    foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.90.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>May, Anthony</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Anthony May</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Henry Catcott’s company
                    in the Arundel Rape Trained Bands by 10 Dec. 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        124.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Sussex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>May, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas May</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Captain Arthur Saville’s
                    company in Strode’s Trained Band regiment, 19 Sept. 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 5.549.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Somerset: </emph><emph type="i">Col</emph><emph type="i">. </emph><emph
                        type="i">William Strode’s Trained Band </emph><emph type="i"
                    >Regt.</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Maynard, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Maynard</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of dragoons in
                    the earl of Essex’s Army which was commanded by Sir John Seaton and then George
                    Melve, by early Mar. 1643 until at least late June 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/5/205, SP28/7/452.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mazieres, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Mazieres</emph><br/>Colonel of a regiment of horse raised in
                    Essex in summer 1643. However, it experienced difficulties recruiting and seems
                    to have been quite short-lived, disappearing from the records by spring 1644.
                    Mazieres himself was French, his brief command of this regiment seems to have
                    been his only military contribution to the civil war and in 1645, orders having
                    been given for his arrears of pay to be met, he returned to France.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.67; Holmes, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                    176, 177.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mazy [Massey], Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Mazy [Massey]</emph><br/>Captain in a London militia
                    regiment in 1647, put out by the Presbyterian militia committee in 1647, ‘for
                    stopping and breaking open the Scotch Letters in May last, though the thing was
                    approved and hee acquitted by the House of Commons; yet Alderman Bonch [Bunce]
                    said it was a Jesuetticall plott to keepe him in’ (<emph type="i">Clarke
                        Papers</emph>, 1.155).<br/>After the entry of the New Model Army into London
                    in Aug. 1647, he was appointed captain in the Tower regiment (Colonel Robert
                        Tichborne).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Clarke
                        Papers</emph>, 1.155; Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental
                        History</emph>, 2.572.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>McKenzie, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George McKenzie</emph><br/>In spring 1645, lieutenant-colonel of
                    the regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army commanded successively by
                    Colonels James Holborne and William Davies. Unlike Davies himself and a few of
                    his other officers, he did not transfer to the New Model Army.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>,
                    1. 149.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meadows, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Meadows</emph><br/>Down to June 1644, captain in the earl of
                    Manchester’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.65.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meares, Moses</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Moses Meares</emph><br/>Captain in the Red regiment, London
                    Auxiliaries (Colonel Samuel Harsnett), commanding a company from Fetter Lane and
                    Holborn (uncertain date, probably 1644). Major of the same regiment on 22 Oct.
                        1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/121A, Part 5, f. 620
                    r. &amp; v.; Nagel, ‘London militia’, 317; Marshall, <emph type="i">Essex
                        funeral</emph>, 12.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Medcalfe, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Medcalfe</emph><br/>Commissioned captain in a regiment of
                    foot in the Yorkshire militia.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">CSPD, 1650</emph>, 506.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Medlam, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Medlam</emph><br/>Medlam served in Nottinghamshire, and
                    was successively Gentleman of the Arms in Captain Charles White’s troop of
                    horse, 14 Dec.-4 Aug. 1643; Cornet in Captain Lawrence Palmer’s troop of horse,
                    11 Sept. 1643-21 June 1645; and lieutenant in Captain Michael Dolphin’s troop of
                    horse (formerly Palmer’s), 21 June 1645-7 Nov. 1646.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/133, Part 2, ff. 83r.-88v.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Nottinghamshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meech, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Meech</emph><br/>Cornet.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>, 387.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meering, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Meering</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Captain Needham’s
                    company in John Barker’s/Thomas Willoughby’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s a</emph><emph
                        type="i">rmy</emph>, 23.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meldrum, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Meldrum</emph><br/>Not the Sir John Meldrum who was active
                    in the East Midlands and whose attempt to capture Newark in Mar. 1644 ended in
                    disaster. This separate and different John Meldrum began the civil war as one of
                    Balfour’s officers – initially, in 1642, as lieutenant in Balfour’s troop of
                    horse in the earl of Essex’s Army – but in 1643 was promoted to colonel and
                    commissioned to raise a new regiment of horse. He and his regiment fought under
                    Waller in spring 1644, including at the battle of Cheriton where Meldrum was
                    wounded and he died, presumably from those wounds, a few weeks later. His
                    regiment was reduced and absorbed into one of the regiments in the earl of
                    Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, Waller’s army, 101;
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 48; TNA, SP28/4/146, SP28/5/521,
                        SP28/7/285.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex;
                        </emph><emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association).</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meldrum, Sir John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir John Meldrum </emph>(died 1645)<br/>Born probably in the
                    early 1580s, of obscure Scottish origins and little is known of his parentage or
                    early life. He seems to have fought with Scottish or English forces in Ireland
                    in the early seventeenth century, as well as on the continent. He was knighted
                    by James I in 1622. He later supported Buckingham’s Ile de Rh&#xe9; expedition
                    before returning to fighting in the Thirty Years War.<br/>In summer 1642 he came
                    out strongly in support of parliament and commanded a body of reinforcements
                    sent to strengthen and to hold Hull, beating off a rather lacklustre royalist
                    siege. In Aug. and early Sept. he supported Waller in his recapture of
                    Portsmouth. In effect he commanded Viscount Saye and Sele’s regiment of foot and
                    two other regts. forming an infantry brigade under him at the battle of
                    Edgehill. He formally took command of the regiment soon after and led it until
                    summer 1643.<br/>From the latter half of 1643 onwards Meldrum was generally
                    employed to lead or support operations in the (East) Midlands: ‘a
                    trouble-shooter in the midlands’ is how the <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>
                    describes this phase of his military career. Despite the failure of his siege
                    operation against Newark in spring 1644 and the ignominy of having to surrender
                    his army to Rupert, he was generally quite successful in this role; he played an
                    important part in the victory at Montgomery in summer 1644 and went on to
                    recapture Liverpool later in the year. In spring 1645 he had command of the
                    siege of Scarborough. He survived both falling from the cliff-top, when his
                    cloak acted as a parachute, and being ‘shot through the Codds’, but in May he
                    was shot in the stomach when leading the assault and endured probably a long and
                    lingering death from that wound.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Oxford DNB</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mellor, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Mellor</emph><br/>Presumably a kinsman of Robert Mellor of
                    Derby. Captain of foot in Derbyshire. In Dec. 1644 he was one of the signatories
                    of a petition of Derbyshire officers against Sir John Gell.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Brighton, ‘Governor’, 26.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Derbyshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mellor, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Mellor </emph>(died 1656)<br/>Of Derby, son and heir of
                    Henry Mellor, first mayor of Derby, and himself a mercer of Derby. He married
                    (1) Elizabeth, daughter of Robert Willimot of Chadsdon, Derbyshire and (2)
                    Susanna, daughter of Henry Sanders, citizen of London.<br/>Mellor raised a
                    company for Sir John Gell’s regiment of foot from the burgesses of Derby in
                    1642. In Mar. 1643 he was left to garrison Derby when Gell went to take command
                    at the siege of Lichfield after Lord Brooke’s death. By the end of 1644 (if not
                    earlier) Mellor, a county committeeman, was restive about the way Gell managed
                    to exclude all but those closest to him from the administration of the war
                    effort, and in 1645 he fell out with him. In Sept. Sir John’s enemies proposed
                    Mellor as a candidate to stand against his brother Thomas Gell in the recruiter
                    election for Derby. Sir John disrupted Mellor’s campaign by sending Mellor and
                    his company first to Chatsworth and then to join Poyntz in the attack on Newark,
                    and it was only in Jan. 1647 that the Commons committee of privileges ruled that
                    Thomas Gell’s election should stand.<br/>By 1650 Mellor was a sequestration
                        commissioner.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Vis.
                        Derbyshire</emph>, 18; Turbutt, <emph type="i">Derbyshire</emph>, 3.1061,
                    1063, 1066, 1068, 1070, 1085, 1099.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Derbyshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Melson, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Melson</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Rochford’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 32.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Melve, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Melve</emph><br/>When its original colonel, Sir John
                    Seaton, headed North in winter 1642-3, Melve – on 19 Nov. 1642 a pay warrant had
                    been issued for him as a colonel and general adjutant for the earl of Essex’s
                    Army – was given command of his regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s
                    Army, though the regiment seems to have been broken up in summer 1643.<br/>On
                    the evening of 23 Apr. 1643, Essex sent out Melve with four troops of his
                    dragoons, in a party with horse led by John Middleton and Sir John Meldrum,
                    which clashed with royalists at Dorchester upon Thames.<br/>‘Melve’ is his own
                    spelling of his name, though others sometimes spelt his name Mill or
                    Mills.<br/>He is probably the reformado colonel paid by warrants dated 29 Feb.
                    and 29 Apr. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/3b/406,
                    SP28/5/204, 225, 334, 340, SP28/7/79, 94, 348, 401, SP28/9/255, SP28/12/179,
                    SP28/14/384; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>, 6.17.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Melve, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Melve</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of dragoons in
                    the earl of Essex’s Army which was commanded by Sir John Seaton and then by
                    (presumably his kinsman) George Melve in 1642-3, from at least mid-Mar. 1643. He
                    continued in that role despite the breaking up of George Melve’s regiment in
                    summer 1643 and served as a Dragoon captain in the earl of Essex’s Army until at
                    least mid-Feb. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/5/171,
                    SP28/7/93, SP28/5/205, 206, SP28/7/345, SP28/8/139, SP28/12/125.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Melvin, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Melvin</emph><br/>In 1642, probably at and from its
                    formation, lieutenant in Lord Robartes’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s
                    Army. In Apr. 1645 when the regiment was disbanded and the Lords wished to
                    appoint Robartes’s officers <emph type="i">en bloc</emph> in place of the
                    officers chosen by Fairfax for John Pickering’s regiment, Fairfax instead
                    appointed Melvin captain in the New Model regiment of foot originally intended
                    to be commanded by Edward Aldrich but then given to Walter Lloyd and after the
                    latter’s death commanded by William Herbert.<br/>Melvin was wounded at the
                    storming of Bristol in Sept. 1645.<br/>When Herbert agreed to take a regiment to
                    Ireland in 1647, Melvin was appointed lieutenant-colonel in the regiment formed
                    when the men of the existing one proved recalcitrant, a regiment allegedly
                    intended to form part of an anti-New Model force by the Presbyterian leadership.
                    He left the regiment after the defeat of the Presbyterian attempted
                        coup.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 37; TNA, SP28/9/5; Temple, New Model Army’, 61, 72; Firth and
                    Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental history</emph>, 1.384-6; <emph type="i"
                        >JHL</emph>, 9.219.<br/>.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mercer, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Mercer</emph><br/>Major in a Southwark regiment, probably the
                    Southwark Trained Bands regiment, in late 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/131, Part 13, f. 5v.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Southwark</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mercer, Christopher</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Christopher Mercer</emph><br/>During 1644 served as captain in
                    the earl of Manchester’s regiment of dragoons in the Eastern Association Army.
                    He later served as a captain in Okey’s New Model Army dragoon
                        regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 1.58; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model
                        Army</emph>, I, 50, 60, 71, 81, 92, 104.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model
                        Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mercer, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mercer</emph><br/>In 1642, probably at and from its
                    formation, captain in Lord Robartes’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 37.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mercer, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Mercer</emph><br/>Lieutenant in John Urry’s troop in Lord
                    Wharton’s regiment of horse in Wharton’s Army raised for service in Ireland in
                    1642. Instead, he continued as Urry’s lieutenant when Urry became captain, later
                    major, in Sir William Balfour’s regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army.
                    In late Aug. 1642, when he was paid &#xa3;48 mounting money as Urry’s
                    lieutenant, it was noted that he had already been listed for the Irish service
                    (the last certain reference to the troop is dated 19 Oct. 1644).<br/>By 1644
                    Mercer was serving as a reformado captain of horse in Essex’s Army, between at
                    least 29 Feb. and 1 Oct.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph
                        type="i">Army lists</emph>, 67; TNA, SP28/1a/217, SP28/2b/411, SP28/12/176,
                    SP28/14/384, SP28/17/110, SP28/19/1.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex; Reformado</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meredith [Merredith], William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Meredith [Merredith]</emph><br/>Captain in Lawrence
                    Crawford’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army from Mar. 1644 until
                    its disbandment on 17 Apr. 1645.<br/>Meredith, despite his surname, appears to
                    have been a Scot (a constable of Covent Garden certainly thought so). He is
                    almost certainly one of the officers in Crawford’s regiment who had originally
                    served in Ireland (although his name does not appear in published lists of
                    Ormonde’s officers in 1642).<br/>On 24 May 1645, in a brawl which developed when
                    Crawford and his officers tried to get released from impressments the General’s
                    servant, Richard Man, a Covent Garden constable, ‘then seized on Captain
                    Merydith, disarming him; and he, with several others of his Company (who also
                    railed most bitterly ... against the Scottish Nation), kicked him, and beat him
                    most inhumanly, calling him a beggarly Scotts Rogue, and Scotts Cur, and Rascal,
                    with many other opprobrious Words’ (<emph type="i">JHL</emph>, 7.393). On 27
                    Aug. 1645, ten days after Crawford’s death, Meredith appeared before the Lords
                    to represent the case of his commander’s widow.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.14;
                    TNA, SP28/25/488; Davies, ‘Eastern Association’, 94; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>,
                    7.393, 555; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 3.428.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meredith, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Meredith</emph><br/>By May 1644 until at least Jan. 1645,
                    captain in the earl of Manchester’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.64.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Merrett, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Merrett</emph><br/>At the time of its reduction, in
                    spring 1645, lieutenant of Thomas Hammond’s troop in the earl of Manchester’s
                    regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                        1.54.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Merrick, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Merrick</emph><br/>In 1642, probably at and from its
                    formation, lieutenant in Lord Robartes’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 37.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Merridith, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Merridith</emph><br/>By the beginning of 1645 ensign in Azariah
                    Husbands’s company in John Pickering’s regiment of foot in the Eastern
                    Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 2.85.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Merser, Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Merser</emph><br/>Captain-lieutenant in the colonel’s
                    company, Southwark auxiliaries regiment (Colonel James Houblon) on 16 Apr.
                        1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/121, Part 3, f.
                        339r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Southwark</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mewer, Nicholas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Nicholas Mewer</emph><br/>Cornet to (presumably his kinsman)
                    Captain Mewer in John Browne’s regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army
                        1642-3.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock<emph type="i">, Army
                        lists</emph>, 57.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mewer, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert </emph><emph type="b">Mewer</emph><br/>In the 1642 army
                    list, he is shown as a captain in John Browne’s regiment of dragoons in the earl
                    of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock<emph type="i">,
                        Army lists</emph>, 57.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl
                        of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            
            <tr>
                <td>Mewer, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mewer</emph><br/>Lieutenant to (presumably his kinsman)
                    Captain Mewer in John Browne’s regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army
                        1642-3.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock<emph type="i">, Army
                        lists</emph>, 57.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meyrick [Merrick], Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Me</emph><emph type="b">yrick</emph><emph type="b">
                        [Me</emph><emph type="b">rrick</emph><emph type="b">]</emph><br/>In
                    Aug./Sept. 1642 captain in Sir John Meyrick’s regiment of foot in the earl of
                    Essex’s Army.<br/>Probably son of Sir Francis Meyrick of Fleet, Monkton,
                    Pembrokshire and thus younger brother of Sir John Meyrick and cousin of Rowland
                    and Thomas Laugharne.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph
                        type="i">Army lists</emph>, 28; TNA, SP28/2b/512; Meyrick, <emph type="i"
                        >Welsh pedigrees</emph>, 1.137.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Meyrick [Merrick], Sir John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir John Me</emph><emph type="b">y</emph><emph type="b">rick
                        [Me</emph><emph type="b">r</emph><emph type="b">rick] </emph>(c.
                    1600-1659)<br/>Born a younger son of Sir Francis Meyrick of Fleet, Monkton,
                    Pembrokshire; through his mother he was cousin of Rowland and Thomas
                    Laugharne.<br/>Like his father and uncle before him, he pursued a military
                    career, fighting on the continent during the 1620s and 1630s. He was elected to
                    the Short and Long Parliaments and in 1640 commanded a regiment of foot in the
                    Second Scots War. A friend of the earl of Essex, in summer 1642 he raised and
                    part-funded a regiment of foot in the London area. His regiment supported the
                    recapture of Portsmouth in Aug. and Sept. 1642 and then joined Essex’s main army
                    in the Midlands, but it was employed to garrison Worcester and so was not
                    present at Edgehill, though Meyrick and at least some of his men were present at
                    the subsequent defence of London. During 1643 the regiment had a rather
                    fractured existence, part of it garrisoning Plymouth and part of it garrisoning
                    Gloucester; some of those troops were drawn out to serve under Waller in summer
                    1643 and so fought at Lansdown and Roundway Down. Merrick and some of his
                    regiment fought under Essex at the relief of Gloucester and first battle of
                    Newbury. Much of the regiment was then disbanded in late summer 1643, though
                    parts of it probably survived and Meyrick was certainly with Essex in his doomed
                    march into the south west in summer 1644, escaping with him by boat. His
                    military activity finally ended with the Self-Denying Ordinance.<br/>He was
                    secluded and for a time imprisoned at Pride’s Purge and then effectively retired
                    to Pembrokshire. He was certainly dead by 1659, possibly somewhat earlier than
                        that.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                    DNB</emph>; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 28.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Micklethwaite, Elias</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Elias Micklethwaite </emph>(baptised 1611, died 1644)<br/>Of
                    Swine in Holderness, Yorkshire (East Riding), third son of Elias Micklethwaite
                    (died 1633), merchant and twice mayor of York and a Jacobean MP there and his
                    wife Dorothy Jaques (died 1611). Baptised at Holy Trinity, York, 7 Feb. 1611. He
                    attended the Inner Temple.<br/>Captain of horse. Probably recruited early in
                    1643 and was captain in Lord Fairfax’s regiment of horse. He remained in Hull
                    when the rest of the horse was withdrawn. In Apr. 1644 he marched to Selby with
                    Fairfax. He was at the siege of York and was killed at Marston Moor. His will
                    was proved at York on 13 July 1644. Brother of Joseph Micklethwaite.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 393-4; <emph type="i"
                        >Yorks. Vis., </emph>2.359-60; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’,
                        102.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Micklethwaite, Joseph</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Joseph Micklethwaite</emph> (1594-1658)<br/>Of Swine in
                    Holderness, Yorkshire (East Riding) and of York, esquire, eldest son of Elias
                    Micklethwaite (died 1633), York merchant and mayor, and elder brother of Elias
                    Micklethwaite. Baptised 8 Nov. 1594 at St John’s, York. JP and committeeman for
                    the East Riding in the Northern Association. Will made 8 Sept. 1658, proved 2
                    Dec. 1658.<br/>A captain in Yorkshire but little evidence survives of his civil
                    war activities.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorks.
                        Vis., </emph>2.360; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 101; Jones, ‘War
                    in the North’, 394.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Middleton </emph><br/>Captain in Colonel
                    George Mill’s (later Waller’s) regiment of horse.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        147.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, David</td>
                <td><emph type="b">David Middleton </emph><br/>Captain-lieutenant. Son of
                    Lieutenant-General John Middleton. He was a reformado cornet in Apr. 1643. He
                    served as captain-lieutenant of the colonel’s troop in his father’s regiment of
                    horse in 1644 and early 1645. In Apr. 1645 his troop was stationed in Surrey and
                    was ordered to rejoin the regiment in the West.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        105.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, Francis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Francis Middleton</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of dragoons
                    in the earl of Essex’s Army which was commanded by Sir John Seaton and then
                    George Melve in 1642-3, by early Mar. 1643 to at least late June 1643.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/5/206, 452.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Middleton</emph><br/>By Feb. 1644 and continuing in the
                    regiment until spring 1645, captain in Sir John Norwich’s regiment of horse in
                    the Eastern Association Army. From 1645 to 1647 served in Vermuyden’s New Model
                    Army regiment as a captain, down to his dismissal in late 1647.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.74; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I,
                    52, 62, 73, 83, 94, 107.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, John </td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Middleton</emph><br/>Ensign in Thomas Grantham’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 41.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Middleton, first earl of Middleton</emph> (1606-1674)<br/>A
                    Scot, eldest son of Robert Middleton, laird of Caldhame, Kincardineshire. After
                    experience fighting on the continent during the 1630s, he returned home and
                    joined the Covenanter army in its wars against Charles I in 1639 and
                    1640.<br/>He fought in England for parliament during the main civil war,
                    beginning as colonel of a regiment of dragoons in the earl of Essex’s Army,
                    though he soon relinquished that command on becoming colonel of a regiment of
                    horse previously commanded by or earmarked for Basil, Lord Feilding. He fought
                    at Edgehill and commanded the left wing at the first battle of Newbury.<br/>In
                    May 1644 Middleton fell out with Essex’s Commissary-General Hans Behr, who
                    (according to the diarist Thomas Juxon) ‘had affronted Colonel Middleton and the
                    Scots nation’ (Juxon, <emph type="i">Diary</emph>, 59); Juxon also claimed that
                    both men had been committed for a time. Behr’s broadside of 1 May answered a
                    number of charges, which did include that he had ‘detracted, by ill Language,
                    from the Honour and reputation of the Scottish Nation in generall; and in
                    particular, from the Honour of his Excellency the Lord Generall Lesley [i.e.
                    Alexander Leslie, Earl of Leven]’ (Behr). Moreover, he accused the Scottish
                    officers of trying to undermine the happy union between the two kingdoms:
                    ‘divers Commanders who have laid downe their Commissions in his excellencies
                    Army, upon no other ground, but that it standeth not with their honour to serve
                    where the Robber of their Nations honour is tolerated’ (Behr). Middleton headed
                    the list of four officers who responded in a counter-broadside accusing him of
                    cowardice.<br/>Thus in spring 1644 he transferred to Waller’s southern army,
                    becoming his lieutenant general of horse. As such, he brought with him his
                    existing regiment of horse, raised in 1643, which had already fought at the
                    relief of Gloucester, the first battle of Newbury and the battle of Cheriton,
                    and in summer 1644 he raised and commanded a new regiment of horse, though it
                    incorporated one or more troops already raised for service under Sir Richard
                    Grenville. His old regiment later returned to Essex’s Army; his new regiment
                    probably fought at the second battle of Newbury and in the West before it was
                    disbanded shortly after Middleton left his command and left
                    England.<br/>Middleton played a prominent role in the Battle of Cropredy Bridge
                    and led a brigade which tried to harry the rear of the king’s army and thus
                    relieve the pressure on Essex in the far South West. On 20 Aug. he reported to
                    the Committee of Both Kingdoms that, in accordance with Waller’s orders, he was
                    suppressing all levies and stopping all provisions in Somerset, and had driven
                    nine royalist colonels to Minehead, blocking their attempts to raise troops in
                    the county. He was wary, however, of advancing too far into Devon, leaving the
                    Bristol and Bridgwater garrisons in his rear. After the escape of Essex’s
                    cavalry, it joined up with Middleton’s force between Taunton and Bridgwater.
                    Middleton and Behr were ordered to bury personal differences. Some found it
                    convenient to blame Middleton rather than Essex for the latter’s disaster at
                    Lostwithiel, and on 21 September the Commons received a letter from the Earl at
                    Portsmouth protesting that it would be impossible for his cavalry to serve under
                    Middleton whose dilatoriness in coming to the aid of the army in Cornwall had
                    been the cause of their miseries.<br/>Middleton resigned his English commissions
                    in spring 1645 and returned to Scotland. He raised a regiment of horse in spring
                    1645 in England, ‘all for the most part of our owne nation’ (<emph type="i"
                        >Oxford DNB</emph>), but including some Englishmen, and on 5 May received
                    permission from the Scottish commissioners in London to join the Army of the
                    Solemn League and Covenant.<br/>He fought in the Covenanter army against
                    Montrose, before supporting the Engagement and fighting in the Scottish-royalist
                    army defeated by Cromwell around and south of Preston in Aug. 1648; he was
                    captured, but was allowed to return to Scotland. By the 1650s a committed
                    royalist, he played a prominent role in the Scottish-royalist invasion of summer
                    1651, escaped from Worcester but was captured shortly afterwards, only to escape
                    from the Tower and reach exile in France. He was a leader of royalist military
                    resistance in the Highlands in the mid-1650s, but again eluded capture and
                    rejoined Charles II in exile. Raised to the peerage, he resumed his colourful
                    career resumed after the Restoration; initially in favour and high office in
                    Scotland, he fell out with Lauderdale, lost office and for a time lived in
                    retirement, only to come back into favour and end his career and his life as
                    governor of Tangier.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph><emph type="i">; </emph>TNA, SP28/1a/132, 2b/424, 425, 460, 461,
                    3a/207, 251, 3b/335, 341, 359, 4/159, 304, 423; H. Behr, <emph type="i">The
                        declaration of Commissary Generall Behr </emph>(1644); <emph type="i">There
                        hath bin a printed paper lately published </emph>([2 May] 1644); <emph
                        type="i">CSPD, 1644</emph>, 293, 434; Gardiner, 1. 362, 2.15, 29, 31;
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army</emph>; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1644</emph>,
                    293, 434, 439-40, 448, 469-70, 491; Stoyle, <emph type="i">Soldiers and
                        Strangers</emph>, 89-90.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, John [later first earl of Middleton]</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Middleton [later </emph><emph type="b">first</emph><emph
                        type="b"> earl of Middleton]</emph> <emph type="i"/>(c. 1608-1674)<br/>Eldest
                    son of Robert Middleton (died 1645), laird of Caldhame, Mearns, Kincards., and
                    his wife, Helen Strachan, a daughter of Alexander Strachan of Thornton,
                    Kincards. In July 1639 he married (as her third husband) Grizel Durham (died
                    1666), the twice-widowed daughter of Sir James Durham of Pitkerro.<br/>John
                    fought in the Thirty Years’ War in the 1630s, serving first as a pikeman in Sir
                    John Hepburn’s regiment of foot in France. By 1639 he had returned to Scotland
                    and in 1639 was a captain in Montrose’s army and fought with distinction at the
                    Brig o' Dee (19 June).<br/>In 1642 he joined the English parliamentarian army.
                    By the end of July he was colonel of a regiment of dragoons (the three captains
                    named in his regiment had appeared in the published list of Essex’s Army as
                    Captains of the firelocks in Essex’s own regiment of foot). On 3 Sept. 1642 he
                    was commissioned colonel of a regiment of horse, previously commanded by Basil,
                    Lord Feilding (later earl of Denbigh), and relinquished his command of the
                    dragoon regiment Middleton commanded the left wing of Essex’s horse at the first
                    battle of Newbury (20 Sept. 1643).<br/>In May 1644 he fell out with Essex and
                    transferred to Waller’s Southern Association Army, where he became
                    lieutenant-general. He was to the fore at the battle of Cropredy Bridge in June,
                    commanding one part of Waller’s divided army. It was reported that he badly
                    wounded and captured Lord Wilmot (who was later rescued from his guards).
                    However, Middleton’s force was routed by royalist charges. In Aug. he was sent
                    into the West with a force of 2,000 men to support Essex’s Army by harrying the
                    enemy rear and impeding royalist supply and recruitment at the taking of Wareham
                    (Dorset) and ordered to support and cover Essex’s Army by approaching as near
                    the king’s army as it could. On 20 Aug. he reported to the Committee of Both
                    Kingdoms that, in accordance with Waller’s orders, he was suppressing all levies
                    and stopping all provisions in Somerset, and had driven nine royalist colonels
                    to Minehead, blocking their attempts to raise troops in the county. He was wary,
                    however, of advancing too far into Devon, leaving the Bristol and Bridgwater
                    garrisons in his rear. After the escape of Essex’s cavalry, it joined up with
                    Middleton’s force between Taunton and Bridgwater: Middleton and Essex’s
                    Commissary-General Behr were ordered to bury personal differences. In fact, the
                    House found it convenient to blame Middleton rather than Essex for the latter’s
                    disaster at Lostwithiel, and on 21 Sept. the Commons received a letter from
                    Essex at Portsmouth protesting that it would be impossible for his cavalry to
                    serve under Middleton, whose dilatoriness in coming to the aid of the army in
                    Cornwall had been the cause of their miseries.<br/>Middleton was offered command
                    of a regiment of horse in the New Model Army, but as a Scot declined. Instead,
                    he raised a regiment of horse in spring 1645 in England, ‘all for the most part
                    of our owne nation’ (<emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>), but including some
                    Englishmen, and on 5 May received permission from the Scottish commissioners in
                    London to join the Army of the Solemn League and Covenant.<br/>He was appointed
                    major-general of the Army of the Solemn League and Covenant, which he reached on
                    20 June 1645. He was second-in-command at the defeat of Montrose at Philiphaugh
                    and on 4 Feb. 1646 was appointed commander-in-chief in Scotland. In Jan. 1647 he
                    was appointed major-general of the Scottish New Model Army.<br/>He supported the
                    Engagement and was a senior officer in the Scottish-royalist armies in both the
                    Preston and Worcester campaigns, and after the latter escaped trial for treason
                    by escaping in his wife’s clothes and making his way to the king in France. In
                    late 1653 he was commissioned captain-general of the forces raised in the
                    Highlands by the earl of Glencairn, which were routed by Monck and Colonel
                    Thomas Morgan at Dalnaspidal on 10 July 1654.<br/>At the Restoration he was
                    appointed commander-in-chief in Scotland, governor of Edinburgh Castle and lord
                    high commissioner to the Scottish parliament. In 1662-3 he imposed an
                    espicopalian and authoritarian regime in Scotland. After his fall, he retired to
                    England and in 1668 was appointed governor of Tangier, where he died in
                        1674.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 393;
                    Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental history</emph>, 1.239-40, 2.554-7;
                    Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 120; <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>;
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army</emph>, 95; <emph type="i">CSPD,
                        1644</emph>, 434, 439-40, 448, 469, 491; TNA, SP28/1a/132, 2b/424, 425, 460,
                    461, 3a/207, 251, 3b/335, 341, 359, 4/159, 304, 423; <emph type="i">CSPD,
                        1644</emph>, 293, 434; Gardiner, <emph type="i">Great Civil War</emph>,
                    1.362, 2.15, 29, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire;
                        Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army (Poyntz); Northern Army (Lambert);
                        New Model Army; Earl of Essex; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Middleton, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Middleton</emph><br/>Possibly captain in Sir John
                    Douglass’s regiment of foot in the earl of Northumberland’s Army raised to fight
                    the Scots in 1640.<br/>Fourth captain in Thomas Ballard’s regiment of foot
                    raised for Lord Wharton’s Army for service in Ireland in 1642; when Ballard’s
                    regiment of foot instead became part of the earl of Essex’s Army, he remained
                    one of its Captains.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph
                        type="i">Army lists</emph>, 88, 69, 43.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Milbourn, Matthew</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Matthew Milbourn</emph><br/>Ensign in Lord Mandeville’s regiment
                    of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 36.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mildmay, Anthony</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Anthony Mildmay</emph><br/>In 1642 listed as captain of a troop
                    of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 51.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mildmay, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Mildmay </emph>(1619-1692)<br/>Born the eldest son of Sir
                    Henry Mildmay of Graces, Little Baddow, Essex, a family which had risen to
                    greater prominence in the sixteenth century and had acquired much monastic
                    property.<br/>He supported parliament during the civil war and sat on an array
                    of Essex committees during the war and beyond. He also took up arms at the
                    outset of the war and in 1642 was listed as captain of a troop of horse in the
                    earl of Essex’s Army.<br/>In 1649 he declined to sit in the high court appointed
                    to try the king, he was an opponent of the Protectorate although elected to all
                    three Protectorate Parliaments and in 1659 was arrested (though swiftly
                    released) on suspicion of involvement in Booth’s Rising. However, he seems to
                    have had reservations about the Restoration regime and was not again an MP until
                    the three Exclusion Parliaments, in which he supported exclusion. By the time of
                    the Glorious Revolution he was clearly a Whig.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1660-1690</emph>, 3.
                        64-5.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mildmay, Henry</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Henry Mildmay</emph><br/>From the county of Essex, he was a
                    captain in the earl of Essex’s Army during the first months of the civil war,
                    but in summer 1643 he became a colonel and was given a command of a regiment of
                    foot in the Eastern Association Army, at least part of which served under him
                    during his time as governor of Cambridge.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.67; Holmes, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 121, 125, 126, 215-16.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Ea</emph><emph type="i">rl of Essex;
                        Ea</emph><emph type="i">stern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mildmay, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Mildmay</emph><br/>Listed in 1642 as cornet in (presumably
                    his kinsman) Henry Mildmay’s troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 51.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miles, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Miles</emph><br/>Captain in the regiment of foot in the
                    earl of Essex’s Army commanded by Lord Oliver St John and then Thomas Essex in
                        1642-3.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mill, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mill</emph><br/>Captain in Lord Robartes’s regiment of foot
                    in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642. He first appears receiving money for the
                    regiment, totalling &#xa3;1,244 8s on 20 Aug. 1642, Robartes endorsing the pay
                    warrant that he had appointed his servant John Mill to receive the money. Named
                    as captain on pay warrant for 28 days from 30 Sept. 1642. He was still in the
                    regiment as captain in Oct. 1644 and at its disbandment in 1645, the rank he
                    held when the Lords attempted unsuccessfully to have the officers of Robartes’s
                    regiment en bloc taken into the New Model in place of those proposed for John
                    Pickering’s regiment in the New Model Army by Fairfax.<br/>Although that
                    proposal was dropped, with the formation of the New Model Army Mill was
                    appointed captain of Richard Ingoldsby’s New Model regiment of foot. By July
                    1648 Mill was major of the regiment, and acting governor of Oxford, dealing with
                    a failed conspiracy within the university. In Sept. 1649, while commanding five
                    of the companies stationed at Oxford, he was seized during a brief Leveller
                    mutiny within the regiment. In 1651 he was promoted acting, and then permanent,
                    lieutenant-colonel, and in Sept. 1655 colonel. He was loyal to the Protectorate,
                    one of three officers entrusted to enforce the exclusion of MPs from the 1656
                    Parliament, but he became an opponent of Cromwell accepting the crown,
                    presenting the petition of a hundred officers against it in Feb. 1657. He was
                    loyal to Richard Cromwell but displaced in favour of William Sydenham in June
                    1659; in Feb. 1660 he was re-instated as lieutenant-colonel of the regiment
                    under Sir John Lenthall.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph
                        type="i">Army lists</emph>, 37; TNA, SP28/1a/123; SP28/2b/358; SP28/19/35;
                    Temple, ‘New Model Army’, 58; Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental
                        history</emph>, 1.377-84; Temple, ‘New Model Army’, 71; TNA, E121/2/2/25,
                    second moiety # 37; E121/2/10/49 # 610 [both G].<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Millard, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Millard</emph><br/>Lieutenant in William Colemore’s company
                    in John Barker’s/Thomas Willoughby’s regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army</emph>,
                        22.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                    >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Millard, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Millard</emph><br/>Cornet in Battersby’s troop in
                    Hesilrige’s regiment of horse in Waller’s Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army</emph>,
                        64.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Miller</emph> (died 1645)<br/>Quartermaster in Cheshire. Buried
                    26 Sept. 1644, Nantwich.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire tracts</emph>, 258.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Miller</emph><br/>At some point before the reduction of the
                    regiment in spring 1644, at which point he left the army, captain in the earl of
                    Manchester’s regiment of dragoons in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 1.59.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Miller</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel Robert Duckenfeild’s
                    regiment in Cheshire by 12 Nov. 1645, though not recorded on list of
                    Apr..<br/>Records survive of pay to him and to other officers and soldiers of
                    Major Bradshawe’s company and specifically to Captain Miller for himself,
                    officers and soldiers 14 days’ pay, for his service in the leaguer before
                    Chester and as part of Colonel Duckenfeild’s regiment.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: TNA, SP28/224, f. 57.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Miller</emph><br/>Down to summer 1645, ensign in Peter
                    Burgoyne’s company in John Barker’s/Thomas Willoughby’s regiment of
                        foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army</emph>, 22.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Miller</emph><br/>Served as ensign to Captain Robert Cobbet,
                    both in his company in Lord Grey of Warke’s short-lived regiment of foot in the
                    Eastern Association Army during the first half of 1643 and in Colonel James
                    Carr’s regiment of foot in Sir William Waller’s Army from the end of 1643. He
                    was a lieutenant, and by summer 1647 a captain, in Barkstead’s New Model Army
                    regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 1.38; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model
                        Army</emph>, I, 87, 99.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">; Sir William Waller</emph><emph
                        type="i">; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Miller</emph><br/>A captain of this name may have served
                    in the latter half of 1643 in Sir John Pickering’s short-lived regiment of
                    dragoons in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.82; Holmes, <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph>, 169.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i"> Ea</emph><emph type="i">stern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Miller, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Miller</emph><br/>Ensign in Sir William Constable’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 42.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mills, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mills</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Captain Henry Pinckney’s
                    company in the Red regiment, London Auxiliaries (Colonel Samuel Harsnett) when
                    it mustered on 27 Apr. 1644. He had been promoted captain by 22 Oct.
                        1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/121A, f. 694 r. &amp;
                    v.; Nagel, ‘London militia’, 317; Marshall, <emph type="i">Essex funeral</emph>,
                        11.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Milner, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Milner</emph><br/>At late 1644, ensign in John Jenkins’s
                    company in John Pickering’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.102.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Ea</emph><emph type="i">stern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Milton, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Milton</emph> (died ?1661)<br/>Of St Dunstan in the East,
                    London. In 1638 he was resident in Port Lane, where he was assessed at a rent of
                    &#xa3;25.<br/>Admitted to the Company of the Artillery Garden (now the
                    Honourable Artillery Company).<br/>Quartermaster to the White regiment, London
                    Trained Bands (Colonel Isaac Penington) (Thrale 1642 calls him John Melton). He
                    was captain-lieutenant in the same regiment (then serving with Sir William
                    Waller as part of Richard Browne’s London brigade) on 29 Mar. 1644, when he was
                    wounded and taken prisoner by the royalists at the battle of Cheriton: ‘but we
                    hope to morrow to redeeme him by a strong hand’ (<emph type="i">Letter of
                        Captain Jones</emph>). In Mar. 1645 he was a captain at
                    Whitechapel, where he had arrested a royalist suspect. By Oct. 1646 he was
                    captain in the White regiment (by then under Colonel Thomas Player). By 23 July
                    1647 he was major of the White regiment (now Colonel Joseph Vaughan), paid for his
                    service within the London lines of communication from 11 June until then by the
                    Presbyterian militia committee. The form of the warrant is consistent with other
                    officers known to have been purged then, but other sources show he was retained
                    (and had possibly been promoted) by the Presbyterian committee. He was involved
                    in the invasion of parliament by the London crowd on 26 July to force the Houses
                    to reinstate the Presbyterian militia committee. With the failure of the
                    Presbyterian coup, ‘valiant and resolute Major Milton’ was put out (<emph
                        type="i">A paire of spectacles for the Citie</emph>, (1648), 9). On 24 Sept.
                    1647 the Commons voted that a John Milton junior be indicted of High Treason in
                    King’s Bench.<br/>On 29 Jan. 1658 Ann, wife of Major John Milton, was buried in
                    St Dunstan in the East. There may have been two John Miltons in the parish by
                    the late 1650s (or just possibly one who remarried quickly). A John Milton was
                    buried in the parish on 7 June 1661.<br/>Indeed, there were probably two John
                    Miltons in London in 1647-8 (as the ‘junior’ in the 1647 accusation implies, and
                    excluding the poet), and possibly two in St Dunstan in the East in the late
                    1650s. Three days after one (almost certainly the militia officer) was named in
                    Apr. 1648 as involved in the invasion of parliament, (presumably) another was
                    named as a collector for Tower Ward of the arrears of assessments for the Army.
                    The military career which can be reconstructed makes most sense as belonging to
                    one man, but the Quartermaster and Captain-Lieutenant might be different
                        men.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Thrale 1642; Nagel, ‘London
                    militia’, 317-8, 320; W.N. Parker, <emph type="i">Milton: a biography</emph>, 2
                    vols. (1968), 2.894-5;<emph type="i"> Life records of John Milton </emph>comp.
                    J. Milton French, (5 vols. 1949-58), 5.405;<emph type="i"> A letter from Captain
                        Jones to a worthy friend of his dwelling in Bartholmew Lane : being a more
                        full and an exacter relation of the particular proccedings of Sir William
                        VVallers armie then any that hath yet been published</emph> (1644); <emph
                        type="i">Kingdomes Weekly</emph><emph type="i"> Intelligencer</emph>, 21-28
                    Sept. 1647, no. 228, 683; <emph type="i">A paire of spectacles for the Citie
                    </emph>(1648), 9; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 5.317; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>,
                    10.219, 230: <emph type="i">St </emph><emph type="i">Dunstan in the East
                        registers</emph>, 2.6, 8, 71, 73, 77; Dale, <emph type="i">1638,</emph> 50;
                        <emph type="i">CCAM</emph>, 1.519.<emph type="i"/><br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Minshaw, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Minshaw</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Major George Hutchinson’s
                    company in William Bampfield’s regiment of foot, raised for Lord Wharton’s Army
                    for Ireland in 1642. Instead, he served as captain in William Bampfield’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 70,
                        40.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Minshull [Minshall], Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Minshull [Minshall]</emph> (died 1643)<br/>Buried
                    Nantwich, 14 July 1643. Captain of a foot company, probably that commanded after
                    his death by Captain Thomas Malbon in Colonel Booth’s regiment.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/224, f. 327; <emph type="i">Cheshire
                        tracts</emph>, 256.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mitchell, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Mitchell</emph><br/>Of Haslehead, Thurlstone township,
                    Penistone, Yorkshire lieutenant in Captain Adam Eyre’s troop; in Jan. 1647 they
                    went together to meet the committees to state their accounts.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Eyre, 2, 21; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’,
                        117.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mitchell, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mitchell</emph><br/>Of Liversedge, Yorkshire (West Riding),
                    a parliamentarian lieutenant in Yorkshire.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Hopper, ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 104.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mitchell, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Mitchell</emph><br/>Of Morthen, Whiston parish, near
                    Rotherham, Yorkshire (West Riding), son of Christopher Mitchell of Morthen and
                    grandson of James Mitchell, merchant. His cousinage included William Spenser and
                    Francis Rogers.<br/>By spring 1645 Mitchell was a captain in the Hull garrison
                    in Colonel John Mauleverer’s garrison regiment (from early 1648, Robert
                    Overton’s). He remained in that New Model Army regiment, going with it to
                    Scotland. By 21 Sept. 1650 he was a major, given joint command of the garrison
                    at Linlithgow. He was later promoted to lieutenant-colonel of the regiment, and
                    in spring 1655 he became its colonel. Whilst the regiment was stationed in
                    Scotland, Mitchell spent much of his time in England and in 1658 pledged his
                    support to Oliver Cromwell and upon the latter’s death he and his regiment
                    accepted Richard Cromwell as Lord Protector.<br/>In 1659 Mitchell lost his
                    command upon Overton’s restoration. He was to be compensated with the creation
                    of a new regiment, and he may have been given a company at Hull towards it, but
                    it is not clear whether the regiment was ever formed.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’, 393; Firth and Davies, <emph
                        type="i">Regimental history</emph>, 1.239-40, 2.554-7; Hopper, ‘Yorkshire
                    parliamentarians’, 120; Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 89.
                    101. 103; TNA, E121/5/7, no. 79.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Yorkshire; Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army (Poyntz);
                        Northern Army (Lambert); New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Molanus, Johannes Conradus [John Conradt]</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Johannes Conradus [John Conradt] Molanus </emph>(died
                    1661)<br/>Of Middleton-by-Wirksworth, Derbyshire, but in his origins a Dutchman,
                    Molanus evidently came to England with the drainage engineer Cornelius
                    Vermuyden, acting as his agent at Hatfield Chase in 1628. Vermuyden’s
                    involvement in the drainage of the Dovegang Mine at Wirksworth brought Molanus
                    to Derbyshire. He was living in or near Middleton by 1633, and was Gell’s tenant
                    by 1642.<br/>Gell commissioned Molanus Major in his regiment of foot in Nov.
                    1642; he also acted as Gell’s Commissary until 7 Jan. 1643.<br/>In Dec. 1642
                    Molanus commanded a force of 400 foot and a company of dragoons which stormed
                    and looted Bretby Hall. He commanded, or jointly commanded, a number of the
                    expeditions of Derbyshire forces outside the county. In Dec. 1642 he helped the
                    Nottinghamshire parliamentarians in repairing the defences of Nottingham, and in
                    Feb. 1643 took part in the unsuccessful attack on Newark. In Apr. he and Thomas
                    Gell took 500 men to help Lewis Chadwick in Staffordshire to take Sutton
                    (Derbys.).<br/>In Sept. 1643 Molanus was sent to the support of Nottingham with
                    a force of horse and dragoons. He helped drive off royalists who were bombarding
                    the castle (according to Gell, Molanus’s men drove them off; according to Lucy
                    Hutchinson, the royalists had withdrawn without fighting and Molanus let them go
                    whilst his men looted the houses). Molanus did refuse to join with Colonel John
                    Hutchinson in attacking a fortified bridge across the Trent: ‘the maior of
                    Derby, an old dull-headed Dutchman, sayd ten thousand men could not doe it’
                    (Hutchinson, <emph type="i">Life</emph>, 157-8). He returned to Derby, but was
                    sent back to take the fort, which the royalists abandoned after they were driven
                    from their trenches.<br/>In Dec. 1643 Molanus was engaged in skirmishing in
                    Staffordshire and Derbyshire. In Feb.-Mar. 1644 he was at the siege of
                    Newark.<br/>In late 1645 Molanus was sent to besiege Chatsworth; after its
                    surrender he joined up with Poyntz’s Army, and he was at the storming of Belvoir
                    (17 Nov.).<br/>On 25 Mar. 1646 Molanus and the Derbyshire foot stood firm when
                    the royalists attacked Poyntz’s camp at Stoke.<br/>In the political attacks on
                    Gell, Molanus was accused of involvement in Gell’s alleged peculation. By Feb.
                    1646 Molanus had evidently fallen out with Gell (Thomas Gell in a letter alluded
                    to when Molanus had accused Sir John of treason).<br/>During the war Molanus had
                    kept up his business, renting a smelting mill and buying ore from Sir John Gell.
                    He remained a mine-owner and lead-smelter at Wirksworth after the war and was
                    alive in 1655.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Brighton, ‘Civil War’,
                    46-49; Slack, <emph type="i">Man at War</emph>, esp. 33, 72, 76, 81-4, 91-2, 97,
                    102-3, 134, 137-9, 147, 161.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Derbyshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Molden, Daniel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Daniel Molden</emph><br/>Captain of horse of long service in an
                    unidentified regiment in Yorkshire, claiming arrears of &#xa3;682 19s in
                        1648.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                        394.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Molyneux, Josias</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Josias Molyneux</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir Arthur Hesilrige’s
                    regiment of horse in Waller’s Army. Captain-lieutenant in John Butler’s New
                    Model regiment of horse (lately Sir Arthur Hesilrige’s and later Thomas
                    Horton’s). When Butler left the regiment in 1647, Molyneux became captain of the
                    troop, and remained as such until 1649.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph> 54<br/><emph type="b"
                    >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association); New Model
                        Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Momford, Peter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Peter Momford</emph><br/>Captain in Thomas Ballard’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 43.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Monings, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William Monings</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir William Ogle’s
                    regiment of foot in Northumberland’s Army against the Scots in
                    1640.<br/>Lieutenant-colonel in Sir William Fairfax’s regiment of foot in the
                    earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock,
                        <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 86, 43.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Monorgund [Monogrund], -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- </emph><emph type="b">Monorgund [Monogrund]</emph><br/>An
                    officer in Gloucestershire, noted 12 Apr. 1643.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 6. 635 [citing TNA, SP28/299/720], TNA, SP28/129, Part 5, fol.
                        4r.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Glo</emph><emph
                        type="i">ucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Montagu [Mountague], Edward [later first earl of Sandwich]</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Montagu [Mountague], later first earl of Sandwich</emph>
                    (1625-1672)<br/>Born Barnwell, Northamptonshire, second but in due course eldest
                    surviving son and heir of Sir Sidney Montagu (died 1644), of the Montagu family
                    of Hinchingbrooke, Huntingdon; the earl of Manchester, commander-in-chief of the
                    Eastern Association, was a cousin.<br/>He was in his late teens when in summer
                    1643 he was commissioned colonel of a regiment of foot in the Eastern
                    Association Army. Raised in Cambridgeshire and the Isle of Ely, the regiment
                    spent much of winter 1643-44 based at Newport Pagnell and taking part in
                    operations in the area, including the capture of Hillesden. During 1644 it
                    besieged Lincoln and York, took part in the campaign and battle of Marston Moor,
                    the ensuing capture of a string of minor royalist bases in southern Yorkshire
                    during the rest of the summer, followed by the campaign and second battle of
                    Newbury during the autumn. He supported Cromwell in his subsequent attack upon
                    his cousin. In winter 1644-5 Montagu and his regiment spent further time at
                    Newport Pagnell and in Henley-on-Thames, of which Montagu had been appointed
                    governor. The regiment transferred more or less complete, initially still under
                    Montagu, into the New Model Army upon its formation in spring 1645 and played an
                    active role in the New Model’s campaigns of summer and autumn 1645, fighting at
                    Naseby and Bristol. In Oct. 1645 he was elected Recruiter MP for Huntingdonshire
                    in the Long Parliament and resigned his army command in line with the
                    Self-Denying Ordinance.<br/>Although he withdrew from parliament at Pride’s
                    Purge, he returned to politics after the ejection of the Rump, as a member of
                    the Nominated Assembly and of Cromwell’s Protectoral Council; from the mid-1650s
                    onwards he was also active and successful as a naval commander
                    (‘general-at-sea’). He actively supported the Restoration, ensuring that the
                    fleet was loyal, and he was rewarded with an earldom and high office. He served
                    Charles II both as a diplomat and at sea as an admiral in the second and third
                    Anglo-Dutch wars. He perished in a naval battle in Southwold
                        Bay/Solebay.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Montagu, Edward, second earl of Manchester</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Montagu, </emph><emph type="b">second</emph><emph type="b"
                        > earl of Manchester </emph>(1602-1671)<br/>Eldest son of Henry Montagu,
                    first earl of Manchester (died 1642), of Kimbolton, Huntingdon. Edward
                    represented Huntingdonshire in the later parliaments of James I and the opening
                    parliaments of Charles I, before being raised to the peerage in spring 1626 as
                    Lord Kimbolton, as well as gaining the courtesy title of Viscount Mandeville. In
                    that year, too, his second marriage to a daughter of Robert Rich, second earl of
                    Warwick, cemented his links to a group of peers who during the 1630s became
                    disaffected from and out of favour with the king. He was critical of royal
                    government in the Short Parliament and was one of the peers who pressed for the
                    summoning of another parliament in summer and autumn 1640. He was a prominent
                    critic of the king’s government during the opening phase of the Long Parliament
                    and in Jan. 1642 he was the only peer named alongside the 5 MPs whose arrest
                    Charles unsuccessfully sought on charges of treason.<br/>In autumn 1642 he
                    raised a regiment of foot within Essex’s Army – generally referred to as Lord
                    Mandeville’s regiment of foot – but it performed poorly at Edgehill and was
                    probably disbanded shortly after the stand-off at Turnham Green in Nov. 1642.
                    Having succeeded his father as earl of Manchester, in Aug. 1643 he replaced Lord
                    Grey of Warke as Major General (and thus commander-in-chief) of the Eastern
                    Association Army, at which point he raised and commanded a trio of new
                    regiments.<br/>His regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army was raised
                    in late summer 1643 and fought at the battles of Winceby and Marston Moor, after
                    which it took part in the short campaign to mop up minor royalist bases in
                    southern Yorks; it was back with the main Eastern Association Army for the
                    campaign and second battle of Newbury in autumn 1644. In spring 1645 the
                    regiment was absorbed into the New Model Army.<br/>His regiment of foot in the
                    Eastern Association Army was raised in Essex in summer 1643. Despite some
                    initial problems both recruiting to and equipping the regiment, for a time it
                    was very large, with eighteen companies nearly a double regiment. During 1644 it
                    campaigned in the east Midlands and Lincolnshire, including playing a role
                    during the campaign and battle of Marston Moor. It was broken up and in large
                    part disbanded in spring 1645 rather than being incorporated en bloc into the
                    New Model Army.<br/>His regiment of dragoons was raised in Essex in Aug. 1643;
                    it was reduced in size and taken over by John Lilburne in spring 1644 and it was
                    thus Lilburne who commanded it at Marston Moor and in capturing a string of
                    royalist outposts in southern Yorkshire in summer 1644.<br/>As well as actively
                    campaigning and leading these regiments and the Eastern Association Army in
                    1643-4, Manchester worked to improve the running, administration and finance of
                    the Eastern Association from his base at Cambridge; he also attended parliament
                    from time to time.<br/>Having led the Eastern Association Army at the siege of
                    York in spring 1644 and to success at Marston Moor on 2 July, his comparative
                    military inactivity over the succeeding weeks and months and the criticism which
                    he attracted for alleged lethargy during and immediately after the second battle
                    of Newbury in Oct. – though he was far from the only senior parliamentarian to
                    under-perform there – led to the bitter clash with Cromwell later in the year
                    and, indirectly but in turn, to the Self-Denying Ordinance and the creation of a
                    new army which ended his military career.<br/>From his base in the House of
                    Lords, Manchester retained political office and influence in the mid and later
                    1640s; in July 1647 he supported the Army when it restored order in London and
                    Westminster. He opposed and had no part in the regicide and was effectively in
                    retirement and out of office during the 1650s.<br/>He welcomed the Restoration
                    and, while his political role during the 1660s was not huge, he returned to
                    favour and office at the court and in central and local government.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph><br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Montgomery, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George Montgomery</emph><br/>Major in the earl of Manchester’s
                    regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army down to Jan. 1645 or
                        later.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 1.62.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moody, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Moody</emph><br/>Captain in Colonel Charles Fleetwood’s
                    regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army by spring 1644 and served with
                    that regiment through to spring 1645, but does not appear to have transferred
                    with it into the New Model Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring,
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.35.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moody, Samuel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Samuel Moody</emph><br/>By autumn 1643 and continuing to serve
                    until the regiment transferred to the New Model Army in spring 1645, captain in
                    Vermuyden’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.102; Holmes, <emph type="i">Eastern
                    Association</emph>, 240.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Moore</emph><br/>Regimental chaplain to the Southwark
                    auxiliaries regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Waller's Army</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Southwark</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Daniel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Daniel Moore</emph><br/>Captain in Southwark Trained Bands
                    regiment questioned in parliament as a defaulter refusing to do his required
                    guard duty; described by Richard Symonds as ‘not confided in by the Parliament’.
                    A dyer by trade.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Nagel, ‘London militia’,
                    92; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 2.946.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Southwark</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Moore</emph><br/>A captain in the Lancashire regiment of
                    foot commanded by (perhaps his kinsman) John Moore.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Gratton, <emph type="i">Lancs. war effort</emph>,
                        291.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Hugh</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Hugh Moore</emph><br/>Ensign in John Bodley’s company Anthony
                    Stapley’s Sussex regiment of foot by 2 Feb. 1645.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        122.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Sussex; Waller
                        (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, James</td>
                <td><emph type="b">James Moore</emph><br/>In 1642 listed as lieutenant in Francis
                    Fiennes’s troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 51.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, James</td>
                <td><emph type="b">James Moore</emph><br/>Lieutenant-colonel in the earl of
                    Denbigh’s Army, receiving payments on 11 Sept. 1643 and 28 Apr. 1644 (on the
                    latter occasion he was paid &#xa3;10, half to bear his charges to London, half
                    for his quarters).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/131, Part 12,
                    ff. 12, 24.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Denbigh</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Moore</emph><emph type="b"/>(c. 1599-1650)<br/>Of Bank Hall,
                    Walton, Lancashire, eldest son of Edward Moore (c.1577-1632), merchant, of Bank
                    Hall, Walton, and his wife, Katherine (died 1641), daughter of John and Margaret
                    Hockenhull of Prenton on the Wirral, Cheshire. His wealth was based on land and
                    trade.<br/>Mayor of Liverpool in 1633 and MP for Liverpool in the Long
                    Parliament, where he served on several committees.<br/>In Apr. 1642 Moore helped
                    organize the resistance to James Stanley, Lord Strange (later earl of Derby) and
                    as a colonel in West Derby Hundred helped secure Liverpool for parliament. From
                    Aug. 1642 to Apr. 1643 he was colonel and captain of the guard of horse and foot
                    in Westminster.<br/>In Aug. 1643 Moore went back to Lancashire as colonel of a
                    regiment of foot, captain of a troop of horse, and governor of Liverpool
                    (records of debentures in TNA, E121/5/7 suggest that he had at least three
                    troops under command). He escaped from Liverpool by boat when the town fell to
                    Prince Rupert in May 1644, and although re-instated when it was recaptured, his
                    role in its failed defence remained controversial and there were attempts to
                    displace him. He finally relinquished the governorship in May 1645 under the
                    Self-Denying Ordinance. He was again active in parliament, although he returned
                    to Lancashire in autumn 1645 to help in the final parliamentarian
                    victory.<br/>In 1646 Moore raised a new regiment and went to Ireland, where by
                    early 1647 he was governor of both County Louth and Dundalk and a commissioner
                    for Ireland.<br/>He returned to England in Jan. 1648 and was a supporter of
                    Pride’s Purge and signed the king’s death warrant.<br/>In 1649 Moore claimed
                    arrears of &#xa3;2,368 16s 4d. In June he returned to Ireland and served there
                    as a colonel until his death. He fought at Rathmines (Aug. 1649) and died of a
                    fever whilst besieging Tecroghan Castle, County Meath.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; Keeler, <emph type="i"
                        >Long </emph><emph type="i">P</emph><emph type="i">arliament</emph>, 277;
                    Gratton, <emph type="i">Lancs. war effort</emph>, 290-2 and <emph type="i"
                        >passim</emph>; <emph type="i">Warr in Lancashire</emph>, 10, 44; Blackwood,
                        <emph type="i">Lancashire g</emph><emph type="i">entry</emph>, 108; Firth
                    and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental history</emph>, 2.650-2; <emph type="i"
                        >Moore Mss.</emph>; <emph type="i">HoP: The Commons, 1640-1660
                        </emph>(forthcoming).<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Lancashire; London; Ireland; New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Nicholas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Nicholas Moore</emph><br/>Captain in Sir William Waller’s (later
                    James Holborne’s regiment of dragoons) from 1 Aug. 1643. Possibly the Nicholas
                    Moore who became major in John Okey’s regiment of dragoons in the New Model
                    Army, although the latter may have been Major Nicholas Moore of the earl of
                    Manchester’s regiment of dragoons in the Eastern Association.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s army,</emph>
                        41.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern
                        Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Moore</emph><br/>A lieutenant-colonel in the Plymouth
                    garrison, 1645-6.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Worth, <emph type="i"
                        >History of Plymouth</emph>, 134.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Devon</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Moore</emph><br/>In Feb. and Mar. 1644 he was
                    lieutenant-colonel in James Kerr’s [Carr’s] regiment of foot, before going west
                    to serve under Kerr at the same rank in his Plymouth garrison
                        regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army</emph>, 37.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Waller (Southern Association); Waller </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Roger</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Roger Moore</emph><br/>Ensign in Captain Robert Long’s company in
                    Lord Wharton’s regiment of foot in Wharton’s army raised for service in Ireland
                    in 1642; later that summer he went instead with the regiment as ensign in Lord
                    Wharton’s regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 68,
                        31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                    Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Sackville</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sackville Moore</emph><br/>Major in the earl of Manchester’s
                    regiment of dragoons in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.57;
                    Holmes, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 201.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moore, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Moore</emph><br/>Captain of dragoons in Dec. 1642,
                    probably in Waller’s own regiment of dragoons. His account in June 1643, for
                    monies owed from Waller and Essex for Feb. and Mar. in Sussex and Hampshire,
                    refers to a cornet, suggesting horse rather than dragoons.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peachey and Turton, <emph type="i">Fall of the
                        West</emph>, 7.715; TNA, SP28/6/40.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Earl of Essex; Waller </emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mordant, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Mordant</emph><br/>In May 1643, captain serving in one of the
                    three regiments of foot formed from the Essex militia, part of the Eastern
                    Association Army that contributed to the siege of Reading in spring 1643, the
                    siege of Greenland House in summer 1644 and probably to some other actions in
                    which the Army was involved.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 1.33.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mordaunt, John, first earl of Peterborough</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mordaunt, </emph><emph type="b">first</emph><emph type="b">
                        earl of Peterborough </emph>(1599-1643)<br/>Born Lowick, Northants, the son
                    of Henry Mordaunt, fourth Lord Mordaunt, into a prominent but Catholic family,
                    though John was brought up a Protestant. He became a courtier and close to both
                    James I and the duke of Buckingham, given office both at court and in
                    Northamptonshire and in 1628 created first earl of Peterborough. However, he
                    became increasingly distant from Charles I, resisting both ship money and
                    service in the Scots Wars, he supported parliament in 1641-2 and in summer 1642
                    was created colonel and given command of a troop of horse and a regiment of foot
                    in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/>In autumn 1642 much of the regiment garrisoned
                    Banbury, though Peterborough himself – who was also General of the Ordnance –
                    and some of his men were present at Edgehill. His lieutenant-colonel defected to
                    the king in the course of the battle and much of his regiment performed poorly
                    and surrendered Banbury shortly afterwards. Although the regiment was partly
                    refounded late in 1642 and took part in the siege of Reading in spring 1643, by
                    then Peterborough was ailing – probably of consumption – and he died in June
                    1643. After his death, his regiment appears to have been broken up and much of
                    it disbanded.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph>; Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 25, 28, 48; TNA,
                        SP28/2b/390.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mordent, Lewis</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Lewis Mordent</emph><br/>Ensign in the regiment of foot in the
                    earl of Essex’s Army commanded by Lord Oliver St John and then Thomas Essex in
                        1642-3.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex; Bristol</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>More, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward More</emph><br/>Perhaps a younger son of Thomas More of
                    Larden, Shropshire. Captain in Thomas Mytton’s regiment of horse by July 1645,
                    when he was based at Oswestry. Still there in Dec. By Mar. 1647, when one of the
                    commissioners for the surrender of Harlech Castle, promoted to major.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Perfect Passages</emph>, 9-16
                    July 1645; Dore, <emph type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 2. 392; J.R.
                    Phillips, <emph type="i">Memoirs of the Civil War in Wales and the
                        Marches</emph> (1874), II, 333.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Shropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>More, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard More</emph><br/>Lieutenant in the regiment of foot in the
                    earl of Essex’s Army commanded by Lord Oliver St John and then Thomas Essex in
                        1642-3.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army
                        lists</emph>, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>More, Samuel</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Samuel More</emph><br/>On Linley, Shropshire, son of Richard More
                    (died Dec, 1643), the MP for Bishop’s Castle in the Long Parliament.<br/>Samuel
                    was appointed to the Shropshire county committee in 1643 and by autumn 1643 was
                    an officer, probably Captain, in garrison at Brampton Bryan Castle on the
                    Shropshire/Herefordshire border. By early 1644 he was commanding the garrison in
                    nearby Hopton Castle, Shropshire, resisting a prolonged siege and repeated
                    attacks before surrendering on minimal terms; he was taken prisoner and survived
                    but most of the garrison were then killed. He was exchanged duringthe spring and
                    by 20 June was an officer at Wem. He was with the Shropshire horse in the attack
                    on and capture of Shrewsbury in Feb. 1645 and by Oct. was governor of Montgomery
                    Castle, Montgomeryshire. By the end of 1645 he was a colonel and he and his
                    troop, together with other Shropshire horse, were serving at the siege of
                    Chester. He commanded a Shropshire force which on 8 Mar. 1646 at Church Stoke,
                    Shropshire, cornered and forced the surrender of what remained of Sir John
                    Watts’s garrison who were retreating from Chirk Castle. A colonel commanding
                    both Shropshire and Montgomeryshire Forces at the siege of Ludlow in spring
                    1646. He became governor of Ludlow Castle upon its surrender in June 1646 and
                    later in the summer was appointed Mackworth’s deputy and thus second-in-command
                    of the remaining Shropshire county forces. He was a very active committeeman,
                    named to all Shropshire committees 1644-8.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    HMC, <emph type="i">Calendar of the Manuscripts of the Marquis of Bath, I</emph>
                    (1904), 29-30, 36-40; Warws. RO, C2017/C9/98, C2017/C9/133; Dore, <emph type="i"
                        >Brereton letter books</emph>, 2. 162, 204; <emph type="i">Colonell Mitton’s
                        Reply to </emph><emph type="i">Lieutenant Colonell Reinking’s Relation of
                        the taking of Shrewbury</emph> (1645); <emph type="i">Perfect
                        Occurrences</emph>, 8 May 1646; <emph type="i">CSPD, 1645-47</emph>, 441;
                        <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, IV, 614;<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Shropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moreland, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Moreland</emph><br/>From 1642 down to 1646, ensign in
                    Robert Colemore’s company in John Barker’s/Thomas Willoughby’s regiment of
                        foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Waller’s
                        army</emph>, 23.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Warwickshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moreton, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Moreton</emph><br/>Served for a time as major in James Kerr’s
                    [Carr’s] regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Waller’s army</emph>, 37.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moreton, Leonard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Leonard Moreton</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Thomas Ballard’s
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 43.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morgan, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Morgan </emph><br/>Captain of dragoons in
                    Kent by 6 Jan. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph
                        type="i">Waller’s army</emph>, 70.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Kent; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morgan, Miles</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Miles Morgan</emph><br/>In 1642 cornet in William Pretty’s troop
                    of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 49.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morgan, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Morgan</emph> (1604-1679)<br/>Colonel. Eldest of the four
                    children of Lewis Morgan, landowner, of Llangattock Lingoed, Monmouthshire. He
                    married firstly an unknown woman on the Continent in 1632 and (2) Delariviere
                    Cholmondeley (died in or before 1683), daughter of John Cholmondeley of Braham
                    Hall, Spofforth, near Knaresborough, Yorkshire in Aug. 1644. A professional
                    soldier from the age of sixteen, he served in the Low Countries under Sir Horace
                    Vere and Bernard of Saxe-Weimar, and alongside George Monck and Charles
                    Fairfax.<br/>By Apr. 1643 a captain raising dragoons in the Elland and Barnsley
                    area of Yorkshire. His company was in the forlorn hope at Adwalton
                    Moor.<br/>Promoted major, and in Sept. 1643 took his dragoons and then into
                    Lincolnshire and to Nantwich, where his brother, his lieutenant, was
                    killed.<br/>Chief engineer at the siege of Lathom House, March 1644.<br/>March
                    1644 promoted colonel of dragoons in the regiment formerly Sir William
                    Constable’s/Sir William Fairfax’s.<br/>He was at the siege of York and Marston
                    Moor, and at Pontefract on 1 March 1645, when he held Ferrybridge long enough
                    for the parliamentarians to escape; in June his dragoons were sent to Sandal
                    Castle.<br/>Appointed governor of Gloucester in succession to Edward Massey on
                    18 June 1645.<br/>Colonel of a regiment of horse in Gloucestershire and of the
                    governor’s regiment of foot (previously Edward Massey’s).<br/>Campaigns in
                    Gloucestershire, Herefordshire and Monmouthshire in the First Civil War. Failing
                    to get a command in Ireland in 1648, he retired to Yorkshire until
                    1651.<br/>Service in Scotland and Flanders; an ally of Monck’s at the
                        Restoration.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the
                    North’, 394; <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>,
                        4.632-4<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Gloucestershire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morgin, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Morgin</emph><br/>A lieutenant buried at Nantwich, 7 Feb.
                    1644. This was a couple of weeks after the battle there, so he may have been an
                    officer of either Sir William Brereton’s Cheshire Army or Sir Thomas Fairfax’s
                    Yorkshire Army, or indeed possibly a wounded royalist officer.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Civil war in Cheshire</emph>,
                        257.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morley, Herbert [Harbert]</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Herbert </emph><emph type="b">[Harbert] </emph><emph type="b"
                        >Morley</emph> (1616-1667)<br/>Baptised 1616, eldest son of Robert Morley
                    (died 1632) of Glynde, Sussex, a leading landed and godly family, prominent in
                    the local administration of Sussex; elder brother of William Morley.<br/>He was
                    MP in the Short and Long Parliaments, where he was a prominent critic of royal
                    government. He was commissioned colonel of a regiment of foot and a regiment of
                    horse in winter 1642-3, and between then and resigning his command in spring
                    1645 under the terms of the Self-Denying Ordinance, he divided his time between
                    his duties as an MP at Westminster, where he was increasingly a radical and a
                    political Independent, local administration in Sussex, as the leading light on
                    the county committee, and active campaigning at the head of his
                    regiments.<br/>He and his men may have supported the earl of Essex’s relief of
                    Gloucester in summer 1643 and been present at the first battle of Newbury; he
                    certainly campaigned under Waller at Farnham, Surrey, and Bamber Bridge, Arundel
                    Castle and Chichester, Sussex in 1643-4, as well as at the sieges of Basing
                    House in 1644 – when and where he was wounded – and 1645. From early 1644 he was
                    governor of Arundel Castle. Some of his men probably for a time went off to
                    reinforce the garrisons at Weymouth and Melcombe Regis, Dorset and Abingdon,
                    Oxfordshire. At least parts of his two regiments survived his departure from the
                    army in spring 1645, continuing to be based at Arundel under its new governor,
                    his younger brother William Morley.<br/>Morley supported the army in 1647 and
                    kept his seat at Pride’s Purge, though he was not closely involved in the trial
                    of the king. As a Rumper and republican, he did not favour the Protectorate and,
                    although he was elected to all three Protectorate Parliaments, he was one of
                    those republicans who criticized the regime in the first and third and was
                    excluded from the first session of the second. He was active in the Rump when it
                    returned in 1659-60, though by then he was suspected of possible royalism by
                    former republican colleagues. In the end, he secured a pardon but nothing more
                    at the Restoration. He sat in the Restoration parliament until his
                        death.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph><emph type="i">.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morley, William</td>
                <td><emph type="b">William </emph><emph type="b">Morley</emph> (1621-1679)<br/>Son
                    of Robert Morley (died 1632) of Glynde, Sussex, and his wife Susan
                    (1594/5-1667), daughter and heir of Thomas Hodgson of Framfield; younger brother
                    of Colonel Herbert Morley. He was captain in his brother’s regiment of horse by
                    at least 16 Sept. 1643; he was already a captain by the previous Dec. when he
                    sent a spy to Colonel Edward Apsley during Hopton’s invasion of Sussex By 6 Aug.
                    1644 he and his troop were in John Middleton’s regiment of horse. But by Jan.
                    1645 it was back in his father’s regiment, when it was ordered to escort some of
                    Morley’s infantry regiment into the West. On 1 May 1645 Morley was appointed
                    governor of Arundel Castle in succession to his brother He was still governor in
                    1651 and according to one account the fleeing Charles II almost ran into him
                    whilst he was out hunting; he and his party dismounted to make themselves
                    inconspicuous, and afterwards Charles laughed that, ‘I did not much like his
                    starched mouchates’ (Stanford-Thomas, <emph type="i">Sussex</emph>, 259).<emph
                        type="i"/><br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army,</emph> 97-9; <emph type="i">Sussex Genealogies: Lewes
                        Centre</emph>, comp. J. Comber (1933), 193; Thomas-Stanford, <emph type="i"
                        >Sussex</emph>, 75, 169-70, 259.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Sussex; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morphe [Murphe], Maurice</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Maurice Morphe [Murphe]</emph><br/>25 Sept. 1644-13 Apr. 1646:
                    lieutenant in foot company of Captain Richard Lawrence in regiment of Colonel
                    Robert Butler, Wareham garrison. Arrears claim 30 Oct. 1646.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset Standing Committee</emph>,
                        42.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morris, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Morris</emph><br/>Captain in John Hampden’s regiment of foot in
                    the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock,
                        <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 46.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morris, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">- Morris</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Glisson’s troop in Francis
                    Russell’s regiment of horse in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>,
                        2.98.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morris, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Morris</emph> (c. 1615-1649)<br/>Of North Elmsall township,
                    South Kirkby parish or Esthagh, South Elmshall, near Pontefract, Yorkshire (W.
                    Riding), eldest son of Matthias Morris (Hopper gives North Elmshall as John’s
                    residence; the <emph type="i">Oxford DNB </emph>gives that
                    of him and his father as Esthagh).<br/>Morris served first in Ireland, then came
                    to England as a royalist but defected after the fall of Liverpool, 1 Nov.
                    1644.<br/>Morris joined the Northern Army as major and was promoted to
                    lieutenant-colonel in May 1645 during the siege of Pontefract. Changing sides
                    again, as a royalist during the second civil war he captured Pontefract Castle
                    by guile on 1 June 1648 and held it until Mar. 1649. He was executed on 23 Aug.
                        1649.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph>; <emph type="i"/>Jones, ‘War in the North’, 394-5; Hopper,
                    ‘Yorkshire parliamentarians’, 119.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Yorkshire; Northern Army (Fairfax); Northern Army
                    (Poyntz)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morris, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Morris</emph><br/>Captain of a troop of horse in the earl of
                    Denbigh’s Army. On 14 Apr. 1644 he received monies towards raising, completing
                    and paying his troop. He was also noted in a list of free quarter imposed on
                    named villages in Warwickshire by the earl of Denbigh and his
                        officers.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/131, Part 12, f.
                    22; SP28/136, Part 28.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Denbigh</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morris, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Morris</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Lord Brooke’s regiment of
                    foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Peacock, <emph type="i">Army lists</emph>, 34.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">Earl of Essex</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morton, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Morton</emph><br/>Captain-lieutenant in Sir Thomas Hoogan’s
                    company in Sir John Palgrave’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association
                        Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.77.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Morton [Mooreton], Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Morton</emph> <emph type="b">[Mooreton]</emph><br/>Captain
                    of a troop of horse, which he commanded at some point between Dec. 1644 and Feb.
                    1646 (William Rideout also commanded the same troop). Arrears order, 21 Jan.
                        1647.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Mayo, <emph type="i">Dorset
                        Standing Committee</emph>, 132, 152.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">Dorset</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mosley, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Mosley</emph><br/>Probably Edward Mosley (born 1618/9) of
                    Manchester, second son of Oswald Mosley (died 1630), of Ancoats, Manchester. If
                    the identification is correct, his elder brother Nicholas (baptised 1611, died
                    1672), was a royalist who in July 1642 attempted to secure the ammunition stored
                    in Manchester for James Stanley, Lord Strange, whose estates were confiscated in
                    1643 and who on coronation day 1661 led the procession to Manchester Collegiate
                    Church as ‘Captaine of the Auxiliaries raised in the Towne for the defence of
                    his Majesties most Royal Person and prerogative’ (<emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB</emph> [Nicolas Mosley]).<br/>In 1643 Edward’s sister Margaret
                    (1616-1675) married the Puritan minister John Angier.<br/>Edward was a
                    parliamentarian captain of horse in Lancashire, commanding a troop in succession
                    to John Bexwick. One of his troopers was owed arrears of &#xa3;80 2s. 6d. in
                    Mar. 1652.<br/>In May 1644 he carried the summons of Colonels Richard Holland
                    and Alexander Rigby senior to the countess of Derby summoning her to surrender
                    Lathom House.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Vis. Lancs.,
                        1664</emph>, 213; TNA, E121/4/6; <emph type="i">Lancashire </emph><emph
                        type="i">military proceedings</emph>, 181; R Raines and C.W. Newton, <emph type="i">Life of Humphrey Chetham, founder of the Chetham
                        hospital and library, Manchester</emph>, 2 vols., Chetham
                        Soc, (1903), 1.146; <emph type="i">Oxford DNB </emph>[Nicholas Mosley
                    and John Angier].<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Lancashire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mosley, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mosley</emph><br/>From summer 1642 lieutenant in
                    Ayscough’s troop in Lord Willoughby’s regiment of horse in the earl of Essex’s
                    Army and the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.108.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; Eastern
                    Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mosse, George</td>
                <td><emph type="b">George </emph><emph type="b">Mosse</emph> (died 1643)<br/>The
                    Colonel’s ensign in the Red regiment, London Trained Bands (Colonel Thomas
                    Atkin) in summer 1642; Captain-lieutenant of the colonel’s company in same
                    regiment by Sept. 1643. Killed at the first battle of Newbury (20 Sept.
                        1643).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Thrale 1642; BL, Harl. 986, p.
                        1.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mottershead, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mottershead</emph><br/>Lieutenant in Captain William
                    Watson’s company in Henry Bradshaw’s regiment of foot in the Cheshire militia at
                    the battle of Worcester, 3 Sept. 1651.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Earwaker, <emph type="i">East Cheshire</emph>, 2.64-68.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Cheshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mould, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mould</emph><br/>Lieutenant in the Red regiment, London
                    Trained Bands (Colonel Thomas Atkin) in summer 1642.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Thrale 1642.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph
                        type="i">London</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moulson, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Moulson</emph><br/>By Oct. 1643 and still there in Aug.
                    1644 but subsequently superseded, captain in Sir John Norwich’s regiment of
                    horse in the Eastern Association Army.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.73.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mowsier, John[?] </td>
                <td><emph type="b">John[?] Mowsier</emph><br/>In late 1644 ensign of the colonel’s company in
                    Sir John Pickering’s regiment of foot in the Eastern Association Army. In spring
                    1645 he transferred with the regiment into the New Model Army as a lieutenant,
                    but he was killed at Faringdon in early May 1645.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph>, 2.84;
                    Wanklyn, <emph type="i">New Model Army</emph>, I, 167.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Eastern Association</emph><emph type="i">;
                        New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Moyse, Richard</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Richard Moyse</emph><br/>Captain in Valentine Walton’s regiment
                    of foot in the Eastern Association Army (commanded by James Hobart from spring
                        1645).<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i">Eastern
                        Association</emph>, 2.105.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Eastern Association</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mudd, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">– Mudd </emph>(died 1643)<br/>A captain who fought in the forlorn
                    hope at Adwalton Moor; he died of wounds incurred in the escape from
                        Bradford.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Jones, ‘War in the North’,
                        395.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Yorkshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mugford, Edward</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Edward Mugford </emph><br/>Lieutenant in Edward Harley’s regiment
                    of foot in Gloucs. In Nov. 1644.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: HMC,
                        <emph type="i">Portland Mss.,</emph> III, 130.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mullenex [Mullenax], Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mullenex [Mullenax] </emph><br/>Lieutenant in Sir Thomas
                    Myddelton’s brigade in North Wales. Surviving warrants record payments to
                    Mullenex, at that time still in London, in spring 1644, to enable him to equip
                    himself and, on 23 May 1644, to march out of the City that day.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346, no. 154.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Munday, -</td>
                <td><emph type="b">-</emph><emph type="b"> Munday</emph> (died 1645/6)<br/>Captain
                    in Ralph Weldon’s Kentish regiment of foot by Apr. 1645 and its absorption into
                    the New Model Army. He was killed in the campaign in the West in late 1645 or
                    early 1646.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army,</emph>153; Firth and Davies<emph type="i">, </emph><emph
                        type="i">Regimental</emph><emph type="i"> history,</emph> 2.452-3.<br/><emph
                        type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Waller (Southern Association); Kent;
                        New Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mundy, John</td>
                <td><emph type="b">John Mundy</emph><br/>Of Markeaton, Derbyshire. Commissioned
                    captain in Sir John Gell’s Derbyshire regiment of foot in Nov. 1642. In early
                    1643 he was sent with his company to help fortify Sheffield Castle. He
                    disappears from the record after 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>:
                    Brighton, ‘Civil War’, 46, 49; Brighton, ‘Governor’, 6; Turbutt, <emph type="i"
                        >Derbyshire</emph>, 3.1061.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Derbyshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Murford, Peter</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Peter Murford</emph><br/>Major in Richard Norton’s foot regiment
                    by late 1643.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army</emph>, 112.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Hampshire; Waller (Southern Association)</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Muskett, Fulke</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Fulke Muskett</emph><br/>Lieutenant in the earl of Essex’s own
                    regiment of foot in the earl of Essex’s Army in autumn 1642. On 13 Mar. 1645 the
                    Commons named him as one of the four Captains of Essex’s regiment to be retained
                    in the New Model Army and recommended him as captain in Sir Thomas Fairfax’s
                    regiment of foot, which the Lords duly accepted. In Apr. 1647 Muskett was one of
                    the officers of the regiment who engaged for service in Ireland, and was
                    involved in getting the engagement of the men. In May he was a signatory to an
                    account of the likely willingness of the men to engage for Ireland once
                    indemnity and arrears had been settled. This was countered by the agitators’
                    representation of the soldiers’ grievances. In the summer, in the face of the
                    regiment’s continuing defiance of parliament, Muskett left – or was driven out
                    of – the regiment.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock, <emph type="i"
                        >Army lists</emph>, 26; Firth and Davies, <emph type="i">Regimental
                        h</emph><emph type="i">istory</emph>, I. 317-25; Temple, ‘New Model Army’,
                    55; <emph type="i">JHC</emph>, 4.76, 79; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>, 7.274,
                        279.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of Essex; New
                        Model Army</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Myddelton, Andrew</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Andrew Myddelton</emph><br/>Military treasurer, addressed by Sir
                    Thomas Myddelton as his ‘cousin’ in a number of the warrants directed to him,
                    but there is no mention of him in the extensive Myddelton pedigrees in <emph
                        type="i">Miscellanea Genealogica et Heraldica</emph>, 3rd. ser., volunteer
                        2.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: TNA, SP28/346.<br/><emph type="b"
                        >Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Myddelton, Sir Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir Thomas Myddelton </emph>(1586-1666)<br/>Born London, the only
                    son of a City merchant, who held land in and around Chirk and Chirk Castle,
                    Denbighshire. These were settled on Sir Thomas in 1612, around the time of his
                    first marriage and a few years before he was knighted by James I. He sat in the
                    last parliament of James I and the first of Charles I. Elected to the Long
                    Parliament, Myddelton did not at first stand out as a strong opponent of the
                    king, but in the wake of the Irish Rebellion his position became clearer.<br/>In
                    summer 1643 he was appointed by parliament its commander-in-chief in North
                    Wales, then entirely in royalist hands. He co-operated with Sir William Brereton
                    in the brief parliamentarian expedition in north-east Wales in Nov. 1643 and,
                    more fruitfully, during 1644, raising troops and building up his own brigade or
                    army, securing Oswestry and its hinterland and beginning to push into mid Wales
                    via victory at Montgomery in Sept. and the capture of the castles at Montgomery
                    and Welshpool (Red Castle). However, only limited gains had been made in mid and
                    North Wales by the time he gave up his command in spring 1645 as a consequence
                    of the Self-Denying Ordinance. He played little part in the second civil war, as
                    a moderate was excluded at Pride’s Purge and was largely out of office and under
                    suspicion during the 1650s. He declared for the king in 1659 and actively
                    supported Booth’s Rising, only for Chirk Castle to be attacked and badly
                    damaged. He returned to favour and to parliament at the Restoration.<br/><emph
                        type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford DNB</emph>; <emph type="i"
                        >DWB.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North
                        Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Myddelton, Sir William, second baronet</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Sir William Myddelton, </emph><emph type="b">second</emph><emph
                        type="b"> baronet </emph>(baptised 1603, died 1651/2)<br/>Cousin of Sir
                    Thomas Myddelton and eldest surviving son of Sir Hugh Myddelton of the New River
                    Company, whom he succeeded as Governor. Colonel of a regiment of foot in his
                    cousin’s army. On 3 Jan. 1644 he received a warrant from Essex to search for
                    horses and arms in and about London (within a 20 mile radius). On 22 Mar. 1644
                    an agreement was concluded between Sir William and his cousin that the latter
                    would pay Sir William 6s 8d per head for every man in his regiment of foot, and
                    provide arms and equipment plus 6d apiece for ribbons for the regiment. By June
                    his forces were serving under Denbigh (somewhat mutinously) and on 27 June
                    Denbigh ordered three companies of Sir William’s regiment to reinforce the Wem
                    garrison. Sir William was still absent from Sir Thomas’s main army in Sept., and
                    so took no part in the actions at Montgomery and Red Castle. In letters of 25
                    Sept. and 2 Oct., reporting the victories of Montgomery Castle and Red Castle to
                    the Committee of Both Kingdoms, Sir Thomas Myddelton begged them to send Barton
                    and Sir William Myddelton with horse to him. Sir William had apparently joined
                    his cousin by the end of Oct., when Sir Thomas Middleton ordered pay for
                    quarters and others necessaries of Sir William’s troop.<br/>According to Tucker,
                    he commanded 100 horse in the defeat of the royalist attempt to relieve Beeston
                    Castle in Jan. 1645. He served at the siege of Chester – as such he sat on
                    various courts martial and councils of wars in spring 1645 – and under Mytton
                    was second-in-command at the siege of Denbigh and briefly its governor following
                    its fall.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Miscellanea
                        Genealogica et Heraldica</emph>, 3rd. ser., vol. 2, 270; Dore, <emph
                        type="i">Brereton letter books</emph>, 1. 188, 437, 445; 2. 494; Tucker,
                        <emph type="i">Denbighshire Officers, </emph>76; TNA, SP28/346; <emph
                        type="i">CSPD, 1644; CSPD, 1644-45.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>:
                        <emph type="i">North Wales</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mydhope [Midhope, Medhope], James</td>
                <td><emph type="b">James Mydhope [Midhope, Medhope]</emph><br/>Mydhope was cornet in
                    Captain John Hale’s troop of horse in the earl of Essex’s Army in 1642.<br/>In
                    Apr. 1643, when a lieutenant, Mydhope fought in the defence of Lichfield
                    Cathedral Close against Prince Rupert’s army (from this it is inferred that he
                    was an officer in Brooke’s Army). When a breach was made on 20 Apr., he held it
                    with 40 musketeers. According to the account of Captain John Randolph, ‘these
                    fortie seeing little execution done by their shot, being lead on by that truly
                    valiant Souldier, Leiutenant Mydhope did fall upon their Adversaries (being
                    betweene two or three hundred) pell mell, and with their Butt ends of their
                    Muskets, their Swords, and Holbeards, did most bravely repell them’ (Randolph,
                        <emph type="i">Honour Advanced</emph>, 4).<br/>Mydhope probably came from
                    Staffordshire. He appears in the accounts of the earl of Denbigh’s Army,
                    receiving monies on 17 Aug. 1643 and 23 Mar. 1644, but appears more as an
                    officer commanding a troop of horse in Staffordshire. In Dec. 1643 the
                    Staffordshire county committee noted that, as Mydhope’s troopers had brought
                    their horses with them when they came into the service of the county and had
                    lost them, Mydhope ‘who is now in service of the County in or about Leeke shall
                    have powre to take so many horses of Papists Delinquents or Malignants as to
                    horse the said Troopers’ (Pennington and Roots, <emph type="i">Committee at
                        Stafford</emph>, 14-5).<br/>In Dec. 1643, by when he had been promoted
                    Major, Mydhope was ordered to a rendezvous at Newcastle under Lyme and take
                    command of the county horse there and to march to Leek against the royalist
                    forces. Mydhope continued to serve in the county in 1644.<br/>With the coming of
                    peace in England Major Mydhope proposed bringing in a regiment of horse which he
                    had enlisted in Worcestershire, Warwickshire and Staffordshire for service in
                    Ireland, and on 12 Oct. 1646 the Committee of Both Houses for Irish Affairs
                    ordered commissions to be made out for Mydhope and his officers.<br/>Mydhope was
                    a signatory to the petition of reformado officers presented to parliament by Sir
                    Thomas Essex on 22 Mar. 1647. On 26 July 1647 he was one of the reformado
                    officers in the crowd which invaded parliament and forced it to reinstate
                    London’s Presbyterian militia committee.<br/>In 1656 Mydhope was living in a
                    house near Westminster Abbey.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Peacock,
                        <emph type="i">Army Lists</emph>, 54; Pennington and
                        Roots,<emph type="i"> Committee at Stafford</emph>, xxxiv, 8, 11, 14-5, 57,
                    108, 156, 316, 318; J. Randolph, <emph type="i">Honour Advanced</emph> (1643),
                    6; TNA, SP28/3/474, SP28/SP28/131, part 12, ff. 6, 17-8, SP28/11/59; <emph
                        type="i">CSP Ireland, 1633-1647</emph>, 520, 529; <emph type="i">JHL</emph>,
                    9.95-6, 10.213-6.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">Earl of
                        Essex; Lord Brooke; Staffordshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mynson, Robert</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Robert Mynson</emph><br/>In summer 1645, ensign to newly-promoted
                    Captain Walford in what had formerly been Godfrey Bosvile’s Warwick-based
                    regiment of foot.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: Spring, <emph type="i"
                        >Waller’s army</emph>, 31.<br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i"
                        >Warwickshire; Waller</emph></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
                <td>Mytton, Thomas</td>
                <td><emph type="b">Thomas Mytton </emph>(1596/7-1656)<br/>Son of Richard Mytton,
                    born into a prosperous Shrewsbury family, though with links over the border in
                    North Wales, he was tied by kinship and marriage to a network of gentry in
                    Shropshire and beyond, including Sir Thomas Myddelton, who was his
                    brother-in-law. During the first half of 1643 he was appointed by parliament to
                    various Shropshire committees, even though the county was at that time largely
                    in royalist hands. Empowered by the earl of Essex in spring 1643 to raise troops
                    in and around Shropshire, in practice though not in name he became parliament’s
                    commander-in-chief in the county. Working closely with Myddelton and Brereton,
                    he secured and fortified Wem in autumn 1643, and it became his principal base.
                    During 1644 he worked to dislodge the royalists from north Shropshire,
                    culminating in the capture of Shrewsbury early in 1645. However, Mytton also
                    fell foul of some of his colleagues on parliament’s Shropshire county committee,
                    who resented his frequent absence from the county and his alliance with external
                    figures such as the earl of Denbigh.<br/>In spring 1645 he succeeded Myddelton
                    as commander-in-chief of North Wales. He campaigned extensively in North Wales
                    in 1645-6 and again in autumn 1648 in putting down the royalist rising in
                    north-west Wales. He held office in both North Wales and Shropshire during the
                    first half of the 1650s and represented his native county in parliament in 1654.
                    He died in 1656.<br/><emph type="b">References</emph>: <emph type="i">Oxford
                        DNB.</emph><br/><emph type="b">Armies</emph>: <emph type="i">North Wales;
                        S</emph><emph type="i">hropshire</emph></td>
            </tr>
        </table>
    </section>
</report>
